<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The unlearned alchymist his antidote, or, A more full and ample explanation of the use, virtue and benefit of my pill, entituled, An effectual diaphoretick, diuretick, purgeth by sweating, urin. Whereunto is added sundry cures and experiences, with particular direction unto particular diseases and distempers; with a catalogue of peoples names, with their dwelings which have used and known the use of the same: also sundry plain and easie receits which the ingenious may prepare for their own health. By Richard Matthew, and are to be had at his house by the Lyons Den at the Tower, next Gate to the By-Ward.</title>
            <author>Mathews, Richard, d. 1661.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 246 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 88 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50275</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M1290</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R214133</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99826345</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99826345</idno>
            <idno type="VID">30746</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A50275)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 30746)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1763:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The unlearned alchymist his antidote, or, A more full and ample explanation of the use, virtue and benefit of my pill, entituled, An effectual diaphoretick, diuretick, purgeth by sweating, urin. Whereunto is added sundry cures and experiences, with particular direction unto particular diseases and distempers; with a catalogue of peoples names, with their dwelings which have used and known the use of the same: also sundry plain and easie receits which the ingenious may prepare for their own health. By Richard Matthew, and are to be had at his house by the Lyons Den at the Tower, next Gate to the By-Ward.</title>
                  <author>Mathews, Richard, d. 1661.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 143, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Joseph Leigh, at the upper end of Bazing-hall street, near the Naggs-head Tavern, and are to be sold together with this Pill, by Giles Calvert at the Black-spread Eagle at the west end of Pauls, and Livewell Chapman at the Crown in Popes-head-alley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Medicine, Magic, mystic, and spagiric --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:30746:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:30746:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlearned Alchymiſt</hi> HIS ANTIDOTE.</p>
            <p>OR, A more full and ample Explanation of the uſe, Vertue and benefit of my PILL, Entituled, <hi>An effectual</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Diaphoretick.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Diuretick.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <hi>purgeth by</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Sweating</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rin.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Whereunto is added Sundry Cures and Experiences, with particular direction unto particular diſeaſes and Diſtempers; with a Catalogue of peoples Names, with their dwellings which have uſed and known the uſe of the ſame: Alſo ſundry plain and eaſie Receits which the ingenious may prepare for their own health.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Richard Mathew,</hi> and are to be had at his houſe by the Lyons Den at the Tower, next Gate to the By-Ward.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London</hi> Printed, for <hi>Joſeph Leigh,</hi> at the upper end of Baz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-hall ſtreet, near the Naggs-head Tavern, and are to be ſold together with this Pill, by <hi>Giles Calvert</hi> at the Black-ſpread Eagle at the Weſt end of <hi>Pauls,</hi> And <hi>Livewell Chapman</hi> at the Crown in Popes-head-alley, 1660.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:30746:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:30746:2"/>
            <p>To all that are ſick, under Pains, Aches, Gripings, divers diſeaſes, Surfeitings, Obſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, Conſumptions, of what kind ſoever and whoſoever, but more eſpecially unto all ſuch of them that fear the Lord in truth and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightneſs, and of theſe eſpecially ſuch as are poor and have no money, <hi>Ric. Mathew,</hi> your brother and companion in the Kingdom and patience of Jeſus Chriſt, humbly Dedicates this his little book, together with his work and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor, with what is his devoted to your ſervice.</p>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is meet of good right that this my Book ſhould be Dedicated unto you, who daily finds the power and vertue of my Pill whereof I have ſpoken; let all the world ſet themſelves againſt it as they pleaſe, I know your experience will vindicate it, and verily if my Pill have not deſerved it from your
<pb facs="tcp:30746:3"/>hands, I will ſpeak not a word for it, but what ever in this book hath paſt me, let it for ever ſtand for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and I do atteſt not onely to you all, but all the world, that if I he deceived concerning the true worth and power of my Pills, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily it is you that hath deceived me, my conſcience bearing me witneſs I have not added unto theſe reports which you have brought me, but have with much ſobriety left out much which would have heightned the power &amp; worth of my Pill, but I am aſſured from my own knowledge and daily ſight and hearing, that things of like nature are done by it daily, bleſſed be God, and therefore I know there is no deceit in the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: Receive then I pray you this little book into your protection, and ſpeak as you have found, and ſpeak that which is true, I deſire no more, I know that is ſufficient,
<pb facs="tcp:30746:3"/>for the trueth is ſtrong, and no force can keep him in bonds whom truth acquits; it were better I were not then it were not my portion.</p>
            <p>It is neither power nor great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, nor humane Art, nor Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that I fly unto for Patronage, only the clear and unbyaſed witneſs of truth, which can be in no other mouths then ſuch of you, the authors of all thoſe ſeveral reports, cures, and wonders I have ſet down in this book, moſt of which my own eys were ſpectators, &amp; conſequently witneſſes of their verity and truth, neither am I unfurniſhed of as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more which here is not ſet down, but theſe have ſpent much paper for me to write, and much of your pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience to read, and he that will not believe at the ſound of this Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet, but ſhuts his ears, reſolved not to hear, this man will not hear if I had ſet down five times as many.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:30746:4"/>But unto the two ſecond ſort un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to whom I tender this dedication, <hi>viz.</hi> the faithful that are yet on earth, but their treaſure in heaven, and their hearts where their trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure is; that at the preſent if need be are in heavineſs thorow many fold temptations, ſickneſſes, pains, aches, and weakneſſes of body I do in a more eſpecial manner dedicate my book, ſelf work and labor of love unto you, who is your brother and companion, and with you have born the chaſtening of the Lord, I know your happineſs and feel it and am made and infranchized a Citizen and fellow ſervant with you, and have labored thorow Chriſt and have not fainted, and now knowing your happineſs do ranke my ſelf with you as being made partaker of like pretious faith, and indeed deſire above all other to be made manifeſt and
<pb facs="tcp:30746:4"/>known unto you? I know although I am a ſtranger unto you as to this body and this world, yet I have ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual feeling and feaſting with you, in and from that abundance of end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs joys freely beſtowed in the blood of Chriſt, and truely our fellowſhip is with the Father and with that Son of his love, whoſe blood clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth us from all our iniquities, and bleſſed be God who hath helped me thorow all kind of ſnares and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptations, to the end I might by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience know his ſalvation, his power and goodneſs; and this is my triumphing joy, that my father is pleaſed to let me live to comfort and help many, and thanks be given unto him, there is but few days paſs me without the happy tidings of ſaving the life of one poor crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture or other, I ſpeak as a man, and in this judge by mans reaſon. And now my beloved brethren as I have
<pb facs="tcp:30746:5"/>freely received ſo I freely give, you above all other I thirſt to ſerve both in body and ſpirit, my maſter hath returned upon my head the fruit of my labor, which indeed hath been much and long, and wherefore have I been always beaten down by ſickneſs and weakneſs of body, but that I might be improved (as I have been improved) for your ſervice and advantages, of which indeed you may make a bold challenge, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire the ſame as your juſt right and propriety.</p>
            <p>But unto the third ſort now I ſpeak, <hi>viz.</hi> you which fear the Lord in truth of heart, and are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his fatherly chaſtening of pains, ſickneſſes, and bodily preſſures, and are poor as to the things of this world; and wherefore is it but that in being here you might not be to your ſelves as men or to this world as this world, you are not poor, but
<pb facs="tcp:30746:5"/>you are rich, riches that faideth not away, made rich thorow him that became poor that he might make many rich; my brethren be without carefulneſs or fear, becauſe tis your fathers pleaſure to give you a Kingdom, a Kingdom that remains to eternity, eternally in the heavens, you will poſſeſs it at that his appearing when you ſhall appear with him in heaven, glory that cannot be ſhaken; and if your earthly tabernacle periſh daily, is it not the Miniſter of joy, foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as it tends to no other end but to haſt you to reſt; now is the time of your labor, labor in fruit-bearing, herein is your Father glorified (that in and againſt the ſtrongeſt wreſtlings of this world and of your own corruptions, and Satanical tentations and deluſion) that you bring forth much fruit, to the end his fruit may remain in you,
<pb facs="tcp:30746:6"/>and his power reſt upon you; you know in all your griefs and ailes, he is Joy, Peace, Reſt, get then to reſt, ceaſe from man, for wherein is he to be truſted, you ſelf and all ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, your own works as God did from his, enter the bleſſed reſt, holy Sabbath thorow Chriſts attonement, thorow whom and in whom we are compleat and perfect, for ſhame be ſilent, the Lord comes into his holy temple, your bodies are the temple of the living God, his houſe and habitation you are, he daigns to ſupp and dine with you, and is with you and in you, ſtand faſt then in that liberty wherewith he hath made you free; take heed of har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kening to fleſh and blood, be not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangled with the yoak of bondage to fear again, if you touch your bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den with your arm, you muſt needs faint, but if you throw it on him he will ſuſtain you; he bore our
<pb facs="tcp:30746:6"/>ſickneſſes, the chaſtiſement of our peace was upon him, and by his ſtripes we are healed, be like him who opened not his mouth, although the Lord laid on him the iniquity of us all; ſickneſſes &amp; poverty is not the greateſt of evils, nay they in their depth with devine love and preſence are joyous &amp; glorious; I never found greater joy and peace, and conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion then when I was in the greateſt pain and bitterneſs, when as to this world there was little hope of life, then was their life in beauty and ſtrength, you of all other are moſt bleſſed and happy, becauſe the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal crown and weight of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and glory is prepared for you.</p>
            <p>What ſhall I ſay unto you my dearly beloved brethren with whom life and glory dwelleth. O my heart is pained for you, yea my ſoul and ſpirit within me is ſet on fire with love, care, deſire, indeavor
<pb facs="tcp:30746:7"/>how I might be moſt manifested unto you, to bear all your diſtreſſes if it were poſſible for me, but alas it is a ſmall thing I am able to do, but I will tell you Jeſus Chriſt will make his croſs and yoak eaſie and light unto you, go to him he is the fountain, all fulneſs is in him, and he freely diſtributes without upbraiding, yea he is perfectly able to ſave all that come to God by him; and as for me his poor ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, I beſeech you pray that I may be found faithful in my Steward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, improving his manifold gifts unto his ends, and therefore in his name and fear, and in diſcharge of my duty unto him, and out of faithful and true ſimpathy and fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low-feeling with you; I do there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in his name and fear invite all that is poor, having no mony and fears the Lord in truth of heart, and is ſick, and in pains and Aches of
<pb facs="tcp:30746:7"/>bodie that they would come and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive at my hand this Pill, or what elſe the Lord hath given me for their health freely for Christ ſake without mony or reward, prove I pray you and aſſay whether I be the man or no that I here would be taken to be, yea come once and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain as your diſtreſs requires, onely as I am a man hide not your ſelf and condition from me, and I hope ſtill in him in whom I have always hoped I ſhall not be left without either a heart or wherewith to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh them, that in the name and fear of God come unto me, intreat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you to joyn with it your faith and prayer for a bleſſing; looking on it as means of Gods ordaining for your help and comfort, then do I not fear a good and bleſſed ſucceſs in the uſe of the means which the Lord hath put in my hands for your eaſe, healing, and benefit.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="list">
            <pb facs="tcp:30746:8"/>
            <head>Certain choice Receits contained in this Book.</head>
            <list>
               <item>The true preparation of the Oyl of Amber three ſeveral ways.</item>
               <item>The Oyl and Ballſom of the Pine-tree, commonly called Tar.</item>
               <item>An unvaluable purge univerſal of Antimony and Sca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of Cream or Chriſtals of Tartar, with their Correction preparation, doſſe and uſe.</item>
               <item>The true preparation of Crocus Martis.</item>
               <item>The preparation of Sugar of Saturn.</item>
               <item>The true preparation of the Eſſence of <hi>Venus,</hi> or <hi>Ens Veneris.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The true preparation of the Salt of Mars.</item>
               <item>The true preparation of the Sympathetical powder late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly treated of by Sir <hi>Kenelm Digby.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>An Antidote againſt all diſeaſes, Surfeits and infections.</item>
               <item>To make and prepare the drink now in uſe called Coffee.</item>
               <item>To make a choice Cordial Sirrup of Black-Cherries.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THou art deſired to look with a favorable eye upon thoſe faults which thou maiſt meet with in this Book, and to Correct them with thy pen. If there be any that does make the ſence ſeem harſh to thee, thou art cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſly required to amend them.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:30746:8"/>
            <head>An effectual
<list>
                  <item>Diaphoretick</item>
                  <item>Diuretick</item>
               </list>
purgeth by
<list>
                  <item>Sweating</item>
                  <item>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rine.</item>
               </list>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Pill is a Corrector of all Vegeta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive poiſons.</hi> This that I have written is true, although ſome there are which takes it in foul ſcorn that I ſhould profeſs that power, as to Correct <hi>opium</hi> and they themſelves cannot; but let ſuch contentious Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors know, that the Gentleman is yet in very good health that drank 200. grains of <hi>opium</hi> at one draught, which was of my correcting, <hi>So that if it be taken after any portion vomative or laxative, it will not work at all; or when any portion works over violently, it forthwith ſtops it by reaſon of its cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rective power:</hi> This alſo as far as my experience hath taught me, is true, and if any liſt let them make further proof; <hi>In like manner it Corrects all poiſons in mans body from head to feet;</hi> By conſtant experience we find its working ſo various and ſtrange that we can believe no leſs, for although to all appearance people that are alike troubled, yet will it vomit ſome, purge others, and make others ſweat out of meaſure, and others purge ſtrangely by Urine, and others as ſtrangely ſend
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:30746:9"/>forth Rhums and Fleam at the mouth; and ſome others it may be none of all theſe, but will break out all over, and ſundry other ways as nature hath provided to great wonder, which people when they are well, tell us how ſtrangely it wrought with them. Unto God only be given all the praiſe for his mercies, it ſufficeth that peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple finde relief in their diſtreſs; ſo that indeed we do clearly ſee it doth ranſack whole nature of what temper, complexion, or conſtitution ſoever, and finding out what it is that is noctious unto it, finds out one way or other as nature is moſt prompt to adminiſter relief, and according unto our experience it is ever conſtant unto a conſtant mind, and moſt certain it is that many fooliſhly out of a fond conceit, becauſe this Pill hath operated contrary unto what they before hand have ſuppoſed, have left its uſe to their great hurt and damage; and at this day (out of ſome ſuch phantaſtical humor neglecting it) lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh in their pains and griefs, theſe lending their credulous ears unto the envious which nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther know nor underſtand the thing they ſpeak evil of, but thou which wilt believe thy expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, will find that if thy grief lies in thy head, any part of it, thou ſhalt be ſure to find it awakened, nay oft times when men doth not think that their grief lieth there by reaſon it may be that thy illneſs proceeds of ſome old Cold or Surfeit, or Bruſe, ſo as thou haſt forgotten it, this Pill will begin at the root of thy grief, and if of Wind, it ſtrangely followeth it up and down the body of man till it be turned out; or if it be
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:30746:9"/>ſome inward breach or ſoreneſs, or Impoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hums it by reaſon of its power from fixt Salts doth break, and by reaſon of its Balſamical vertue, doth heal above belief, ſo that as people inform us of great pains and grief they have had for ſome years, till by this Pill ſometimes ſtinking Matter, and ſometimes ſtinking blood hath been ſent forth which hath been infinitely beyond my skill to help, but God hath bleſſed the uſe of this Pill to ſave the lives of many ſo grieved bleſſed be his name, and if the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect be amongſt the Uritures, Kidnes, Rains or Bladder, then the effects by Urine is as admirable much beyond our reaſon, for it ſometimes ſends out ſtuff of divers collours, and ſometimes but of one collour like ſnot and like jaggs of cloth, jaggs of paper, and of divers collours mixed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and ſometimes ſwiming on the Surface, and ſometimes lying in the bottom; and ſo alſo hath brought out many Stones, many of which we have to ſhew, which people that voyded them upon the taking of the Pills have brought us; alſo Gravel in abundance, both red and other collours, which it doth by its power from fixed Salts, and the true preparing the Spirit of Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentine, and I do atteſt to all men, that I am ſix moneths in preparing the Spirit of Turpentine for this Pill; and let all men know aſſuredly, it is not nor cannot be ripe for this Pill under, and therefore thus duely prepared, I do believe a high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Ballſom is not in the world both inwardly and outwardly; God grant I may uſe it to his glory and peoples good, for we find it ſo potent in
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:30746:10"/>cleanſing all Windineſs, Slimineſs, Stone, or Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel, and in caſe of Flux of blood, running of Rains, and the like, or Flux of ſcouring, I think the like is not to be found, for by reaſon of the mixion of forceable Vegetatives, it doth ſo ſweetly ſtop all bleeding beyond belief, although it be either by Fundament, or by Urine, or by Mouth, as in Conſumptions, or at Noſe, it forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with ſtops it as ſoon as it is warm in their Bellies; if it be grief of the Joynts, Ach of Bones, Pains of the Feet, as the Gout in the Feet, or the run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Gout, or that which is called the Kings-evil, by that time a Pill can be warm in their belly, the patient will be ſenſible of eaſe, and to the praiſe of God I ſpeak it, many of every Sex and Age that have not been able to feed or help them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, or ſtir a limb in their beds, with the uſe of this Pill are now in health and ſet at liberty; there would be no end of ſpeaking, and yet but what is true, the wonderful wonders that God hath done by this Pill both inwardly and outwardly, and if thoſe take it who have Conſumptions with ſore Coughing, alſo thoſe that wheeſe with ſhortneſs of Breath with Coughing; I ſay there are many of theſe alive thanks be given to God who comfortably injoy themſelves, which to the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of man would never a held out, and many of theſe perfectly cured and ſo remain, which indeed is more then in reaſon we might have expected, for according to the opinion of the ableſt in Phyſick, theſe diſtempers proceed from a debelity in nature, and therefore not cure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, but God hath ſhewed his power and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:30746:10"/>to many, that there doth not appear the leaſt ſign of a diſtemper, ſo that in a reaſonable time both Cough and Rhume is quite gone and Breath at will: I am loath to recite particulars, and yet give no more but the very truth, becauſe I know many will hardly believe it (&amp; yet I am conſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed here to give ſome inſtances) for I ſpeak not this without witneſs, thanks be to God, many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds about <hi>London</hi> will give teſtimony of the truth written, with thankſgiving unto Almighty God who hath ſtrengthened and opened their Breaſts when they were almoſt brought unto the gates of death, God bleſſing this Pill to them for their reviving, thanks be given unto God for all his unſpeakable gifts. I had a Maid-ſervant that from a child had a ſore Cough in ſuch extremity, and I feared oft ſhe would never get Breath a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, it had ſuch violence upon her; and ſhe ſaid it would never be cured, it was natural unto her, and that her mother died thereof, I cauſed her to take of theſe Pills, as well for my own quietneſs as her cure, ſhe did ſo diſturbe me in the night ſeaſon; I gave her but little ones and gave them time, ſhe never lay hour for them, but roſe eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry morning all Winter, and did perform her duty in the houſe without interruption, and I think it was half a year or near before it was quite gone, and in that time it took it ſo perfectly away, as to my knowledge I heard her not Cough in half a a year more, nay not while ſhe was in my houſe.</p>
            <p>A man ſo afflicted with ſhortneſs of Breath and Coughing, as did exceed moſt that I have heard
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:30746:11"/>of, and he ſends to me for Pills, which he took, and with his own mouth telleth us, that for ſeven years he was ſo grievouſly afflicted therwith, that he could not all the Winter ſeaſon lie down in his bed, and if he had aſſayed to do it, then he ſhould ſtrangle, and of a ſuddain ſtart up and ſtretch up his arms above his head to get paſſage for his Breath again, which with difficulty he recovered; ſaid he unto us the firſt Pill that ever I took of yours, I laid me down and ſlept ſweetly all the night, at which I and my Wife greatly admiring, praiſed God, as alſo we did with him, and that it ſeemed more ſtrange, he ſaid he Coughed not all the night, nor was he ſenſible of any ſtraightneſs of Breath all the night; and this man remains ſo well, that to my knowledge he doth not ſpend ſo much as one quarter of an ounce in a quarter of a year. It grieves my heart as I go up and down the ſtreets to hear the people Cough and wheeſe, holding their ſides with ſhort breathing, when God hath put in my hand ſo great a bleſſing for mankind, and ye will not make uſe of it many that have knowledge of it, and if I ſhould go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to perſwade them to it, ye will imagine I do it for my own advantage; there are ſome that have much to anſwer for diſſwading well-mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed People againſt it to their hurt; I pray God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give them, it is evident that they themſelves can do nothing in this caſe, but are juſt like the dogg in the manger, that will eat no hay himſelf, nor ſuffer the horſe to eat it; notwithſtanding a a volume might be written of its power and effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy which is true and real touching its pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:30746:11"/>help in the caſes aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe for all kind of Scowrings and Fluxes whatſoever, and therefore it is truely ſaid, that it is a Corrector of all poiſons within mans bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy from his head unto his feet.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And helpeth the patient to cure, except it be over long decocted that it became Cronical, yet then it gives perfect eaſe;</hi> The cures which hath been perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in this four or five years laſt paſt, are too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny here to recite; I ſhall give you a few inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, ſuch as came at the preſent into my mind as I was a writing, by which the reſt may be the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter gueſſed at.</p>
            <p>A woman that is now well and in health (rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to bear teſtimony if there were occaſion) comes to me and preſſed me to conſider her condition, which indeed was very lamentable and ſad, for one of her leggs was all out or very near as bigg as my waſt, with ſundry ſtinking Fiſtulad Ulcers running in it, which I was not able to look on, this legg in growing into this condition, ſhe told me was ten or eleven years, and all that time ſhe could get no help but had ſpent what ſhe was able in vain; I gave her of my Pills at a ſmall rate conſidering her condition, and willed her to prove whether there were likelihood of help by them, to apply nothing outwardly, but to waſh it with her own water or with Brandewine, ſhe accordingly did, keeping it warm as ſhe ought to do, and ſo gave my Pills time, which ſhe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly did, and at firſt they did not onely ſweat her out of meaſure, but did throw out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of filth out of meaſure at the Ulcers
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:30746:12"/>that did greatly wet her bed in the night; ſhe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to be fearful and I perſwaded her to patience, whereon ſhe continues her order, and when they had thrown out all that was fit to be thrown out, then began the bigneſs of her legg to abate, and ſo with abundance of eaſe ſweetly took down her legg and healed thoſe Ulcers one after ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther unto her great wonder, and when ſhe was near whole, and had but one hole in her legg open, and the greatneſs of it gone, and that legg no bigger then the other, ſome of her Goſſips perſwaded her, if ſhe did not keep one of the Ulcers open, that ſhe ſhould dye; I think ſhe was near ſix moneths in bringing her legg unto this condition, and then ſhe left off, that ſo the hole left might run ſtill, and ſo it did, and by degrees her legg begun to ſwell again, and I on the other ſide wondred what was become of my cuſtomer, for my councel to her was, that if the Pills heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them all perfectly ſhe was a happy woman and ought to give God thanks for it; and further that if they were all whole ſhe would yet continue taking of them for at leaſt three moneths, that her nature might get ſtrength and find other pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers then at her Ancles, conſidering for how long time her nature had been debelitated and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther emantuaries found which nature did not or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain, but ſhe forſaking this advice as is above ſaid relapſed, and finding that her legg began as faſt to go back as when ſhe uſed the Pills it did to heal, ſhe fell to work again and followed the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the Pill as ſhe ought and thorow Gods mercy perfected the cure, as is to be ſeen at this
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:30746:12"/>day, and now it may be ſhe ſends for a quarter of an ounce in three or four moneths, unto God who ſheweth mercy to the poor that put their truſt in him, be all praiſe and glory for ever amen.</p>
            <p>There came unto me two or three men of good quality, and brought with them a Country man about twenty four years old extream lame and weak of the Palſie, ſo ſore that he could not but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton himſelf, nor put on his clothes nor ſeed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, I gave him ſix Pills with a little Oyl of Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of my own drawing, he never came again ſo much as to return thanks (I hope he was thankful to God) a while after I met one of the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men that brought him to me in Abchurch-lane end in Cannon Street by meer accident, he gave me many thanks for my love unto his friend, and told me that he was gone down into the Country again very well about his buſineſs, and had ſtrength and uſe of his hands and limbs, to his great joy and comfort, praiſed be God.</p>
            <p>I will now recite you hear another, I think as ſtrange a cure as any hath been done in this latter age of the world; and truely had I not done it my ſelf as a weak inſtrument, I ſhould very hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly believed it, and truely I will not vary one tittle from the naked truth to the beſt of my un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding and knowledge, and it was upon a Inns of Court Gentleman, that was once of the Kings Army a Colonel, he being deſperately ſick of a very foul and deſperate diſeaſe, and had took many Pills, wherein much Quickſilver as is ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed had been put, but procured nothing but
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:30746:13"/>ſigns of death, that his meſſenger told me he never looked to come off his bed, a bold woman came to me without any guiſe or collour, and told me plainly how it was with him, and I not much caring for ſuch kind of Patient, gave her about ſix Pills and ſent her away, and bid her as he lik<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them to ſend to me again, but ſhe ſoon came again with theſe words in her mouth, the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman ſaith that he never meet with a honeſt man till now, and doth intreat you that you would not ſlight him in this ſad condition, but go forward with him, by what you have done al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready he is of good hope of ſuddain cure, for by and by after one of your Pills were in his belly, the ſore racking of limbs, and knawing of his Bowels did ceaſe, and that he is greatly refreſhed with them, I ſent him more of the ſame, with order how to uſe it more effectually; ſhortly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſhe came again for more of the ſame, and then ſhe did aſſure me that my Pills and drink which he took, had ſuch wonderful effects upon him which did almoſt fright them, but that he was hearty and eat his meat, they ſhould have feared, for all his hair came off from all parts of his whole body, and alſo his whole ſkin came off all over his whole body, and alſo all his nails, both on his hands and feet came off from him without any violence fell off of themſelves; I do proteſt as in the ſight of God what is ſaid is true, to the beſt of my underſtanding, and about three weeks after I began with him or thereabout, this Gentleman came to me and ſhewed me his naked body, which I was loath he ſhould, and not one hair upon
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:30746:13"/>him, but a freſh ſkin as of a young childe, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed he looked ſhotten and wan, as one that had been ſick, and ſo he had; he told me he was as well as ever he was in all his life, and that which made me more to wonder, was that the nails of his hands did then begin to peep out like the little white that is at the root of our nails. I may not handſomely ſay any more, I bleſs God that hath guided me to ſpeak what is very true, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but what is true.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Over long cocted that it become cronical:</hi> Thorow length of time that humor commonly called peccant, or Acrimonious, or Tartarous, although its beginning may be but ſome ordinary cold, yet being long neglected, and many noctious humors therby ingendred through long circulation 'twixt heart and brain; theſe two being the extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of heat and cold, I ſay with ſubjection that theſe humors 'twixt heat and cold, the heat of the heart which cauſeth them to aſcend, and the cold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the brain cauſeth them to deſcend; this work continued, thoſe Rhums muſt needs grow fixt, and conſidering that the ſalt of nature wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly joyns, as ſalt would be in water as his proper veſſel; hence ariſeth thoſe groſs diſeaſes, called Cronical, ſo called becauſe they are out of the reach of Gallenecal Phyſick; every common Chimiſt doth know that long ſublimation or cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culation doth fix the ſubject, ſo that diſeaſes of this gender are for the moſt part uncurable: and let all be warned betimes, when their head and teeth ake, and Rhums in their eyes, they ſlight it becauſe they to appearance do amend, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:30746:14"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:30746:14"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:30746:15"/>indeed doth, and too many fall into this gulf which doth not ſo appear it may be in ſeven years after, by that time their Rhums get a crown upon their head, they grow ſurly and appear in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers manners, as firſt ſore pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ns in the head, then the evil in the eyes, beware of blindneſs, then out goes the teeth with great pain, or elſe when this humor becomes more groſs, then out they go with the Scurvey; then beware the Lungs, it is now grown ſharp and corroding, then look unto the Region of the Bladder and Kidnes, and all the griefs that attend them; but if it do eſcape theſe, then look well to your hips for the Sciati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca, and if you eſcape that then beware the feet: I know well that <hi>Paracelſus</hi> preſcribes a fourfold ground or Radix of all diſeaſes, but it doth not bend with my brain, I think it all lieth hear and touch one and touch all, and let that Medicine be produced in the world, and appear that is like unto my Pill that will both eaſe and cure theſe, ſome and all of theſe, at leaſt conſider what I have ſaid and what further ſhall be ſaid con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning it, it hath pritty well ſpoke for it ſelf.</p>
            <p>There are hundreds other diſeaſes which all hange on this root, for as all diſeaſes take their beginning of a Surfeit of one kind or other, ſo do they all finiſh in a Conſumption, called death of one kind or other, and their variations are from the ſeveral complections and temperatures of men and their mixture, as Sanguin, Choller, Melancholly, Flegmatick, their temperature whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hot, cold, moiſt, or dry, and the ſeveral com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poundings
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:30746:15"/>of theſe, all which paſſeth my brains, I do not know them for my ſelf, and therefore undoubtedly cannot know them for any other, neither do I take it upon me, but my work teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth me to know that long circulation doth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce fixing, and when fixt, its effects are more or leſs ſtrong or weak, much or little according unto the degrees thereof.</p>
            <p>A man is therefore truely called <hi>Microcoſme,</hi> a little world, a world indeed of wonders; <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith ſpeaking of man, God hath ſet the world in his heart, and who can find it out? And in his Book of Wiſdom, where he promiſeth to teach us all wiſdom, and the beginning of it, and whence it is, he telleth us ſomething of his one beginning that he was born of a woman as all others are, and more he teacheth but of that nature, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he whiſpereth that man is the ſeat or ſubject of true wiſdom, which you may read at your lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</p>
            <p>A late but expert Philoſopher telleth us in one of his Riddles, that he had been all his life time ſailing twixt the Artick and the Antartick Poles, which in another place he calls his mouth and his belly; and who is ſo wiſe as to ſee the myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of hunger, and what is it that hath power to ſatisfie its draught or atraction, and when hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger is ſatisfied, what the operation of nature is, untill it came unto the Antartick or Expulſive Pole, how forcibly nature will throw out the feculence, after curious nature hath drawn and elaborated the ſubject, and ſeparated the quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſence; ſo that this little world hangeth up on
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:30746:16"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:30746:16"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:30746:17"/>the two Poles, atractive and expulſive; now then if there be a man in the world that knoweth himſelf, then would I ask what that man is igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of; but if thou couldeſt as it were go out of thy ſelf, and could diligently converſe with thine one Intelligences, and the opperation of the threefold world in one, <hi>viz.</hi> Celeſtial, Intelligable and Terreſtrial or Beaſtial, mixt with infernal thorow the fall of man. I ſay the vaſt Latitude and extent of man in all reſpects, thou wouldſt find him ſuch a miſtery as hath whole nature con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in him, and conſequently the variety of his Ailes are accordingly, whence very many take their root from the mind, and very many from ſecret Sympathy and Antepathy, which with a witneſs ſheweth the preſumption of Piſpot Doctors, nay that man or hundredth man may be truely called wiſe that is able with their tongues to give a true Character of their one Ailes which I ſpeak it boldly, not one of a hundred is able to do, and God knows they are adminiſtred to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly; all which duely conſidered, thou wilt ſee reaſon and cauſe why the Ancients ſpent their time in ſearching out Medicines Univerſal.</p>
            <p>I have therefore from the ſerious conſideration of the premiſes, wholly ſet my ſelf unto the ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Hemetick Phyſick, and that is wholly ſet on two things, Univerſality for ſafty when wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly adminiſtred and univerſality in opperation; and let it not ſeem to thee as a new or ſtrange thing; this is evident in the Books of the Ancients as the height of their ſkill, and nothing more frequent in all their writings then receipts of Medicin
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:30746:17"/>Univerſal, as all that read can bear witneſs, and if I ſhould give you their receipts, it would ſwell this little Book unto a great Volum.</p>
            <p>I do affirm unto all men that there is nothing contained in all the three kingdoms of nature, <hi>viz.</hi> Mineral Vegetative and Animal, but that it doth contain in it ſelf Medicin univerſal; ſuppoſe what you will in the world, if he grant that which no man can deny, <hi>viz.</hi> That all things created by the bleſſed Trinity are made of three, Salt, Sulphur and Mercury, then take I pray you what individual you pleaſe, ſuppoſe it to be a Vegetable any Herb of any kind for the Arcanus or Spirit of Life, is the ſame in all things, and ſeparate by a natural proceſs, theſe three ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, give them their due cleanſing, <hi>viz.</hi> for the Salt give a natural calcination, then diſolve fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter coagulate, and again calcin repeating theſe ſo long untill they will yeild unto thee no more fecis; but be ſure thy calcination do not excite too much, for thy Salt doth conſiſt alſo of three ſorts, a fixed Salt, and a Nitrous, and a Volitil, and if thou ſtir him too much be ſure thou wilt give wing unto the Vollotil; this wiſely prepared is a great treaſure, be as careful and as natural in the cleanſing and rectifying of thy Sulphur, and likewiſe of thy Mercury, each one according unto his kind and being cleanſed according to Art, then conjoyn them according unto the poiſe of nature, then feed them by <hi>Vulcans</hi> hand, but let not his Bellows be to bigg untill all reunite a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, and do fix and make it lively; this work being finiſhed, I do demand of all men what this
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:30746:18"/>wanteth of a univerſal Medicin or fifth eſſence: Now that Salt, Oyl, and Water will really be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a body, is evident for the mediation of Oyl, or Fat, or Sulphur binds or brings together the two extreams, <hi>viz.</hi> Salt and Water, the one being fixed of kind, and the other being Volitil, the ſweet Mediation of Sulphur brings theſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treams into unity, and this is apparently ſeen in a vulgar working of ſope, and although that working be violent and unnatural, yet is there ſuch a conjugal imbracing each other performed and that in few hours as would puſle a good Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt to undo truely for ſome moneths, if it can ever be done at all, it is not ſables I ſpeak of, nor ſcraped out of books without reaſon, but is the daily work and labor of my hand with reaſon upon experience that enforceth me to believe this matter, and I have ſpoke the more unto it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe many that want not ignorance do laugh at a univerſal Medicin, but I am upon good grounds bound to believe that all and every thing in the world hath it, yea the moſt diſpiſed creature, that the moſt high God hath created and made, and further I freely grant the leaſt or worſt of things that have being, doth carry ſo much of the Wiſdom of its Creator in it, that the more I have and do labor to know its extent, the more I am at a loſs, yea indeed I become the more a fool, confeſſing freely that I know nothing as I ought to know it, and if of creatures thus to ſpeak in general, then what ſhall we ſay of the moſt choiſeſt creature, man; this then I do certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly take alſo for granted, that there is no ſickneſs
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:30746:18"/>or Aile attends the body of man, but his cure is of and from his one body, he always hath it with him if he knew how and what and when to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply it to himſelf, either of his ſubſtance or of his excrements.</p>
            <p>From hence may the miſerable eſtate of poor man be diſcerned, who of all creatures when he is ſick is the moſt helpleſs, miſerable, full of tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting pains, and as ignorant of his one cure or what ſhould cure him, for men in health think not on ſickneſs untill they be ſick; but ſpend their time in the beaſtiality and ſordid covetings after the things and pleaſures of this life, blinded in ſin and drenched with Surfeiting, either abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Gods creatures or themſelves in inordinate deſire after them, ſo that they neither know God in his word nor in his works, nor them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, or what is good to help them; one word further which ſets out mans miſery, and I hope may awaken ſome to amendment of life, I would ask, why is it a man ſuffers ſuch intollerable pain in ſickneſs and death more then a beaſt: I will give two reaſons for it, firſt the intireneſs of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures compoſition together with the length of time in his maturation, for things where in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hath but a weak and ſhort time of coction ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits of a eaſie and ſuddain diſſolution or ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, every one in every thing diſcerneth this, but man hath the moſt perfect com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of any thing that hath a animal life with ſence and feeling, and add to that the great time he requires before he come up un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his full ſtrength, this muſt needs require ſome
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:30746:19"/>hard knocks in the diſſolving as well as it did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive time and ſtrength in cocting. Secondly, that which is more then this, is the force of his imagination and apprehenſion both of death and of Gods diſpleaſure for ſin, all which doth make him ſo mightily ſenſible that the terrors of death is oft born before it come, as in <hi>Agag</hi> King of the <hi>Amalekites,</hi> a word to a wiſe man is ſufficient, becauſe this is not my proper diſcourſe intended in this place.</p>
            <p>What hath been ſaid, let it admoniſh all men as they tender the wellfare of body or ſoul, not to be unfurniſhed for either, aſſuring that they will not be hurt by true knowledge, and do therefore conclude that the Medicin that ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens and comforts the Vital Spirits, fortifies the heart, and purgeth and cleanſeth the blood, is a Univerſal Medicin, for what temper or quality aboundeth and exceeds the poiſe of nature, that is, he an enemy unto, as if a man have a Feavor, that I ſuppoſe will be granted to be too much fire, he is a perfect enemy of that, or if Wind, drives away that; theſe things are common with me performed with my Pill, judge of it as you pleaſe, &amp; I ſhall count it ſufficient thorow Gods rich mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and goodneſs, frequently to cure and fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently to eaſe pains &amp; Ailes counted uncureable.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It being tak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> granted that all diſeaſes for the moſt part proceed from a poiſonous quality Hetrogenial to na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: If any man liſt to deny or diſpute this, I would gladly he informed by him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>For Agues, if this Pill be taken in reaſonable doſs two hours be ore the fit, and a glaſs of Sack or Ale drank
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:30746:19"/>after it,</hi> That is to ſay, ſo much as the Patient finds by good experience that they can bare and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve this order two hours before the fit comes, take two Pills, &amp; in the intrim of fits take one Pill.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Patient being put into a warm bed diſpoſed for ſweat, at three tim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s taking it for the moſt part, is ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute cure, let it be never ſo malignant,</hi> The Pill working by ſweat principally in this diſeaſe, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires a warm bed, and that two hours before the fit, becauſe by that time the Pills will contribute their vertue all over the body, ſo that inſtead of having a cold and ſhaking fit, the patient will be a ſleep and in a fine ſweat, provided that you have given a right doſs, that is ſo much as the ſtrength of the patient can bare, &amp; the diſeaſe doth require, it hath fallen out oft that one Pill alone hath cured an Ague, and it falls out that ſome that are compounded with other diſeaſes, will not be cured with twenty, yet all do feel their benefit at the very firſt taking of it, which will give them incouragement ſufficient to perſevere and give it time, if it be ſo that the diſeaſe require it, for you may take notice that the Ague is but the beginning or forerunner of many other diſeaſes, far worſe then it ſelf, as Dropſie, Scurvy, Jaundies, and ofttimes Conſumptions, yet thorow the bounty of God, I have helped many far gone with all theſe with this Pill, and very little other things to help; it is alſo to be noted how irregu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar many are in the uſe of means which will nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther give themſelves time nor reſt, but finding their fit at the firſt and ſecond taking to be gone will no longer be ruled, and will take no more,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:30746:20"/>and thus in ſix or eight dayes their fits come again whereas indeed they had need to take them at leaſt fourteen dayes after the fits are gone, that nature may get ſtrength, and the blood thorow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly purged, and ſome that will not be ruled, have come again and again, and urged their buſineſs permitted them not, but ſome of theſe by that time the Winter have come unto its depth, their buſineſs has permitted them to dye, I do make mention of this to ſecond my admonition, and I do warn and charge, that although the firſt Pill that you take to your thinking, hath conquered your Ague, that you notwithſtanding expect it, as ſoon as the power of the Pill is wrought out, except you ſupply with another, and that for ſometime you may fear its coming again; there is not any caſe wherein people have more abuſed themſelves and me in my credit and my Pill, then in this buſineſs of Agues, all which might be eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly helped if people would follow home as they ſhould, but let him that is diſpoſed to play with his Ague, aſſure himſelf his Ague will not play with him; neither let him think that it will be ſet going with one violent portion, for experience telleth thoſe that ſo doing they do but drive themſelves into the Dropſie, as extream vomit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting with unknown powders, not but that a vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit is rational and neceſſary with other means; there would be no end for me to write particulars the cures have been ſo many, for many hundreds have been cured herewith, and many have helped their friends with my Pills, whoſe faces I never
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:30746:20"/>ſaw, and they are a living teſtimony of the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of my Pills.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The like for all kind of Feavors, onely in ſtead of Sack drink white wine, but if the Feavor have got head before this Pill be taken, and the patient weak and wanteth the benefit of nature by ſiege, there is a proper Gliſter to be taken to cleanſe, open, and cool the pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, but upon their life not to neglect the taking of the Pills.</hi> As to Feavors, through the bounty of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, I think greater wonders have hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly been ſeen; how ſpeedily and effectually this Pill in few hours doth over-rule the diſeaſe, and in a little time doth cure them, as may appear by the inſtances following, One of my neighbors comes unto me, and brings another with her, and deſired me to viſit her daughter which lay at the point of death, about eleven or twelve yeers of Age, her ſickneſs was a high Feavor accompanied with extream ſhortneſs and want of breath, leſt of a very honeſt and able Doctor, who told her Father and Mother, that if ſhe deſired any thing, they ſhould give it her, for he would not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe or give any thing more unto her; and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that ſhe could not live untill the morrow morning; ſhe alſo ſaid that ſhe would deſire me if I thought good, to give her any thing, if ſhe ſhould dye, yet it would be no diſcredit unto me, for they all looked upon her as dead, although ſhe were alive, I went with her and took of the extract of my Pill, and truely I never ſaw in all my life greater weakneſs and yet live; at her mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers intreaty I gave her half a ſpoonful of my extract in White wine and Sugar, and ſaid if it
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:30746:21"/>pleaſe God that ſhe do ſleep and ſweat (for nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of them ſhe could not be brought unto) I do not much fear b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t that ſhe may yet recover, while we were ſpeaking a very little while her mother telling me the manner how ſhe fell ſick, ſhe turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>elf about, ſaid ſhe, I think my child is a ſleep already, I wiſhed her to feel one her ſore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, and it was a little moiſt, I cauſed all to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part the room, and I went home, this was at four in the afternoon, and juſt about eight the neighbor that came with her mother came in great haſt, and told us that ſhe had ſlept and ſweat all that while, and now ſhe was awaked, and called for meat, and they deſired to know what they ſhould give her; I will ſay no more of of this, what is ſaid is true, and will ſpeak for it ſelf; it is ſufficient through Gods wonderful bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing upon the Pill as the means this child is in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect health, as far as I am able to judge; neither do I doubt but this with other inſtances will ſtand in the face of envy it ſelf, praiſed be God who giveth me many ſuch like witneſſes, whoſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord is true and will ſtand on my behalf both in heaven and earth.</p>
            <p>Another inſtance I will give you more ſtrange then this, a Gentleman well known comes to me with a grave Gentlewoman with him, and he told me he had a onely ſon of about thirteen yeers old, who had laid ſick of a Feavor about ſeven days, and that he neither did eat, ſleep, nor ſweat, but did burn as if he were one fire, and that for want of reſt he did talk idle, and that he had uſed means uneffectual and did much fear his
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:30746:21"/>life, deſired me to give ſomething that might do him good, I gave with him a little bottle of the aforeſaid extract of my Pill, and willed them to make haſt and preſently give him one ſpoonful in two of White wine and Sugar, which as it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears they did; I told them as I did unto the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that if it did produce ſweat and ſleep, I did not doubt the recovery of his ſon (in an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary way of Gods providence) and that I had daily experience in like caſes; and I further wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led them to give him the like portion every half day untill he was well, if they thought good to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low my advice (which advice coſt them nothing) about two days after the ancient Gentlewoman comes again with the ſame bottle, and I am ſure I did hardly miſs one ſpoonful, in ſo much that I would have forced her, if I could, to have taken all her mony again, but I could not; and ſhe ſaid that they made haſte as I bad them, and what was wanting they gave it him at that time, and he preſently fell aſleep, and alſo into a gallant brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſweat, and ſo he lay aſleep in his ſweat ſix hours (for nature having eaſe, the patient will ſoon ſleep) and then he waked and called for meat, which they gave him, and it did well agree with him, to all their exceeding joy and comfort, and ſaid ſhe he is very well, and doth continue ſleeping well and orderly, and alſo eating his meat, and I give you a hundred thanks, and have brought you your bottle again, it may pleaſe God it may ſave the life of another, for he never took it but once; now I do aſſure you, God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty the faithful and true witneſs knoweth
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:30746:22"/>that to my beſt knowledge, I have not erred, no not in one tittle as to the ſubſtance of the relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; unto him therefore be all obedience thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving, praiſe and glory forever Amen.</p>
            <p>The general rules that I follow in giving this Pill, whether it be in a Pill or in a extract is to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin with little enough at firſt, wherein is both pleaſantneſs and ſafty, for ſome have fooliſhly flung off at once taking, becauſe they it may be have ſleeped a hour or two longer then they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, and it may be ſweat more then and longer then they were willing, theſe it is evident com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of eaſe, yet is there own fault for taking it it their own way, and not after my direction.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It helpeth all Headach and Toothach,</hi> Experience which is the trueſt informer, ſpeaks aloud in this matter alſo, for if a little Pill be applied unto the Tooth, it (while one can tell fourty) gives eaſe, and often times never troubles more for that time. I was once with two or three friends in cold weather, drinking a pot of hot Purle at the corner of Broadſtreet, the maid of the houſe almoſt mad with her Teeth, and her Miſtris ſaid ſhe was ready to knock her brains out for mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, I gave her about four grains in a little Pill, and bid her lay it to the aching Tooth which ſhe did, and preſently went to draw us drink, who came preſently up again laughing, my friends thought I had conjured, they could hardly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve her that her Teeth did ach, ſhe affirmed they were well and all her pain gone. I gave her a Pill to take when ſhe went to bed to make all ſure, which it did perfectly ſo that her teeth ached not
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:30746:22"/>while ſhe ſtaid in that houſe; many ſuch like I might relate, but becauſe I ſuppoſe belief in this muſt be granted, it is ſo common that many do much help this way as I never hear of in all parts of the City and Country, but my advice is to take it in a good doſs and go to bed, &amp; if they could be great to take three or four, ſo it will do thee many good offices beſides the help of the Tooth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ach, for if the defluction of Rhums be high, and there appear unto their preſent ſeeling, nothing but pains of Teeth, yet if they make not uſe of good means to ſtop and dry up that humor, they may expect the Scurvy, Conſumption or Dropſie to follow, whereby their lives will ſpend out in miſery and haſt them to death; and for the Head-ach it is as ready help, and all kind of pains in the Head, I never knew any grief of the Head ſtand with it but one, and the Gentleman ſaid it was called a <hi>Virtego,</hi> what that is I am not ſo wiſe, but this I know, that the party grieved, ſaid he always was pained with a ſcalding twixt the ſkin and the ſkull of his head; and I think but that I durſt not to be ſo bold with him, if this Pill had been applied unto the ſkull of his head it would have reached it better, but for any other pain or grief, although never ſo bad or of long ſtanding it doth over-rule it, <hi>It dries up dropping Rhums, Catarhs which deſtroy the Lungs:</hi> Bleſſed be God I ſpeak it with joy, the many which this Pill hath helped both in City and Country, which have been left of great and able men, and ſome of them ſo weak that they have not been able to come to me; at this inſtant one man <hi>Northum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berland</hi>-Alley,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:30746:23"/>a loſt man in all appearance, and in his and his wives judgements, even at once is a living monument of Gods mercy and the Pills power and efficacy; I do verily believe I might have Certificates of hundreds of this grief onely, if I would deſire them under their own hands, with their place of dwelling, I do know well that the more good I am an inſtrument to do the more ſome will envy; I may not look to ſpeed better then he that was without ſin.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Preſently helpeth any cold Cough or Surfeit,</hi> which is alſo true, that although a mans Cough were never ſo violent, yet ſhall he not Cough that night he takes a Pill till towards morning a little, then it may be he may Cough a little to caſt forth his Rhums thickned, for lying twixt Head and Lungs defends the one and ſends up ſweet vapon<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in to the other that there is no Coughing; many people of great age at the gates of death to their thinking, God bleſſing this Pill unto them are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vived, and comfortably in joy themſelves and are at eaſe in joying their breath in good order, which before was ever ready to ſtrangle; I do perſwad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> my ſelf that the world never injoyed a more ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtantial help for all griefs of this kind, and let m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> tell thee plainly and freely if the firſt Pill tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thou ſhalt take do not ſufficiently ſpeak for it ſelf<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I do aſſure thee that I deſire to ſay nothing, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will I perſwade thee to take a ſecond.</p>
            <p>There is in <hi>London</hi> a Agedand honorable Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man which for ſome years was much trouble with a Diſtillation or Defluction of Rhums from his head, this Gentleman ſpent and took mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:30746:23"/>for the ſame of ſundry of the greateſt note, but to no purpoſe as he informeth me himſelf, the firſt Pill of mine that ever he did take, although but a little one, did ſtop his Diſtillation, that he did not Cough all that night, unto his great won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and I thank him he did in my vindication ſend unto thoſe whoſe things before proved un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>effectual, and let them know what one ſmall Pill of mine had done, which did win me and my Pills great credit; there would be no end of wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of particulars, we hardly paſs a day without experiences of this kind thanks be to God; and for ſuch kind of colds as carry the ſymptoms of Ague or Feavor with them, if you take it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times and in reaſonable quantity as the Patient may bear, it is ſeldom but that one Pill brings you off maſter, but if not (for it is according as the ſtrength of the infection is) yet continue and with ſmall patience all will be overcome; I ſpeak by experience, for I have oft in cold and foul weather come home with the apparent ſigns of both Feavor and Ague, and then I haſt to bed, taking one Pill juſt preſently, for every minuit would be to loſs; and about four or ſix hours after I tooke another, always having by me a bottle of good Strong Waters, that in caſe of faintings I may refreſh my ſelf with a ſpoonful or two there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, either by it ſelf or mixed with Ale or Beer; and keeping this order that fever nor one in ten ſtayes with me above twenty four hours, or to keep me in a doors all the next day, if the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be favorable, and for any Surfeit either of diet, drink, or labor, or any other way, it is as
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:30746:24"/>ready help as poſſibly the nature of the diſeaſe will permit; but if the Surfeit be by meat or drink it will work variouſly, ſometimes by vomit, and moſt frequently, and ſometimes by purging one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and ſometimes by both, and if the Surfeit be long taken, it will work higher then by Sweat and Urin, and will cauſe the patient to break out more or leſs according as the nature and degrees of the patient is, whereby thorow the bleſſing of God, it hath eminently ſaved the lives of many, as I will give you here a few inſtances.</p>
            <p>A luſty &amp; ſtrong young man upon ſtrong labor being both hot and dry, met with ſmall Beer, and he dranke freely, which did chill his fat and blood within him, he ſuddainly was ſenſible and betook himſelf unto his bed, where he lay in a deſperate condition, none expecting his life could be ſaved, his wife comes to me for him, making great complaint that they had ſpent all that they had, and words to that purpoſe, I gave her Pills and heard no more of her: about three or four months after by a mear accident I was with ſome where alſo this man was in company, I knew not him, nor he knew not me, till by the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of the company, he gained knowledge that it was I who gave Pills at the Tower, and he did there before them all, make a relation of his long ſad condition, and that his wife found fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor, ſaid he, with this Gentleman, who gave me freely a ſmall pot of ſtuff to make Pills on, and the firſt Pill, ſaid he, that ever I did take, I did find my ſpirits revive within me, and I never had more; and Sir I crave pardon for my unthankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:30746:24"/>unto you, and now give you a hundred thanks, for under God you ſaved my life, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> this man is alwayes ready to ſpeak to the full height of what I have ſaid, and much more both of himſelf and friends.</p>
            <p>Another man coming up from <hi>Mancheſter</hi> in cold weather, a man that uſe to be much in the fire, and alſo to keep company, by that time he got unto <hi>London,</hi> his ſpirit was ſpent, having got Surfeit upon Surfeit, and being both perverſe and alſo covetous, reſolved to dye rather then fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to any Doctor, Apothecary, or Chirurgeons hand, his brother and ſiſters perſwaſions were all in vain, he being reſolved to lay his bones here, as he ſaid, at laſt his brother thought of me, and ſaid unto him, that he would bring a man to him that was neither Doctor nor Apothecary, then he began to hearken a little, but what was I then? an Alchimiſt (which he underſtood as well as Wallthams Calf) I was brought (for I could not ſay my friend his brother nay) and found him in a lumpiſh heartleſs temper, and burning in a Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor, he regarded little what I ſaid, neither would be perſwaded to take any thing, till I hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made three little Pills, and firſt I took one my ſelf, then his brother took the ſecond, and when he ſaw that, he for ſhame took the third, it did vex me, &amp; yet it was ſome pleaſure to ſee the hoggiſh temper of the man; I haſted and made two and left them for to take at other nights if he liked the working of that in his belly, and the all that I made was but little ones, partly becauſe of the mans exceeding timorouſneſs, and partly becauſe of my
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:30746:25"/>ſelf being from home, I willed him to haſt to bed and be kept warm; I came the next morning to to ſee my patient, he coughed and told me he was much better, gave me many thanks, his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther proteſted that they heard him break wind in the night (as he and his wife lay in the Chamber over him) as if he would have blowed the bed from under him; and alſo when he came down to ſee him that his Rugg with which he was co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, did ſtand all on a dew, his ſweat coming thorow all the bed cloaths, he got up while I was there, and did eat a little of a Neck of Mutton the firſt meat that he did eat at <hi>London,</hi> and as I ſtood talking with him, I thruſt the two Pills to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and made up the number out of my box which he did not perceive; but the firſt had done the work, for they both did not near work ſo high with him as the firſt did, and in three dayes time this man was as well as ever he was in his life, and as chearfully went about his buſineſs; unto God whoſe commandment gives healing, be all praiſe and glory for ever, I confeſs I did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive too much reſpect, being but a poor weak inſtrument of ſo great and miraculous a work, conſidering the time of its performing, and I was as thorowly rewarded, for when he returned to <hi>Mancheſter,</hi> he ſent me the beſt <hi>Cheſhire</hi> Cheeſe he he could buy for mony, as he promiſed me for my cure. I have given you the particulars with their circumſtances in this and in divers other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances for good reaſon, which is, that the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant thereby, together with my punctual directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on might be well inſtructed, how in all caſes they
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:30746:25"/>order themſelves in making uſe of this Pill, for by experience I find, both ſay and write what I will for direction many forget, and many will do what they liſt, but I hope all will hold me excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, having afforded rules in abundance for di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, <hi>viz.</hi> be ſure aat firſt to take little enough and by little and little come on in quantity as you can bear it, and as your condition requires it (a wiſe man will cut his meat with his knife, but it may be that a mad man will cut his throat there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, yet notwithſtanding the knife is good and neceſſary.)</p>
            <p>One inſtance which comes now to my mind, I will tell you, A very good friend of mine well known amongſt Trades men, were feaſted by his Landlord at the time of paying his rent, with Veniſon and Reſpaſs wine, and being free and merry did eat and drink freely thereof, but did not at all diſgeſt the ſame, this one Saturday mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, he found himſelf indiſpoſed, and not well all the day, and grew worſe and worſe; at night he took one of my Pills (always having them in the houſe ready upon all occaſions) and goes to bed, in two hours time he begun to vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, which he did very much with much illneſs, and as it may be ſuppoſed, wanted the moſt part of the benefit thereof (in that caſe I would advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to have took another) notwithſtanding he vomitted and drunk much all night with great violence, and he burned inwardly and was moſt unſatisfiedly dry (his drinking was out of mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure) but ſtill inwardly burned worſe and worſe, and being ſpent grew very weak and feeble, in
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:30746:26"/>ſo much that his wife and friends did diſpair of life; and I being locked up in the Tower could not be ſpoke with till betwixt ſix and ſeven in the morning; being ſent for I haſted and took with me one gill of my Antidote, for Pills I knew they had in the houſe, and when I came to him, he was ſo weak he could not ſpeak unto me, his face and noſe, his hands and feet was all as cold as earth, I had little hopes of his life, for contrary unto theſe his ſtomach did burn like fire, which indeed cauſed him to pour into his belly ſo much ſmall Beer, and by this time had no ſtrength to evacuate it again, that his Surfeit now was double as well from unreaſonable drinking of ſmall Beer, as of Reſpaſs wine and Veniſon, with his wives good liking I gave him three ſpoonfuls of my An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tidote in four ſpoonful of Treacle water (praying for a bleſſing, yet much feared his life) it gave him a little eaſe as we conceived by his quiet ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, I hoped all vomiting had been ſtaid, think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that to have been the beſt for him, he lay ſtill while one might tell treatably half a thouſand or thereabout, then he began to ſtretch out himſelf and turned up the white of his eyes, we all that were ſpectators was ſorely diſtreſſed for him, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting nothing but that his laſt breath was going from him, but contrary unto our expectation he gathered up his ſeet and twiſted himſelf about and ſtart up, a great Baſon much like a Barbars baſon being ready, which he had uſed in the night, and there at once comes up ſuch a full torrent as his mouth could admit, which quickly filled the great Baſon, ſuch a vomit as I never beheld in
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:30746:26"/>all my life, and am perſwaded never ſhall again, and in the end of it comes his Reſpaſs wine, and his Veniſon unwrought on by nature, for it is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident, that all the former vomitting did not reach the root of the matter, this vomit being o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and another Baſon ready, he gave again a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother eaſie ſtrain and brought up again my Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dote juſt as he put it into his belly, both for quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and collour, as neer as we could gueſs; look you ſaid his wife unto me, here is your ſtuff again, well ſaid I, bleſſed be God for this ſtuff, he hath done well for this time the Lord make us thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful; I would not for more then I will ſpeak of, your huſband had dyed, you would have thought ill of me and my Antidote, thorow the goodneſs of God this man was about his buſineſs in two dayes time; this my friend with all the reſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent are ready to witneſs what I have ſaid, and more touching this matter, unto God eternal im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal Lord of life and death, be praiſe and hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor and glory for ever Amen, for he taketh the ſtrong and hardy, and caſteth them unto the duſt of death according to his will; and again he tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that which is ready to dye and reſtores it to life at his good will and pleaſure, and who is he of the hardieſt of men that can withſtand God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It removes pains of the Breaſt, trembling of the Heart, cleanſeth the Blood.</hi> I have not known any pains ſtand before it, but in Feavors, or any other grief wherein is great crying out of pains and oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of the Breaſt, but the firſt Pill gives relief; there is a very aged woman by me on Tower-hill,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:30746:27"/>hard by the Scaffold, who was almoſt off of her leggs with extream trembling and aching of her Heart, which was occaſioned thorow a fright and much grief and ſhe took this Pill for almoſt or al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together this three years, and thanks be to God is now luſty and for ſtronger and better then when ſhe began to take it at firſt; that it is a forcible cleanſer of the blood it is evident by its univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal ſweating and purging by Urin.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It helpeth ſuddain fits of Sounding and Convulſions.</hi> A young man much troubled with fits, and oft would fall down and foam in his fits; I do not know what to determine them to be, and with the uſe of this Pill and my Oyl of Amber, found preſent relief, which he thankfully acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed beyond expectation, and very many of each Sex and Ages frequently have received the like benefit.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It drunk with whit-wine, cleanſeth the Reins and Kidnies of Gravel, openeth the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rany paſſages, drive<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> out the ſtone, if it be not coagulated, and oft times at <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rine ſends forth like jaggs of cloth of paper of ſundry collours.</hi> Of its power in cleanſing the Reins, Kid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies and Bladder, many hath plentifully found by good experience, to their exceeding joy and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort. A good friend of mine going to <hi>Colcheſter,</hi> finds a kinſwoman very ſick and near death of the ſtone and Gravel, he gave her two or three, I am not certain, but he brought me home five or ſix ſtones of conſiderable bigneſs full of ſharp ſpikes as pin points and three ſquare which I have reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, they alſo ſeemed as if they had been hung upon a ſtring, many more there were which we
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:30746:27"/>have not, but thorow the goodneſs of God this woman, although near eighty, at once recovered hereon, praiſed be God.</p>
            <p>A man that came from <hi>Ireland</hi> who had married a <hi>Iriſh</hi> whore who had a huſband of her own Countrymen, did poiſon this <hi>Engliſh</hi> man three times, the laſt time wrought ſo ſtrongly that it took him off his buſineſs, his hair and nails came off; this man very weak came to <hi>England</hi> in hope of relief; this man had a perpetual thirſt, and did drink without meaſure, but could not Urin it out ſo that he was ſwelled ready to burſt, and all means which could be gotten could not help him until God ſo ordered it that I heard of him, for a very good friend of his did deſire my charitable aſſiſtance, I ſent him ſix Pills which wrought ſuch happy effects, that after one of them given him, he fell a making of water, ſo out of mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure that he filled what was by him for that ſervice and then had no retention but let all go in his bed, his friend had for him one quarter of an ounce more; I never ſaw the man nor never heard more of him, but what I have ſaid is the true and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful relation of his friend as near as I am able to give it you.</p>
            <p>A very old man in Ducksfild-lan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, lay at the point of death with the Stone, and could make no water for many dayes and nights together, ſo that in the judgement of his neighbors there was no hope of his life, one of his neighbors which did know the worth of my Pills, came unto me and deſired me to adminiſter unto him, I told her
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:30746:28"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:30746:28"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:30746:29"/>that ſhe knew well enough that I never did un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake any thing, and that ſhe knew well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough the power and force of my Pills, and if ſhe ſhould venter to give it him, I would give her ſome, but to give it him by my advice, I would give none, blaming her for letting it be drove ſo far, &amp; the old man near death, ſhe replied the caſe was deſperate and other means was uneffectual, and ſhe would give him a good Pill although he did dye, for there was no way elſe but that for him; I gave her Pills with her, ſhe gives him a good Pill, the old man by reaſon of pain had not ſlept for many nights and days, he preſently falls a ſleep, and ſlept four or five hours, and when he waked calls for a pot, and did ſo Urine, that they had hardly things to receive it, and of a ſuddain this man was up and about his buſineſs, bleſſed be God for all his unſpeakable mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies.</p>
            <p>A loving friend of mine who lives at preſent at <hi>Chattam</hi> who knew well the worth and ſafty of my Pill, by much experience he had made, hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a friend of his that was much, troubled with the Stone and difficulty of making water, my friend gives him a good Pill, and the next day as he ſtood draining againſt a Brick wall to make water, at laſt there flew out a ſtone from him and ſnapt againſt the Brick wall where he ſtood, of an incredible biggneſs to be of a mans voiding, upon which this man was wonderfully releaſed to his great comfort, which Stone my friend bring; to us and we have it at this preſent by us; unto God Almighty be all thankſgiving for ever.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:30746:29"/>A man comes unto me in behalf of his wife, a young woman that was deſperately afflicted, but none could tell her what her grief was, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the woman was weary of her life; her pains and knawing at her Breaſt was ſo excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding much, and the moſt conceived ſhe had the foul diſeaſe (it was indeed a foul diſeaſe) and I did alſo miſtruſt it, and I think the woman did like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, but notwithſtanding made many proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions for her ſelf, I let them have Pills for their money, not doubting but they would make a diſcovery what the matter was and ſo it was that my Pills did provoke ſtrong vomiting, and at laſt comes up (as her huſband telleth me) a thing that either was a worm or like a worm, but it had a ſtrange ugly head, and was at leaſt twelve or fourteen inches in length, I did not ſee it, nor could hear any more of it.</p>
            <p>A woman at <hi>Richmond,</hi> a long time grieved, but knew not what her grief was, but fore oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed at her Breaſt, a neighbor of hers gives her one of my Pills which cauſed her to vomit in a ſtrong and violent manner ſhe brought forth at her mouth clots of putrified blood, and matter of divers collours that hung together that it might be drawn out betwixt ones hands, and like jaggs of linnen, cloth, or paper, thorow Gods bleſſing it, did preſerve her, and ſhe in good health at this day praiſed be God for his rich mercy and goodneſs.</p>
            <p>A very ancient Gentleman well known in the City of <hi>London,</hi> being much afflicted with the Stone and Gravel in the Kidnies, riding unto his
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:30746:30"/>Country houſe, received a very gentle fall from his horſe upon the ſand, notwithſtand it did ſtir him too much, inſomuch as that his Urin was all blood, and as might be gueſſed in reaſon that the Stones in the Veſſel wherein they were bred being ſharp pointed, pricked the Kidnies which might pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce bleeding; this Gentleman being careful of himſelf, cauſed a Coach to be that night ſent for and haſted to <hi>London,</hi> where in reaſon help might be attained, and ſuch was his care, that when the Coach came in hard and ſtony way, he got out of the Coach and went gently one foot, he applied himſelf unto the beſt means for help, as in reaſon were to be attained, but ſtill in vain, in ſo much that he did much fear his life, by reaſon of his much bleeding, and as near as he could gueſs, he had loſt above two Gallons of blood and wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, a friend of mind viſiting him, perſwaded him to take ſome of my Pills, which he did, and with good and happy effect, for it did both ſtop his bleeding, and yet alſo brought away handfuls of Gravel; this Gentleman came unto me for more of my Pills, and this is the true relation as near as I am able to remember, and thorow Gods mercy is ready to atteſt above what I have written, prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be God who gives life from death at his good will and pleaſure.</p>
            <p>An Aldermans wife of this City being alſo grievouſly waſted with a flux of blood, that her condition was very doubtful, a woman that I am perſwaded fears the Lord in truth, ſhe deſired to ſpeak with me to take my Pills, and in two or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ree days finds great relief, and in a day or two
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:30746:30"/>more perfectly healed, and ſhe was about her buſineſs, bleſſed be the God of all our mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies.</p>
            <p>A woman by Biſhops-gate, newly brought to bed but very ſick of inward griefs, takes one of my Pills, which did bring a Stone I might gueſs as bigg as my great finger end, but long and one end much bigger then the other, her little daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter lighting one it, did bite off, as ſhe ſaid the bigger end, and if true, then was it bigger then I have ſpoken, ſhe brought it us and left it for ſome moneths with us; further ſhe telleth us that this Pill did bring from her by ſiege a thick hard congealed matter diſcoloured, and like Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ange Pills, at which they did more wonder then at the former; this woman did recover and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy much eaſe and health long after it; the moſt high who dwelleth with him that is of a humble heart and trembleth at his word, be all praiſe and glory for ever Amen, for I am perſwaded this woman did truely fear the Lord, and put her whole truſt in him.</p>
            <p>A gentlewoman that was rich, but of adiſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented Spirit, being near the point of death heard of my Pills; ſhe took of it, but not according to my rules, but did mix it with ſtuff of her own; ſhe lived about twelve months after ſhe did be-begin with them, but got no ground but grew weaker and weaker, till at laſt ſhe took the Pills a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, and when ſhe was ſo weak that ſhe would take no earthly thing, neither bread nor broth, nor any Cordial either of her own or of any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bodies ſhe would take a little of my Pill, and
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:30746:31"/>that alone did keep her alive, and ſuſtain her for ten dayes, to the great wonder and aſtoniſhment of all about her, and had the uſe of her fences ſo far as to be much troubled at her kindred about the dividing of her eſtate, for ſhe had no child and was rich; this is a true relation, which the Nurſe which was alwayes with her doth give me.</p>
            <p>A very old man near death and bed-rid for a good while meets with my Pill I know not how, and did revive exceedingly; his Son in law be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing accidentally in my company, told me how it did lift up his father from the grave beyond all expectation; I willed him to be careful of him, and told him that if he did neglect him one night it would indanger his life; about three months as I do remember, I met him again, ſaid he to me but that I know you are an honeſt man, I ſhould have thought you had been a Witch, for ſaid he, we forgot to ſend for Pills till it was too late, and the next day my father dyed, then I remembred what you ſaid.</p>
            <p>Another old man near fourſcore being lame in his limbs, and alſo greviouſly afflicted with a Rupture, was bed-rid and could in no wiſe help himſelf not ſo much as to Button his Doublet, and to all demonſtration was very near his end, this man with the uſe of my Pills did begin to feel his arms and limbs, ſo that he could do ſome neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry offices for himſelf, and continuing began to ſtagger upon his leggs, and to feel himſelf upon his, Cruches, and in ſhort time this man firſt threw away one Cruch and then another, ſo that now
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:30746:31"/>at this time this old man will go from <hi>Ratcliff</hi> to to <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> and back again in a day, on his feet about his buſineſs, with onely a little ſhort ſtick in his hand, praiſed be God.</p>
            <p>A very old man upward of fourſcore, lay two yeers bed-rid meeting with my Pill did ſo reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, that as his ſervant tells me that the laſt Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer he did buy him a horſe to take his pleaſure in the Country withall.</p>
            <p>A Knight lay bed-rid and lame of all his limbs in the Kings Bench, in ſuch ſort as that he could not ſcarcely ſtir one finger, but his hands &amp; fingers pulled on heaps, this Knight received ſix Pills which had ſo happy effect on him as at once un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tied and ſet him at liberty, he ſent for me, I did not make ſo much haſt to come at him as he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired, my friend from whom he had the Pills, goes to viſit him, and he had took horſe and was gone about his buſineſs, thanks be alwayes given to God.</p>
            <p>Alſo upon Tower-hill doth live another old man aged fourſcore and ſix years, who for ſome years lay bed rid and paſt hope, as to this world, this man with the uſe of my Pill doth now com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortably injoy himſelf, and ruleth over all his pains and A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>les, and doth riſe up and walk up and down the houſe and keep the fire ſide warm, and prevents his kindred of their expectations, to his great eaſe and comfort; to God alone who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands and it is done, be all praiſe and thankſgiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for ever more Amen.</p>
            <p>In Coleman-ſtreet alſo liveth a very aged wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, who for a long time went to Fiſh-ſtreet to
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:30746:32"/>ſetch ſewing work, and thorow much weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs made five or ſix reſtings by the way with very great pain and grief; in a little time making uſe of my Pills doth now go it with eaſe and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any ſtop or turn, for which the old woman doth return all hearty praiſe and thanks unto God. I ſolemnly proteſt that I do in my conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence believe that I do receive more ſtrength and nouriſhment by a good Pill, then from the beſt meales meat that ever I eat in all my life, and therefore the madneſs of thoſe do appear which thorow their ignorance do charge my Pill with deſtroying Nature, but the beſt is, thoſe that ſo do, are ſuch as never took any of it, they may better be allowed to ſpend their verdict, both old and young that uſe it find the contrary by good experience; for I do not commend a thing in the air, or beyond Sea, but a thing that near or alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether one quarter of a pound is taken every night, and certain things concerning it may be attained; and I do wonder at the ſhameles ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and forgeries of ſome, that one would think ſhould a little more reſpect their credit, but it is beſt for me to let them forge on till they are weary; I am perſwaded their lying is the way to make me thrive.</p>
            <p>Sometime ſince I met a very good friend who was not well, I gave him ſix large Pills fit for his own taking, but they being all run into one by that time he came home, his wiſe made the ſix up into nine, and that night ſhe took ſix of the nine, regarding not rule or order that I had given and indeed any of the ſix had been a portion ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:30746:32"/>for her to take; this woman about twelve a clock in the night began to vomit and ſo cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued till ten the next day; and much foul mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it brought from her, and after ſhe had gained reſt and received meat ſhe found her ſelf well and much eaſed of her oppreſſions; a while after I met her husband, who thanked me for working a wonderful cure upon his wife, I replied I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gave her any thing, then he told me what his wife had done, and ſaid, that although he was afraid that ſhe had killed her ſelf, yet it proved very happily, for ſaid he, your Pills have not onely cured all the pains and illneſs of her body, but likewiſe they have cured all her ill conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons too, at which I and ſome friends with me fell a laughing; why ſaid he it is true, for before ſhe took your Pills ſhe was ſo apt to be angry and peeviſh, I could pleaſe her in nothing, but ſince ſhe took thoſe Pills, ſhe is the lovingeſt wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man that may, and ſo pleaſant that I give you thanks for them for my wiſe, for I my ſelf took none of them; although this ſtory is matter of laughter to thoſe that heard it, and a Proverb unto this day, and it may be as ridiculous to you that read it, yet if you pleaſe to conſider that it is pain that oftentimes makes peeviſh, the eaſe of pain doth remove away ſuch peeviſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
            <p>A woman comes to me ſorely afflicted along time in all her limbs, and her torment was ſuch as is not to be credited; the woman I perceived was exceeding ſenſible, and in moſt greivous extremity cried out, I haſted and gave her of my
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:30746:33"/>Pills, ſhe comes the next day and did ſo load me with thanks and praiſe that my heart did ake within me, leaſt God ſhould be diſhonored; this poor woman giving ſo much to me.</p>
            <p>A Lady of an honorable family in this Nation, was ſorely tormented all over her body accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with ſhaking of joynts, was held ſixteen weeks under no ſmall means, but to as ſmall ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, ſhe ſends for me in great haſte, ſhe deſired my help, I preſented her with ſuch things as I had, whereof my Pills was chief; the firſt Pill that ſhe took, took off her great pains, and when I came there about two dayes after, her pains was not onely gone, but her joynts lay as quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly together as my own did, for when I firſt took her by the hand, her bones did ſtart and tremble, as if they would never came near each other again; I ſay no more, God will requite every one according as his work ſhall be.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It alſo ſends forth by vomit or otherwiſe clods of blood, breaks inward Impoſthums to aſtoniſhment, and effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally eaſeth pains got by Surfeits, cold or bruiſes, whereby many ſecret and hidden griefs are cured which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe could not be diſcovered.</hi> A Plummers wife in Biſhopſgate-ſtreet, having five years before re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived ſome wrong in her delivery of two chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, in which time of five years ſhe was ſorely afflicted with ſundry griefs and pains, and fits of falling and ſwounding, in ſo much that this wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man was very weary of her life, and whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver means ſhe uſed it proved uneffectual to her, but her pains and griefs did ſtill increaſe upon her, and by accident I met with her husband at a
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:30746:33"/>friends houſe, who ſpeaking of his wives miſery withal ſaid, as poor as he was he would give ten pounds for his wifes help, I replied and aſked him if he would give ten groats: I gave him ſix Pills with him, and before they was ſpent ſhe ſent me word ſhe was in a new world, and that ſhe, for ought ſhe knew, was as well as ever ſhe was in all her life time, that the Pills thorow Gods bleſſing had ſully freed her from her griefs, and that they did ſo handle her, that by vomit ſhe did bring up ſuch clods of blood, congealed matter, that ſhe was fain with her thumb and fingers to pull it out of her mouth; and further that they did ſend forth by Urin as ſtrange mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to great eaſe and comfort, although to her great wonder and aſtoniſhment, this woman re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains in health to this day, and will not ſpare to give teſtimony hereunto, thanks be given to God.</p>
            <p>Another woman being left for a dead woman, took one of my Pills which cauſed her to vomit up a pint of matter as if it came out of a ſore which no doubt but it did; ſhe ſent for an able Chyrurgeon to ſee it, who ſaid it was better in her baſon then in her breaſt; ſhe kept it two dayes for me to ſee it, but I ſaw it not; it pleaſeth God thus wonderfully to bleſs its uſe, for many grieved ſome years together and cannot tell what they ail, and all that they do adviſe with are in ſeveral tales concerning what they ail; this Pill when taken aſſaults it, and by the grace of God continuing with it, and if curable doth cure it.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:30746:34"/>A very old man upward of fourſcore, being very weak with looſing his blood at Urin, for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove three years together, meets with my Pills, preſently found eaſe, &amp; in a little time quite ſtopt his Urin of blood, but brought way by Urin a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of Gravel and Skins like jaggs of paper, for ſometime; this man hath uſed my Pill for this three years unto his great comfort, and at this day is very hearty, chearful and in health, and his Urin clear as any other bodies, bleſſed be God which takes away youth and reneweth old age at his good pleaſure, and indeed it is wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to hear the happy tidings which people do bring us every day, and many who have affirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to us that they ſold and pawned what they had, and ſpent it in ſeeking for help but in vain have here either for nothing or for a ſmall matter found cure, and doth fill our ears with the large acknowledgements of Gods good hand in bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing this Pill; and truely my ſpirit is much more refreſht to hear ſuch returns, although it be not a penny advantage unto me more then the receiving of mony where I have truely deſerved it, unto God alone I deſire with my whole heart may be aſcribed all praiſe and thanſgiving for all his wonderful mercies which he is pleaſed to ſhew unto the poor and needy who put their truſt in him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Further more this Pill helpeth the French diſeaſes (commonly called the Pox or French Pox) if it be efectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally uſed.</hi> Before I come to ſhew its effectual uſe as to this diſeaſe, I muſt crave leave to ſpeak a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, but tenderly to two or three ſorts of people,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:30746:34"/>for ordinarily this diſeaſe comes not without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of wickedneſs, and I tremble to think of it, much leſs to ſet down his cure without pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſting one Gods behalf againſt thoſe accurſed ways that brings men into it, and indeed were it not for the ſakes of many good men and women whom I do judge in my conſcience to be chaſt, and are infected thorow the wickedneſs and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithfulneſs of their yoak fellows I durſt have ſaid nothing of it at all, and although theſe are but few in number comparatively, yet far be it from any honeſt mind to deny them help; <hi>Solomon</hi> in his Proverbs ſaith, <hi>Stolen water is ſweet, and bread in ſecret is pleaſant;</hi> but they conſider not that death is there, and that thoſe ſteps lead down to hell, and ſuch is the ahborring of my ſoul againſt this wickedneſs whereby this diſeaſe is for the moſt part gotten and come by, that it is a ſore fear leaſt I ſhould be a means to help any miſcreant to ſuddain cure, that is reſolved to perſevere in this abomination, and double his ſins againſt the God of mercies; and foraſmuch as the righetous judgements of God overtake the wicked plagu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them even in the force of their luſts; ſhall I be an inſtrument of their relief yet to ſin, God forbid it, but for thoſe that truely repent and ſhew it by a chaſt converſation, I ſhould think it a happineſs to be a healer, an eaſer of the pains and ſores of all ſuch; yea I profeſs my ſelf the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant of all ſuch; but as I ſaid Gods juſt ſeverity is moſt conſpicuous upon theſe who ſport, and as they imagin pleaſure themſelves, ſtriving to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie and fullfil (but in vain) their beaſtiality; and
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:30746:35"/>were they not left and given up of God unto a ſordid ſlavery unto the fullfilling the deſires and Iuſts of their concupiſence bond ſlaves to hell and the devil, they would eaſily diſcern they labor altogether in vain; for can the ocean, the gulf or grave, ſay it is enough, or what man laboring to fulfil his deſire is not ten times further off by being vaſſallaged more thereunto, can deſire be ever ſatisfied or filled; and ſo always is the quiver of a Whore always open and cannot be filled, but like the grave ever craves give, give, and he that is appointed to perdition is taken by her; the wiſe King tells that a Whore is a deep pit, and the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horrd of God do fall therein, a dreadful precipe, God grant ears to hear it while the day of hope laſteth, and it is my hope to admoniſh by this unto the preſervation of many, and how light ſoever this unclean wickedneſs is accounted, yet let all the guilty know their names are accounted amongſt thoſe that ſhall not inherit eternal life, but for ever receiving their portion in the black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of darkneſs, from the preſence of the Lord for ever; O thou adultrer and adultreſs would God thou couldſt hear; but thou, O thou who already haſt received the beginning of torment<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> how miſerable of mankind art thou above all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and to thy further judgement know that when thy now rotting body is deſtroyed, thou a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain ſhalt receive a ſpirituous body capable of bearing and receiving a flood of wrath, and as then thou haſt received a body ſpirituous that ſhall remain unto eternity, ſo will the vengeance of God be powred out againſt all ungodlineſs;
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:30746:35"/>now thou haſt but a taſte, and yet O how thou roareſt out as thy limbs rot, but what is that to that ocean or expanſion of wrath prepared; let this awaken thee, if thou be not paſt feeling, to repentance, to break off I ſay thy ſins by true and timely repentance; God Almighty open thy eyes to ſee thy redoubled miſery, that ſo thou maiſt inquire after mercy, then the blood of Chriſt will be precious unto thee, but wo is upon us who are born in a giddy drunken age, drunk, but not with wine, and here alſo I cannot get forward, but muſt crave leave to trace this a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, and you will be ſenſible that it lies conſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trick with the former, and now I come to ſpeak unto a ſecond ſort of people, amongſt whom I believe there are many that have received in their ſouls the power of endleſs life; I ſpeak of thoſe that have ſhewed great zeal and forwardneſs in building Tabernacles for God to dwell in, who have poſted into Churches, and ruſhed upon all Ordinances, which things are good if perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with clean hands and pure hearts, but wo is me when I conſider the works of the unwary, the headdineſs and preſumptions of many, and in my time and obſervation within this twenty five years paſſed, having been an eye witneſs of the beginning, riſe, and fall of many; I cannot but ſpeak a word (although Gently) unto theſe, and am forced to ſpeak it aloud, becauſe I by woful experience have found them dull of hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, for many amongſt them puffed up have miſerably faln into this pit, many of whom I fear have not yet repented, or if they have, yet bear
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:30746:36"/>with me, it is not yet to me evident, ſure I am this Pit is not for Saints to fall into, not many re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns, <hi>Although your way if returning is broad and eaſie,</hi> yet I much fear not ſo with God, it were well if juſtice in this caſe went hand in hand with mercy, that thoſe that ſin not might he admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed and fear, which is one principal end of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection, but theſe alas with eaſe find entrance, but not ſo with others in other caſes leſs material, it were well if you were clean every whit, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the feet muſt be waſhed, the ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity of the heel ſtrove againſt, many lift their head on high, and I pray God keep them from falling, it is a dangerous thing for men to make idols of Ordinances, to put more in the dipping of water then in the regenerating of the ſpirit, there is a golden mine, he is happy that finds it and walks therein, there is a promiſed ſpirit to direct when we turn to the right hand, and when we turn unto the left, to too many neglect or diſpiſe viſible Ordinances, and too many plant their Religion in them, and in divers forms will prepare Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacles for the God of Iſrael, but unto us there is but one God, and one rule of righteouſneſſe, men will at all rates have a covering, but the wo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to them that cover not by and with his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, let me in much ſoberneſſe inquire of you, and it would be a joyful tune if indeed you would conſider whether your raſh and haſty zeal run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning upon Ordinances not ſpirited from on high, have not been an occaſion of ſtumbling and of falling unto many, for having no ſealing pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, but rather a barrenneſſe which from thence
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:30746:36"/>as in your hands may be called preſumptious; I ſay this diſcovers that men ſeeing no beauty to enli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven them, faint; How many have you with ſighs complaining that they are filled with deadneſſe in your aſſembling, but at home when they exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe their mediations on the riches of free mercy in Chriſt, then filled with conſolation.</p>
            <p>You may note, that at this time and in his place I would ſay no more then to awaken you to conſider how you have been an occaſion of ſtumbling to many from the aforeſaid grounds, I freely ſpare you, coveting rather to cover then to diſcover; neither would I charge all for the faults of ſome, but this I muſt ſay, it is like to go ill when the ruling ſpirit is the ſpirit of this world, when the whole head is ſick and the heart heavy; what ſhould I ſay to make you hear and yet cover you all over with love, the moſt high cover you when he maketh inquiſition for blood, when his dead body ſhall live, when his righteouſneſſe ſhall ariſe, when he hath purged <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> with the ſpirit of fire, and with the ſpirit of burning, then will he be a defence upon all your glory, and not till then, but evident it is your glory he ſtains, neither is he any defence upon it; an account muſt be given who required theſe things at your hands, when many ſhall ſay we have done theſe and theſe things in thy name, it will be ſaid, I know you not, it will be then wo unto the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners in <hi>Sion,</hi> fear ſhall ſurprize the hypocrit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, that generation of men at this time will be to ſeek which ſay ſtand further of I am more holy then thou; thoſe I ſpeak of which are pure in their
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:30746:37"/>own eyes and is not waſhed from their filthineſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, thoſe who ſeparating themſelves from thoſe fro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> whom Jeſus Chriſt doth not ſeparate himſelf<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> thoſe which make dipping the ground of the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> communion &amp; not union with Chriſt, it is a wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to look back and conſider the firy zeal of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and whereunto it hath tended; God grant the reſt may be admoniſhed to pray and wait u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the Temple be opened in heaven and a live<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Viſion of the Ark of his Covenant, the preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of men now in this dark and ſmoky day<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to be wondred at, but it is evident no ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> can enter till the appointed time, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed it is evident that excepting thoſe Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances which are granted in common, whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> indeed are ſpirited; the other whereby they will be known and diſtinguiſhed, art without life, and is in their hands a carkaſs: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> I have to ſay further, is, I beſeech you in the bowels of Chriſt Jeſus conſider, how far you have been an occaſion of ſtumbling, or wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> unto the gender of this third generation of men wherof I come now to ſpeak unto, for when men, as I may ſay, have found little but pollotick work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings as men, and have not either diſcerned tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> beauty as doth of good right belong unto Goſpel-Ordinances, or when men diſhonoring God uſe Gods Ordinances for earthly ends, it is juſt with God to give them up unto a ſpirit of ſlumber to believe a lye, becauſe they did not receive the truth in the love of it, nay too many deſigned<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly do get into Churches one purpoſe to heal their gauled conſciences (little thinking what is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:30746:37"/>of them there) and ſhrowd under a cloak of Religion, gain being to them godlineſs; Mark by how much theſe approach or do eſſay to come up unto the Primitive pattern, aſſure thy ſelf ſo much the more will the ſeverity of the higheſt be revealed againſt thee, whoſe fiery eyes of beauty and glory will not bare thy hypocriſie, remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Saphira;</hi> therefore I have obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved well what hath brought people to deſire to get into this or that fellowſhip, whether to ſerve as Chriſt did, or to be ſerved, to perform their own duty in humility, or onely clamor upon their priviledge, for you ſhall perceive quickly who ſent them thither, O how forward theſe will be, apt of tongue, confident in opinion and fears, ſenſorious, and this laſteth a very little while and by and by he is beyond them, and now he is beyond the Scripture it ſelf, and will have it no judge of his ſpirit, but will judge it by his ſpirit; have I not ſeen theſe fall off by companies, what then think not thou that I ſpeak againſt the commandments and Ordinances of the new teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (I had rather my tongue ſhould be for ever cut out of my mouth) or againſt the Chriſtian and conſcionable adminiſtring the ſame; but this is to ſhew how they have been and may be abuſed, in doing of which a moſt accurſed gender of hell is born into the world, which otherwiſe could not be, and I am conſtrained to unvail as wiſely as God inables me this miſtery of iniquity, that you whom it concerns may beware, and if the glory of God nor eternal ſalvation will not prevail, yet that long life and health of body may prevail with
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:30746:38"/>thee, thou maiſt, know that the higher thou ariveſt in the profeſſion of Chriſt, the fiercer wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> thy fall be when not ſupported, if that ligh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> which is in thee prove darkneſs, how great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> that darkneſs? and if thou be a builder look <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> thy ſelf that thy foundation be the true Rock, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe great will thy fall be, and know the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning evil ſpirit doth bring with him ſeve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> worſe then himſelf, and worſe will be thy latte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> end; my heart bleeds within me when I call <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> mind how many great lights or ſtars have bee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thrown from heaven, ſaln from the pinacle of the Temple down to hell, from moſt fiery rigidity un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all abominations; think not that I am unfur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed of a catalogue, meaſurable it is the re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> are ſo blinded as not to lay it to heart, ſo to hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> as again to take up their way, and whole wall<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and that with trembling and ſet ſtraight ſteps un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their feet, leaſt that that is halting be turn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> out of the way alſo; I will at this time abrevia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> this diſcourſe for the truths ſake which you have yet a pretence unto. I know there are a few na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> amongſt you which have not defiled their gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, for their ſakes I ſhould count it a happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to ſerve you. I will conclude with relation of one of you, which I know is reme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred of many of you, A fierce zealot which was very conformable, as indeed did exceed, and I muſt needs ſay from one word I once heart him ſpeak, I had good hope that the truth had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſome rooting in him, <hi>viz.</hi> that he was ſo ſenſib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of the deceitfulneſs of his heart, that he durſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> look upon a woman, this man takes in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:30746:38"/>general tenet of all deſtruction<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>viz.</hi> that the Scripture was a dead letter, this man with the reſt of his accomplices was ſoon inſpired from the King of pride, that they had in themſelves the ſpirit whereby they knew all things, and judge all things, and alſo, the Scriptures themſelves, ſo that now their ſpirit ſhall not be judged by the text, but ſhall judge the text, this infallible man was reſtleſs, and quickly threw of all duties both publike and private, for a ſeaſon they muſt not ſpeak till their ſpirit moved them, but their ſpirit ſoon moved them to make uſe of, and abound in their pure or rather impure liberty, that is to glut and ſatisfie themſelves in unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; this wretch being ſtrong held out ſometime, but abuſing himſelf in all blaſpheamies, riot and exceſs, in due time the rot or the Pox over-took them, but I ſpeak of this one man, his torments grew ſtrong upon him, and to me of all men he would not come or ſend, what he uſed as means was to weak; and thus for a long time he lived blaſpheaming God and roaring out of his torment, at laſt he and his wife uſing the media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of another ſent to me, I could not deny her things for her mony, he was then paſt coming him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; ſhe ſaid his heart was as whole and as ſound as ever, and that he would eat as good a meals meat as ever, and digeſt it as well, but except he had one of my Pills in his belly, he did lie rocking his limbs and roaring out of his intol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable pain, and the next week as ſhe came to me this Strumpet with impudence, ſaid ſhe ſhould dye of no diſeaſe but the Pox; and her friend that came with her told me that as this man was
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:30746:39"/>ſitting by himſelf, his noſe fell of from his face with mear rottenneſs; I conclude with moſt ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous admiration of Gods righteous judgements upon theſe who in the prime of their days are taken a way, and are gone unto their own place for ever to receive the fruit of their doings, and that which doth much heighten my aſtoniſhment, is that the higheſt doth to wonderfully puniſh this wickedneſs in this life, that they live ſome years in bitter torment, and yet hearty and ſtout while they rot away by pieces, their vitals and ſenſes quick, as I may ſay, as prepared of God to ſuffer abundance of pains while in this world, and before I come to give you the way of cure of this ugly diſeaſe, I muſt crave leave to ſpeak this third ſort of people commonly called Ranters, for ſo they are, and theſe are of two ſorts, the one like unto this that I have named, and the other which is the worſe and more dangerous, hold yet in appearance ſomewhat of preaching and pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and would be thought to excel all others in ſpirituals; I ſay theſe are the worſe, for by how much the more any thing that indeed is evil and doth hide it ſelf under the cloak or mantle of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, it is ſo much the more dangerous and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious, moſt apt to leaven and delude the ſimple minds, till they alſo by a ſmoth Satanical ſubtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty are drawn in and become hardened, and then the high Rant or black devil doth not all affright them, being before hand prepared and ſpirited there unto, for the high Rant counts all illegiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate that cannot range in the depth of all abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, ſwear, drunk, whore out of meaſure, yea ſtudy to excel in execrations and blaſph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>my, and
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:30746:39"/>do all this without the leaſt remorce or ſign of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morce, but this other ſort for their credit ſake, and alſo becauſe of encreaſe of their advantage in their Callings, and alſo preferments in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, will not avow this plainneſs, yet do account it their pure liberty, and that is there pure liberty for all of them to live holding com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity of women, and all to abide in their pure Adamical freedoms, pleaſing themſelves in all things, and ſome of theſe to my own knowledge who both ſpeak, &amp; hold, &amp; practice (except they belye themſelves) are of their forwardeſt and I think their eminenteſt Preachers, which would ſeem to thoſe that hear him as if he were caught up into the holy mount, accounting themſelves above all Ordinances, theſe ſurely are the worſt ſort of men that ever breathed upon the face of the earth, for theſe have not onely been hoiſed upon the higheſt pinacle of the Temple, but are miſerably thrown down unto hell, in their own imaginary they are far higher then the higheſt pinacle, conceiving themſelves far above all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted Ordinances, and do bitterly hate, diſpiſe, and perſecute all thoſe that do in the fear of God practice, walk, and live in them with a manifeſt wrath, which is indeed a manifeſt token of their perdition, for many of them have in their own guiddy headed and unſtable minds run thorow all Religions that they might both hate and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute all; the God of mercy put into the hearts of our Rulers to preſerve us from the rage and fury of theſe whom the Apoſtles of Chriſt, <hi>Peter,</hi> and <hi>Jude</hi> doth moſt lively ſet out in their proper
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:30746:40"/>collours, and yet theſe would not be accounted to be Ranters, although as is ſaid ſeven fold worſe, I will hear give a true relation of ſome paſſages concerning one of their chief teachers.</p>
            <p>A good woman whoſe huſband is at <hi>Barbadoes,</hi> having occaſion of buſineſs concerning trade in behalf of her hu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>band, was deſired to except of half a pint of wine, this good woman looking upon hum to be eminent in godlineſs, and her ſelf at that time ſtood need of refreſhing, went to the Tavern with him, by and by he changed his behaviour, and ſhewed himſelf what he was, and by his light ſcurrilous language, declared him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be what he is, and in plain words and deeds would needs have been abuſing her body, and many arguments he uſed to draw her there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, as I have them from her mouth, that ſhe was ſick for want of a man, and why would ſhe not uſe her liberty; and for his part he knew <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> his wife looked on, ſhe would not be offended with it; nay further that it was his ſalvation that he had done it, his wife looking on, and that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> he had not uſed his liberty, his purer liberty, as he called it, it had been dead long ago, and nam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed other perſons, ſome of great quality, that huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band and wife gave each other liberty, and with his might invyed againſt Ordinances, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſing him in his filthineſs, he called her whore, and much to that purpoſe, for ſubmitting her ſelf to forms, as he called them; the relation of his beaſtilneſs expreſſed by him, I was aſhamed to hear and cannot write, but he highly commend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the beaſtly openneſs and nakedneſs of the
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:30746:40"/>Moors and Heathen in the Indies that they was without ſhame, he eſteemed it a high vertue which did excell us here; and ſpeaking of the Quakers, he ſaid that he knew them very well, and that he did know that their principals and theirs were one and the ſame, and that the moſt ſtricteſt of them would ſoon come up and live in the pure liberty as well as they (I think what he ſaith in this may well be granted, as was moſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidently ſeen in <hi>James Nailo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> and the pack of whores that always hung on him; I my ſelf being at <hi>Nottingham</hi> did ſit almoſt a Summer afternoon, hearing ſome of their own company relate the vicious and filthy life, and unclean coverſation of <hi>George Fox,</hi> whoſe whoredoms and filthy life is notoriouſly known in the North of <hi>England</hi>) but to return unto this praying or prating Rantor this filthy man or man of filthineſs without ſhame after God had delivered this woman out of his hand, was ſet on again and again by him, and when he ſaw that he could not draw her unto his filthy luſt, then inquired if ſhe had told any bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, but if ſhe had, yet it was not matter of ſhame unto him, and indeed I think I ſhould have done good ſervice to the Commonwealth, if I had here named him, its pitty all ſuch hath not a brand on their forehead that they may be known who they belong unto; I ſpeak with grief of heart I have known this Varlet the worſt of men, I ſay I have known him a giddy profeſſor of Religion above this twenty years, and I have heard him my ſelf when we have been ſpeaking of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, for he asked me ſeriouſly if I did uſe t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:30746:41"/>read them, I told him yea with joy and gladneſs and they were to me more then my life, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied, ſo could not he, neither did he read any book, he hearkened onely to the voice of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit within him, and that while he made conſcience of reading and expounding of Scripture and of family duty, and going to hear Sermons and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peat them, he all that time was without peace, but now he had not for ſome years done any of thoſe things and that he was at reſt in himſelf. I have in all this ſpoke the leaſt of this vile perſon, and you may by him truely take a view of the reſt that fraternity what they are, and where they will Center, and in what; I hope this relation will he matter of caution to many, not always to credit or be too apt to give heed unto the ſmoth delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive tongues of men, theſe ſtudy to obtain hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of heart, impudency of face that they might commit wickedneſs with greedineſs; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore do deride at the torments of hell, nay one of this company hath put out a book in print, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he doth a vow there is no hell but what is in a mans ſelf, ſo that indeed by their doctrines, if they can but ſtifle their own conſciences, they have freedom, and ſin is no ſin, for ſo they affirm; my ſoul is pained within me when I think of theſe, and of the juſt vengeance prepared of God for theſe which doth withhold the truth by their unrighteouſneſs; O wretched and moſt miſerable of mankind! How is it that Satan hath thus filled your hearts, and the filth of your fleſh thus deluded you, you begun well, who hath hurt you, what hath Jeſus Chriſt and his Goſpel
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:30746:41"/>of peace done unto you; How is it that you will be made perfect in the fleſh? What good things have you found in your ſelves, that comparing your ſelves with your ſelves, you now worſhip your ſelves, nay your accurſed luſts and beaſtli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; how imaginable is it that man indued with common reaſon ſhould thus be ſeduced; I know there is not one of you but do feel the flaſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of fire in your conſciences; what will you do when you ſhalt appear with your works fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing after you? when God that cannot lye will ſet your ſins in order before your face; I know you labor to ſtiflle ſuch thoughts as theſe, O beaſt of men! O moſt deviliſh whilſt men! How is your vengeance hightening? have you profeſſed the fear of God many of you to end in this accurſed Apoſtacy, for whom the blackneſs of darkneſs is reſerved for ever? O that there were thoughts of returning in you! hell beneath hath enlarged her ſelf to receive and meet you at your coming. O miſcreant of man, how long doſt thou think to wallow in thy luſts, ſerving evil concupiſence, drinking iniquity like wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter made fat for ſlaughter? I aſke whether theſe be not they for whom ſupplication is not to be made? Alas, alas my heart bleedeth within me when I confider that ſome of you have not onely profeſſed the name of Chriſt long, but alſo ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered both impriſonment and fled into far Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries out of a zeal for his name, and now have ſpewd up all at once, and returned unto your old luſts (from which you were purged) as a dogg unto his vomit, or a ſow that was waſhed unto
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:30746:42"/>her wallowing in the mire, receiving the juſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence of your error, <hi>viz.</hi> ſeven helliſh ſpirits far more worſe then the firſt, that you might fall into the damnation of hell and be damned to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, even the condemnation of the devil, be not deceived, God is not mocked, as a man ſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth ſo ſhall he reap; and of theſe I ſpeak aloud expecting nothing but plague and pox to follow them, the reward of their labor, I know it boiles amongſt them already.</p>
            <p>I know ſome will wonder why I have ſpoken ſo much of theſe, and of this diſeaſe; and why I have ſpoken unto good people with theſe, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this thou maiſt know. Firſt, I ſpeak unto all men and all ſorts, and ranks of men to admoniſh them all. Secondly, a clean heart is not hurt nor will be offended at any thing I have ſaid. And thirdly, I could not break this order with the diſcharge of my conſcience. And fourthly, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this that I have ſaid both in whole and in part I darſt not give thee the true and clear way of cure of this deteſtable diſeaſe, and all roots from this ground the difference twixt this diſeaſe and moſt other this with abundance of wickedneſs and ſin; firſt againſt God; ſecondly againſt thy one body which ought to be the Temple of God, preſerved in holineſs unto him, and not given to a harlot; thirdly againſt thy relations, who hath power over thy body, but other diſeaſes which are common to man, proceed from ſundry other cauſes which is not in themſelves ſinful, and for theſe cauſes I have thus ſpoken, and hope thereby to be an inſtrument in the hand of God to
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:30746:42"/>pull ſome poor ſoul or other out of the fire; and indeed as I ſaid at firſt had it not been for the ſakes of ſome who are clean but beſtowed with ſome ſuch beaſt or bruit of mankind which hath polluted them, I ſhould have ſaid nothing of this diſeaſe at all; but I do judge it much better that many of the worſt partake of the bleſſing with the beſt, then that one of the beſt ſhould languiſh in the torture of the firſt, and therefore I do ſet down the moſt ſafeſt way, ſpeedieſt, cheap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt and freeſt of pain and torture, I verily believe that is in the world.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rec.</hi> Take two ounce of my Pill, and lay it thin upon a well glazed diſh, ſet it out of the Sun and it will quickly be fit to bring to powder, drive it thorow a Lawn or Hair five, put this powder into one quart of White-wine, or that which is better, <hi>viz.</hi> make a Lixivium or ſtronge lye of <hi>Chalkes Vive,</hi> or White wine, for this is moſt ſlate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and operates very potently both by ſweat and Urin, as is much proved everyday, and is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though diſpiſed, a great bleſſing; and moreover I aſſure thee from knowledge is chief with ſome as univerſal, who have a vulgar ſame in Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick; uſe which thou wilt I do by experience commend this laſt to excel, let this be done in a glaſs bottle, ſhake it oft, and in twenty four hours it will be fit to uſe but longer is better, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe thy ſelf a part if thou wouldſt ſuddainly be well, and thy illneſs require thee, and have warm accomodation, and a good tender and careful Nurſe, eat and drink the bed that can be got for mony, and always have ready good
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:30746:43"/>wine and Strong-water by thee, becauſe of a ſuddain will a windy fainting come upon thee, and of a ſuddain gone, at ſuch a time a ſpoonful of a good cordial water is neceſſary for thee; ſee that thou ſweat by day and not in the night, when thou maiſt have good tendance; ſweat not with this extract, but every other day, and then do it to purpoſe as thou finds thy ſtrength; if thou beeſt of a middle ſtrength, the firſt time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin with ſix ſpoonful in ſix ſpoonful of White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wine, and then obſerve by that how thou doſt bare it, and increaſe accordingly; ſo alſo in all caſes begin with little enough and come on with diſcretion; but know in this diſeaſe thou muſt charge home to the end, it may accompliſh thy deſire, and at once as it were it will whirle all thy diſeaſe into thy in ſkin, the ſuperfices or moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream parts; and in the other night the day that thou doſt not ſweat thy greateſt ſweat, take at night a good Pill of 16 or 20 grains if thou findeſt thou art able to bear it, and that wil maintain and keep what the other hath gotten, for thou muſt know that thou doſt take the ſtrength of at leaſt eight or ten Pills when thou doſt take the extract thereof, for thou art not not able to bear this earthly body, it would ſuffocate the, but being onely his more ſubtile and ſpirituous part it works ſafe and miraculous, not onely in this diſeaſe but in many or all other diſeaſes; and when thou haſt it all in thy skin, fear not, but go on the ſame way, and if any part break and run, fear it not, it will not fail thee, if thou do not neglect thy ſelf, but it will both throw all out
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:30746:43"/>and heal it when it is out, as thou maiſt perceive by the inſtances ſet down in this book, onely uſe thy ſelf to great carefulneſs in the time of thy cure, and always ſweat and be hot till thou art well, for there is no danger but in taking cold, which thou maiſt eaſily prevent if thou be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of thy ſelf, and follow while thou art in the way, and all will be done at an eaſie rate, for I have deſerved twenty pounds when l have not had twenty ſhillings, I never undertook any cure in my life, nor never mean to do, yet have helped many at ſmall rates at ten ſhillings, at five ſhillings, the moſt that ever I had of any was three pounds five ſhillings for my things onely, and I think a notabler cure is ſeldom done, as ſome of good quality can bear teſtimony; a young woman comes to me pained in her throat, head and bowels of this diſeaſe as all ſuppoſed, and ſhe her ſelf did much fear, becauſe her husbands firſt wife were noted for a light huſwife; this good woman almoſt killed her ſelf with grief, and for two years ran up and down amongſt Doctors and Chirurgions, but in vain, and the Chirur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion made holes in her throat by lancing it, and ſuch like fooliſh things, at laſt ſhe comes to me, &amp; I gave her of theſe Pills, and by that time ſhe had ſpent one ſhilling, ſhe told me ſhe was as well as ever ſhe was in her life, and I am confident in three years time, I did not take five ſhillings of her money, but ſhe continues in perfect health, I could not have believed it till time hath made it evident.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:30746:44"/>
               <hi>Cures ſome kind of Gouts, eaſeth the moſt malign, brings the patient unto quiet reſt.</hi> A woman lame eight years of a Gout, which did diſable her in all her limbs, that ſhe could neither ſtir hand nor foot when ſhe ſent to me, her joynts was very much knotted; the firſt Pill ſhe took, being in a kindly ſweat, both ſhe and her huſband told me this ſtory, ſhe began to ſtir her fingers, which was very ſtrange to her, and a while after ſhe could get her hand unto her mouth, to be ſhort, in three dayes time ſhe could go about the Chamber, which ſhe could not do in two years before that time.</p>
            <p>A Gentleman removing her dwelling into Lime-ſtreet, got an extream cold and Surfeit as ſhe doth report, I do ſuſpect it to be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, how ever ſo it was that ſhe could neither ſtir hand nor ſoot, but was perfectly uſeleſs to her ſelf, onely as by main ſtrength of two o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> three which was alwayes ready did liſt her, and this uſeleſneſs of Limbs, accompianed with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream pains; this woman in a matter of three weeks time, uſing onely my Pills, although it was cold weather, was perfectly well unto all demonſtrations, and I by accident ſaw her go along the ſtreet, and truely although an ancient woman, yet ſhe did hold up her head, and went as ſtraight and as nimbly a good luſty pace, as any young woman whatever, and although ſhe ſen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> me word the was well, yet it was far from me to think ſhe had been ſo well, and that in froſty weather; it is to be noted when I ſometimes ſay they have nothing but my Pill, I do includ the
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:30746:44"/>extract of my Pill, and alſo the Oyl of Amber, with which oft times I do annoint, and all is but my Pill.</p>
            <p>A woman in Saint <hi>Johns</hi> ſtreet, was ſo ſorely afflicted with the Gout and Sciatica, that in her extreamity ſhe did roar out in ſuch a hideous manner, as did much diſquiet the neighbors, and no eaſe or cure could be attained, her hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band come to me with ſuch pittiful moan for his wife, as did much exceed; I was much troubled for him, and gave him of my Pills and ſent him away, and told him that by that time the Pills was warm in her breaſt, that ſhe would have eaſe and her pains would ſeaſe, and that ſhe would go to reſt; he did as I ordered him, and when he came again, he ſaid that by that time his wiſe had taken a Pill, in one quarter of an hour ſhe did find ſuch caſe as if ſhe had been in heaven, and truely this man in the name of his wife did ſo load me with thanks as if I had done it; I bleſs and praiſe the God of heaven who hath ſaved my life and brought me thorow great pains and ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for this happy end, even to be a poor in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument in his hand for eaſe and refreſhing of many; and further as I take it about three weeks or a month, I am not certain which, this poor woman comes from Saint <hi>Johns</hi>-ſtreet unto the Tower to me to fetch for her ſelf more Pills.</p>
            <p>A little boy having four of his fingers out off of that diſeaſe called the Kings Evil, this boy at the place where his fingers was cut off, did alwayes ſtand with a drop of water upon them, but next
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:30746:45"/>day after the taking the firſt Pill, there was no drop of water as formerly, at which the parents did much wonder, and the boy grew extream quick and lively in what ever he did, that they was very ſenſible of his real benefit.</p>
            <p>Another Boy lame of his Limbs and Feet from a child, ſo that he could not go to ſtool nor hold a pen in his hand, and by that time he had taken three of my Pills, he was grown ſo ſtrong that he ran up a pair of ſtairs before me, and I made him hold a Tobaco-pipe in form of a pen, and he then held it as ſtedily as I or any in the room could do, which indeed was far more then was to have been expected in ſo ſhort a time.</p>
            <p>And many that have been troubled with one arme ſhorter then another; and with great pains in particular joynts, this Pill thorow Gods good-neſs have proved ready help unto them.</p>
            <p>An old man belonging unto the Charterhouſe many years troubled with Tiſick, ſtraightneſs of breath, that with great difficulty he went about, alſo one arm begun to ſhrink and grow ſtiff, ſo that he could not make uſe of his pocket as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly he had done, with a little uſe of my Pill did receive his breath at length and his Arm at length alſo; and as he and I was going together along the walk before the Charterhouſe, ſaid he to me, look you how I go, and what pace I go, I could not have done ſo before I took your Pills, but I muſt have ſtood and gaped like a Camelion for breath, I do not know how oft in going the length of this walk.</p>
            <p>A vertuous Gentlewoman of good note, and
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:30746:45"/>my very good friend, whom it hath pleaſed God to viſit with much ſickneſs for a great many years, and now lately it ſell out to be very ſore in her head; this Gentlewoman having made uſe of the ableſt Doctors, but her grief could not be helpt, in ſo much that this good woman almoſt in a diſpair, did much fear her ſenſes, and all that could be done could not bring her head to purge untill ſhe met with my Pills, which did moſt powerfully accompliſh her deſire, and did ſet her head a purging at her ear, and ſhortly, very ſweetly cured it to her exceeding great joy and comfort, with the joy of her fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</p>
            <p>A Gentlewoman that liveth at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> that well knew the uſe and worth of my Pills, went with ſome other Gentlewomen to <hi>Barnet,</hi> where ſhe drank water in abundance but without judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſhe preſently fell into a extream ſcowring, ſhe ſends with what haſt could be to me for half an ounce of my Pills, the uſe and vertue of which ſhe very well knew, but before they could come at her ſhe was far ſpent and had entertained a Doctor, whoſe advice ſhe was forced to follow, ſuch was her weakneſs of a ſuddain; but ſo it was that this luſty young Gentlewoman in a matter of ſix or ſeven days was brought home in a Horſ-lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter hard put to it for life; this Gentlewoman lay under the Doctors hands for two months, and was brought unto ſuch extream weakneſs as is not fit for me to relate, nothing but death expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed all this while, my Pills was too low for them, and the Gentlewoman had abundance of other
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:30746:46"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:30746:46"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:30746:47"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:30746:47"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:30746:48"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:30746:48"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:30746:49"/>things forced on her, but in vain; at laſt ſhe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeched her husband if he loved her to fend for me, otherwiſe ſhe was a dead woman, pleading her conformity to him in uſing all the while what means lie and their friends thought good; this Gentleman being touched with pitty to her, at her requeſt ſends a letter to the Tower, but I was in the Country, and he ſtraight ſends a letter unto <hi>Wanſor,</hi> where I was, and I not hearing any thing from the time her meſſenger came unto me from <hi>Barnet,</hi> much wondered that ſhe ſhould ſuffer ſo long ſickneſs, and I not hear thereof; at my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſhe was glad, and I was much ſurpriſed to ſee ſo ſtout and luſty a woman ſo ſtrangely redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to nothing, in ſo much as had it not been that I was ſent for in her name, I could not have known her, I took with me Pills and Antidote, I gave her two ſpoonfuls of my Antidote, which did anſwer my expectation, for it put her into a breathing ſweat, and alſo ſhe ſlept a matter of four hours I ſtirred not my foot till thorow the bleſſing of God, I had very good ſigns of her recovery, but when I ſaw the ſurly behaviour of all, as well the ſervants as kindred thorow the whole family I did not wonder I was not cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led ſooner; the Gentleman himſelf I never ſaw all the time of the cure; the gentlewoman could truſt no creature with my things, I was fain to give with my own hands as much as poſſibly my buſineſs would permit, till the Gentlewoman got ſtrength and kept the Pills alwayes about her and and had regard to her ſelf; it was an unuſal time before this Gentlewoman could get abroad, the
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:30746:49"/>reaſon all may diſcern, was the withholding from her that which did her good; and in ſtead of it give her that which did no good, and being of a good nature, in this caſe proved to her great hurt; but bleſſed be God ſhe ſoon did attain health, and ſo remains uſing my Pills now and then to keep her in health as ſhe has occaſion.</p>
            <p>For Small Pox which generally doth light on children and young people, this I ſay upon good experience that my Pill is always good and profitable whenſoever it is taken at any time of the diſeaſe, either in the beginning of them, or the middle of them, or the latter end of them, it can never be taken a miſs except you give ſuch a doſſe as is not proper for them that take it, for it always ſtrengthens the vital ſpirits, cleanſeth the blood and fortifies the heart, and if the ſmall Pox be ſtruck in again, this Pill doth forthwith throw them out again, with great ſafety, as we have much expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience hereof, but if it be taken before they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, that nature be able, it will relieve them by working the Surfeit out by vomit, or by ſiege, or ſweat, or Urin, all the ways that nature hath to friend, but if the Surfeit have got ſtrength e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough that they cannot be prevented, then doth it throw them out in a moſt gallant eaſie manner, ſo that the patient being freed of all Feavoriſh ſymptomes, and alwayes lying in a breathing ſweat, is ſo ſweetly diſpoſed, as he doth hardly fail of a meals meat all the time he hath them up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, but ſuddainly will recover with great ſtrength and freedom.</p>
            <p>A luſty young man having got many Surfeits
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:30746:50"/>one upon another, felt himſelf not well for two or three dayes together, but not knowing what ſicknes was, would not yield unto it while he was able to hold up his head, and being in my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany much complained how ill he was, and that he doubted he ſhould be able to hold up his head no longer, I gave him preſently a little Pill about four grains, which now he is well one ſix fold ſo big would hardly fur him, but as ſoon as it was well down his throat, he fell into a vomiting with extream violence, I could tell him his breaſt was full of poiſon, but what was the matter fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with him I did not know, for the preſent he had ſome eaſe after his vomiting; I gave him a Pill at leaſt 18 grains to take when he went to bed, which he did, and that in like ſort ſet him a vomit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing moſt of that night and moſt of the next day, it alſo purged his gall of divers collours, but the woman where he lay would let him take no more; the two that I leſt for him ſhe threw them in the fire, and cries out againſt my Pills for mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him ſick; but that night the Small Pox appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed all over his ſkin, and being over-ruled was not ſo happy as to continue with my Pills which had drove them from his heart into his ſkin, and for want of more the diſeaſe grew extream upon him, and he all over covered with them and in flux extreamly, and was for a time ſtark diſtract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and talked idle of he knew not what; they imployed two called Doctors but to no purpoſe, indeed it was beyond all mens judgement that he did eſcape withliſe; but as ſoon as he was maſter of himſelf, he called for mare of my Pills which he had, but did not vomit any more, he ſaith, and I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:30746:50"/>will ſay while he liveth, that nothing that ever he took did him any good but my Pills which did free his heart of them, and as means did ſave his life, which is undoubtedly true, and I am confident if they had been given to ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that which I did give him his ſickneſs would not have been above the tenth of what it was, for ſuch is our experience that if it cannot alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether prevent them, yet it doth ſo diſpoſe them that they are not like the diſeaſe, for ſome that in reaſon would have been as bad as any, yet by their conſtant and thorow uſe of my Pills all the time of their being ill have hardly miſſed one meals meat, but quickly with ſtrength and vigor have been reſtored.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It helpeth the ſhaking and trembling of the joynts, ſtrengtheneth the brains and increaſeth memory.</hi> I have already ſpoke enough of the Palſie or ſhak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the joynts, &amp; for ſtrengthening of the brain and memory, I ſay, I am thorow Gods rich mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and goodneſs a living monument and teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of its true vertue, power and effect, for they are at this day far better then when I was but ſeventeen yeers old, and my ſight as good as ever ſince I had them for any thing I can perceive, and that is as good as any I think in the world, and although there is a ſleepineſs or dullneſs the next day in many that takes it, which is not uſed to it, they find it ſeldom ſo the third day, but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of heavineſs, all for the moſt part do finde a wonderful lightneſs of heart and chearfulneſs of body all over, that they think themſelves as if they were in a new world, and yet it muſt be
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:30746:51"/>granted that if any ones grief lies in their head, that then it will he nimble and accute both to ſearch it out and help it if it pleaſe God to permit, for it is evident it works moſt where moſt cauſe is; many again doth find it fully to anſwer their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ctation, and yet never find it to work in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r heads at all, although they have taken it in great quantity, and let one thouſand take it, and they will all tell of ſeveral effects as eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one differs in one kind or other; alſo their ailes and their different judgements upon thoſe ailes, for very well we know let all ſpeak and judge as they will, that the whole of it to all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents and purpoſes in all the operations of it, is to ſtrengthen and fortifie nature from head to heel, and many which have and do take much of it have confidently ſuppoſed, that I have not made it ſo good at one time as at another, becauſe they find oft times contrary effects and operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as ſometimes to be dry, and ſometimes not, and ſometimes ſweat much, and ſometimes not at all, and ſometimes break wind much, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times not at all; and ſo in many other caſes it is indeed daily evidenced, for as is ſaid as a mans ailes is ſo will it work, it is they that alter, the Pill is the ſame. Note, therefore that you may know I cannot make ſuch alterations in the mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it, becauſe I do give none but what took his beginning three years and upward ago, yet I muſt confeſs it is wonderful to obſerve that ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times it will have a double effect to what it will have at another time, as in caſes of colas and Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feits and the like, or ſome evil quality is gotten
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:30746:51"/>in the ſtomach, it will abide no ſuch thing but will aſſault that that aſſaults nature what ever it be.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Revives and comforts the heart.</hi> The like revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver I think for a creature of God, I do from my heart believe, and by experience I find (as much occaſion as I have had in the world) the world never injoyed the like with it; and let me now bleſſ and praiſe the moſt high, who onely beareth rule in heaven above and in the earth beneath; the time has been, and that a long and tedious time to me many yeers together, I have been ſo oppreſſed and loaden with pains and feebleneſs of heart, as if I always carried a quarter of an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred weight perpetually in my cheſt or breſt, and I went alwayes as if loaden, that it hath made me make a wrinkled face to ſtir out of my way to give place either to horſe or Cart, as for men I al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways would be ſure to give them room enough; I ever going with pain and anguiſh, and full of ſighing; and truely although I was poor, yet was I then filled with ſuch pain as I ſhould have hard-have ſtooped to have took up a penny; but now thorow mercy (that which is true will hardly be credited) I find my ſelf ſet at liberty, that to my own feeling I do not weigh upon my ſhoos, as I go up and down, not one ounce, my heart is ſo light, freed from all oppreſſion, my body ſo clean and nimble; and whereas I was grown ſtiff, that I did ſenſibly perceive that thorow much weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs I began to ſtride ſhort; now my leggs are at liberty, that to my thinking I can never tread wide enough, and at this inſtant of writing, I
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:30746:52"/>took my right foot in my right hand, and did lift my heel to my mouth without the help of the other hand, and all over my whole man without any exception; God by this Pill hath thus renewed me, I do with joy and laughter give my enemies leave to charm againſt my Pill, what is ſpoke is no fable, it is apparently diſcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, eſpecially of all thoſe that in times paſt did know me, and many with me, who with weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and old age have ſtrided ſhort and narrow, their ſilver cords as it were tyed together, ſo that they ſtride little, and that with ſtagering, have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived their leggs again with the uſe of this Pill, and are amongſt us which bear teſtimony, who themſelves are ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cht off their languiſhing beds and in joy their limbs with comfort.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In women it brings them to due Courſes, whether they want or abound.</hi> So is our experience for the moſt part, and this may be eaſily diſcerned for opening all obſtructions.</p>
            <p>One maid of about twenty eight years of age, being obſtructed about five or ſix years, in ſo much as ſhe grew very diſeaſed and troubled with ſtrange fits, and one of her leggs grew as bigg as three leggs, and did alſo break and run; this maid was weary of her life, her racking pains was ſuch, as ſhe did roar out in ſuch hideous man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as was ſore oppreſſive unto her friends, help ſhe could get none; ſhe meets with my Pills and over charging her ſelf, threw them away as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing afraid of them, that which ſhe had taken working a little higher then ſhe would have had it; about a yeer after ſhe comes to me with her
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:30746:52"/>ſiſter, &amp; makes lamentable complaint, and ſhewed me her legg with ſtinking Ulcers in it; ſhe follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed my Pill with more diſcretion then at firſt, it was not above a month, but it freed her of all her fits, brought her into an orderly and monthly Flux, took down her legg and made it no bigger then the other, and healed the Ulcers; ſhe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed ſo much health as ſhe marries a huſband, and lived comfortably with him, and buried him, and married another; all this to my knowledge, and what is become of her now I know not: theſe confirmations I do not want, neither do I wiſh any man more harm to himſelf, then to think ſo ill of my Pill as not to uſe it in his need; but for me, the maſter that I have always ſerved hath confirmed his mercy in bleſſing it to me and to many; unto him alone be all the praiſe and honor for ever Amen.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It is preſent help for any Flux or Scowring of blood, or otherwiſe, and ſtops them incontenantly.</hi> Although it be the Gomorha, or running of the Reins, or iſſue of blood, either at Urin or at Fundament, or any other Flux or Scowring, it is the moſt ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign help I think in the world, for if need be, it will as well purge as binde, and is frequently proved, but it will over-rule the grief and ſtop it by degrees as may be for the patients advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage; and if this Pill be laid open upon a well glazed diſh, and dried and mixed in conſerve of red Roſes, it is very proper on this occaſion, and this hath helped when <hi>Crocus Martis</hi> would do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, nor the Sugar of <hi>Saturn,</hi> all which are as forcible, almoſt as art, I have proved it, for if
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:30746:53"/>theſe have ſtopped, they have thrown the pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent into intollerable pains and rackings, beſide feaver but this ſo pleaſantly, ſo gently and ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that it is the deſire and joy of the patient to have a Pill in his belly.</p>
            <p>A luſty man a Trumpeter, who had been at the Eaſt Indies, brought ſuch a Flux home with him, that could not be ſtaid by what means ſoever could be uſed to that end, and his weakneſs is not to be credited &amp; yet live, and after he came home in this condition it was one year and a half or two years before he applied himſelf unto my Pill, and although his conſtant manner was to purge ſix or eight times in the night, the firſt Pill ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped him and eaſed him, and that in a wonderful manners; I ſhall not want the benefit of this mans prayers while he and I do live together; and as is ſaid my Pill did not violently ſtop him, but by degrees naturally, and when thorow impatience he had got ſome violent aſtringer as thoſe above, he was all torn in his limbs and glad to take my Pill to withſtand their force; but becauſe this fie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Accrimony had cut aſunder all retention tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row length of time, his water for the moſt part going that way; I for my part did diſpaire of his cure, for he would even affrighted one to behold him, yet it hath pleaſed God to be ſo favorable unto this poor man, as that he is now in health, and doth ſound a Trumpet in Colonel <hi>Riches</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment, and who liſt to ſpeak with him ſhall hear much more then I have ſaid, to Gods glory and your wonder, whether friend or enemy. I ſee the bleſſing, of God which he hath afforded unto
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:30746:53"/>poor people, for they will come and ask find help; this is Gods bleſſing, the rich oft aſk and pay large, and go without help, this is a ſore evil under the Sun; ſome cries out againſt it as a great binder or ſhutter up of theirb dies, if it be ſo to any, I am ſure it is to their great benefit, in taking off from them windineſs, alſo Feavoriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, or thoſe other diſtempers they take them for, I am alſo ſure that there is not one in a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, but that although it doth bind them a little at the beginning, but that they find it to purge at at the latter end; I do grant ſome bodies to be drier then other, and for theſe when they have a neceſſity to uſe it by reaſon of weakneſs, let them uſe it with Sirrope of Roſes, in ſuch quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty as doth make it friendly with them, or that which is for ſome better, take equal parts of Sca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony called Diagredium, or make it ſo as to ſuit their conſtitutions, but my advice is in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter not to do it but with good advice, and that there do appear an apparent neceſſity for it, it will frequently aſtring for three, four or five days, and afterwards keep you looſe while you take it, if the cauſe continue for which you take it, you may thus deal with it, otherwiſe if you have need of it in its ſtrength, then ſuffer it to follow its own law, and you will not repent your ſelf, be of what temper you will; there are ſome ſuch whom it hath purged the moſt of all, which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe have been moſt aſtringent; no man knoweth how it will work with him till he have proved it; I my ſelf have gone four or five days without any ſtool, and have wondred what
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:30746:54"/>would become of all I have put into my belly, for I did eat my meat all that time as heartily as ever I did in my life, and was as well indeed, I may ſay in a new world, for it was at firſt when I took it, and all that time I did break wind free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, neither had I the leaſt fumes or ſwelling, or any thing like unto oppreſſion, nor any heat which made me wonder, and indeed may, for it is much againſt common experience; nay further all that four or five days I could have laid my bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to my back, ſo free was I from any kind of ſwelling, then at four or five days end (I confeſs I have forgot whether) all went in a light ſtool, which did lye above like a Cork, and after that it did ever bring me belly to an orderly courſe once every day, and rather purgative, and ſo I remain with much health thorow the bleſſing of of God, and can make my ſelf purge when I will with pleaſure, but I dare not purge, all is well, I have no need, this Pill alwayes doth, as I may ſay, watch over me, and oft doth find matter ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to purge by ſiege, and ſometimes by Urin, and ſome times by ſweat; I do obſerve theſe changes, but the reaſon and cauſe of it I do not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand; I know my Pill is the ſame, but change of all things with me, doth ſometimes work a change in my Pills operation; it is for the moſt part a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant rule with my Pill to purge men or women of groſs corpulent bodies, but people of ſpare and thin bodies not ſo; if any by good experience do find that it doth bind them, and that alſo they find that that binding is indeed hurtful above that which is imaginary, for I know many complain
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:30746:54"/>for no cauſe, but that their cuſtom is broke, and that it doth not follow the order as they would have it, but I ſay if it do indeed in this caſe offend, a gliſter then may be neceſſary for them, onely this you muſt obſerve either in gliſter or in purg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Phyſick, to keep as far off the taking of the Pill as you can, leaſt it ſhould not ſuffer the por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to work, that is, take the purging Phyſick at leaſt two or three dayes after the Pill is taken, or elſe you may expect that that portion will not work, for you muſt know that the purging quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in the portion is from a poiſonous quality, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe it could not purge, and that quality my Pill doth ſo perfectly correct, as you may expect it do nothing, but I do much rather wiſh you if there be cauſe indeed, then to uſe a ſafe gliſter of milk from the Cow and Sugar onely which will produce no evil effects; you may note that as its correction is leſs, ſo its force is leſs, therefore if you with the Pill add a purger, as Scamony or Sirrop of Roſes, or ſome other, it may be it may fute your body, and all this diſcourſe is to pleaſe thee as it were a ſingle perſon and is indued with goodwill and hath need of it; but I do certainly know the poiſe of nature is moſt happy and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for man, for the generality of them, and therfore cannot be altered, and if thou didſt know it, as it may be hereafter thou maiſt, thou wilt ſee nothing in it can be wanting, and alſo that additions would be vain, yet for thy ſake I have ſpoken, if it ſo fall out that the diſpoſition of thy body ſhould ſo far differ from others; I obſerve the general opinion of all, that is, if they be not
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:30746:55"/>in good order as you call it, then do they cry out of fumes, and it may be pairs in their head, and I grant that uſually it is ſo where this Pill is not, bur I aſſure you where this Pill is, is the clean contrary, for although they go not to ſtool for ſix or eight days, yet all that time there is no vapors nor ſumes not in one of an hundred; I confeſs if any will ſtrive thovow ill decorum to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards themſelves and tempt God, it is juſt theſe ſhould be anſwered accordingly; it is further for theſe to note, that if they take this Pill and let it come to powder out of the Sun, as that it will ſoon be, and then heat it to fine powder, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe it in White-wine, and ſo drink the extract of it, that then it doth not aſtring the half as it doth when you take the Terra with it, &amp; you will alſo find it more ſpirituous in effect; ſuch as have no need of it, may at a cheap rate let it alone: But again, thoſe that have need of it, had beſt be well adviſed how they neglect it for ſmall and impertinent matters; we have experience e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough of its juſt power to be both to bind and to looſe according unto natures law; thou that ſnuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fleſt at it becauſe thou haſt took two or it may be but one, it may be by fits more, do thou know if thou wilt uſe it and grow friendly with it, thou wilt find a contrary effect in its working, for it will now binde and by and by purge.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It ſtrengthens and openeth the Spleen, and tares a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way wind in a uncredible manner.</hi> This is the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant experience of all that take it, and I think not one of an hundred but will acknowledge it; but by my own experience I do add further, that
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:30746:55"/>although I have not been made ſenſible of a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent breaking of wind downward, yet before morning I have found all oppreſſion gone, my ſelf ſet free and lightſome, and I have not known which way, but my reaſon tells me, that lying in a gentle breathing ſweat, the Pores of my bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy being thereby all ſet open, wind hath thereby found ſecret and inſenſible paſſage, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times I have ſenſibly perceived it go by Urin, but his ordinary working is mightily downward as all in general finde it to do.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Drieth up Hydroppical humors.</hi> Things not to be credited it hath done in this diſtemper.</p>
            <p>An ancient man troubled with this diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per took it but in reaſonable doſs for one month together, the weather indeed was warm, it did ſweat him, as he told me, every night ſo mighti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that his maid ſaid it went thorow the Feather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed whereon he lay every night, and wrought as ſtrongly by Urin, and I do proteſt this man at the months end was freſher and fairer, and ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to his labor, then when I began with him, and is at this inſtant in good health, and this was three yeers agone from this preſent wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting.</p>
            <p>I ſhall write here a ſtrange and wonderful, but accidental cure, I think, as hath been heard of in this age; A young woman having languiſhed for a long time under very many diſeaſes, the worſt that uſually may attend an honeſt womans body, as the Dropſie, Stone, Conſumption or Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, ſhortneſs of Breath, fore fits of the Mother, Jaundies, as I did clearly fee by her eyes; this
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:30746:56"/>woman having ſpent much for a long time but in vain, ſhe grew worſe and worſe, and did diſpair of help in this world, ſhe was ſcarcely able to ſtand or breath, at the intreaty of good women of our country, I went to ſee her, ſhe being born within a mile where I was, I ſhould hardly have gone to her but that we were School-fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows at <hi>Nottingham,</hi> I ſound her in this ſad condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; I durſt promiſe nothing more then this, If I did her ho good I would do her no harm, I made her five or ſix ſmall Pills, with order to drink White-wine after them, and to take each night one, and as ſhe liked them, ſo let me hear from her; ſhe accordingly takes them, the third day her huſband comes to me with words of wonder and abundance of thanks, and told me that his wife was finely recovered, that ſhe had breath in good length and order, and ſlept well and began to eat, and that he had brought ſome of the Stones which ſhe voided with him to ſhew me, and ſaid he, what ſhall I ſay, your Pills have done more then poſſibly might have been imagined, I praiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed God with him, he took half an ounce of my Pills more with him, and becauſe of the fits of the Mother, I willed him to take half an ounce of my Oyl of Amber, and give her three drops in a ſpoonful of White-wine, and then drink a glaſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of White-wine, after it he went home, and the next morning gives her two ſpoonfuls of this Oyle, the woman faints with heat, as needs ſhe muſt, her heart being ſuffocated with fire, and the next morning he gives her the reſt of the half ounce, ſo that he gave her as much at twice
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:30746:56"/>as ſhould have ſerved two hundred times or near it, it is indeed a miracle that this woman was not deſtroyed, but orderly taken a better thing could not have been given to have helped and aſſiſted her Pills againſt thoſe fits of the Mother, this wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man receiving this half ounce into her body ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly fainted, her husband comes not to me, but runs unto a wiſe Doctor which could not ſee the power of Oyl of Amber, but clatters hard a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me and my Pills, but would give her no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but plentifully beſtowed the Gallows upon me for killing her, and without ſhame as a man that had but one ear, never ſearching the truth, meeting me, and near before a dozen people which ſtood by, charged me with killing this wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, &amp; before them all threatned me with holding up my hand at the Bar; I gave him not a word, it was neither time nor place, but liſted up my heart to God, knowing my own innocency, and was ſorry he ſhould do himſelf ſo much wrong, and of all men living I had deſerved better things at his hand; I did wonder to hear this charge, for I had not heard one word, neither did I, but what came from him till three months after; it pleaſed God that with what good this woman had receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from the Pills ſhe took before (for this Doctor did ſo fright them, that they thought it was my Pills that wrought ſo with her as that ſhe took no more; I ſay) altogether proved happy for the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, for at once ſhe was releaſed of all her diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes, and being well and about the ſtreet, an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Gentlewoman, Miſtris <hi>Tuching</hi> in Beadlam, calls to her and ſaid; you but the other day as it
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:30746:57"/>were was ill of many diſeaſes, and now you are ſo well of a ſuddain, you have got one good Medicin or other, I pray you let me have ſome of it; ſhe replied that ſhe had a Country man at the Tower gave Pills and that they had cured her, but they liked to have killed her, and that ſhe had the reſt of them at home but durſt not take any more of them, come ſaid Miſtris <hi>Tuching</hi> give them me, I will take them, which ſhe did, and when ſhe had ſpent them ſhe calls to her and told her that ſhe muſt bring her to the man, for ſhe muſt have more of thoſe Pills, and this was near three months before either I or the woman did know what it was that did hurt her; this ancient Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlewoman with my Country woman comes to my houſe, I not being at home, this woman asked for the Oyl I ſent her to take by ſpoonfuls, my maid told her that I had no Oyl that I gave by ſpoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuls; I had indeed an Antidote which I did give in ſpoonfuls; to be ſhort, this woman ſoon found the Bottle by its ſcent, and ſo ſhe and we came to know how ſhe came well as God hath ordered it, and ſhe hath remained well for this two years if not more, and hath born a child or two ſince; this is a true and faithful relation to the beſt of my remembrance, as I have it from their own mouths, and thanks be to God who hath kept me and will keep me in his way notwithſtanding the envy and rage of my enemies, ſo that thorow mercy I care not for it; yet notwithſtanding this Doctor in the fury of his malice hath took off thoſe good we men, and not a few more from the uſe of my Pill, which I know well will all turn to his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:30746:57"/>ſhame, I pray God forgive him with my whole heart, I am taught by him to take heed of making men idols.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In fine I know no diſeaſe that it doth not ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther perfectly eaſe or perfectly cure.</hi> Although this Bill hath now been made publike above this four years, and I had both reaſon and experience then enough to avouch it in my conſcience be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Almighty God, and experience enough to avouch it before men; there hath been added e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very ſince a daily load of experiences, which as a cloud of witneſſes confirm what I have pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed, for ſuch are indeed the wonders of God daily brought to our ears, ſome of which I have related unto you, and indeed as I may ſay the happyreturns of prayer in the adminiſtring of this Pill doth abundantly ballance the bitterneſs of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy, and the falſe lies and forgeries of the wilful ignorant and by the conſtant meetings together of a catologue of mercies upon mercies, all of them pleading my juſt cauſe againſt the proudeſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temner; I do therefore with joy ſubmit to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, knowing that reproach ſhall be the por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the happy in this life, and if the Lord whom I ſerve did not by his conſtant preſence and bleſſing upon my labor, give vigor and life unto my juſt and honeſt indeavor for the good of mankind, I ſhould have been charmed and frighted off from this my imployment the higheſt hath called me unto, but putting my truſt in him, ſhall proceed in his name with joy, fear, love, and trembling, not doubting but he that is able to keep that which in his name I have committed unto
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:30746:58"/>him, who hath and doth keep me in all my ways, will never fail me of his bleſſed protection and aſſiſtance in well-doing; and ſuch hath been my care and indulgence towards all always, that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept people deſperately preſumptious, both to abuſe themſelves and me, they cannot lightly hurt themſelves; and while I am now writing I will give an inſtance or two which comes into my mind, which will make good what I now drive at. A woman a Nurſe keeper comes to us for one quarter of an ounce of my Pills, which my wife weighed her; another ſtaying for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſhe having her own catcht up the other out of the ſcale and popt it into her mouth and ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed it all at once, and away ſhe goes; I had a friend with me by the fire-ſide, my wife being frighted cried out the woman would kill her ſelf, we wondred to ſee her skip away ſo faſt, but did not well conceive the matter, about four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen days after my maid met her in Tower-ſtreet, asked her how ſhe did with that quantity of Pill at once in her belly, ſhe told her that ſhe was well, and that ſhe ſat up all that night with her child which ſhe did Nurſe, onely it did make her head-ach a little; this relation is true, but not to be followed without danger, I neither knew her name nor her dwelling, to adminiſtred any thing to have over-ruled it; I do think this propoſtorus act of this woman may ſhew unto all men its ſaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, if there be any reaſon uſed in the admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring of it; and whereas I ſay, I have taken it my ſelf twelve months, it is true that I have taken it now almoſt five yeers, and have not I am ſure miſſed it in all the time from firſt till this preſent
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:30746:58"/>it me not twenty nights, neither ſhall I miſs it ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept it ſhould pleaſe God to grant me a better (of which I now have little hope) and the effects thorow divine goodneſs are with me bleſſed; I always have need of it as of a ſtronge cordial al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I do not alwayes uſe the ſame quantity, for I never weighed one for my ſelf in all my life, but I make them bigger or leſſer as I find my ſelf to have more or leſs need of them; and when I am as well as I could wiſh, I do take a little one to keep me ſo, but if I get cold or ought elſe that troubles me I do then take one bigger, and this I find by conſtant experience, and I do aſſure you it is no more then what is true, that it never fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me, but always comes with freſh ſtrength and reviving as truely and effectually as when I took it at firſt, and not like other things which with much uſe will looſe their vertue, power, and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, but my Pill is ever the ſame, working high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er or lower as it finds cauſe, and according unto the quantity that is taken, ſo that what change is, is not in it but in me; and I do further con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm what I formerly ſaid as to the in joying of my health and chearfulneſs thorow many weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, for ſuch is the clearneſs of my body, and freeneſs from any obſtructions, that I have run from the firſt ſtep of my houſe unto the higheſt ſtep upon the leads on the houſe top and never draw my breath; alſo ſuch eaſe and chearfulneſs of heart, that as I go along the ſtreet it is as if I did not tread on the ground, and as I have oft ſaid, ſo I do ſay again, that to my thinking I do not weigh one ounce upon my ſhoo-heels. Now my
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:30746:59"/>ſleeve for the moſt part is full of pins that I gather from the ground, but when I hung upon my Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors ſleeve, I always was ſo oppreſſed and filled with pains, and ſo ſore oppreſſed and loaden at my Breaſt, that although poor, yet ſhould hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly have ſtooped to have taken up a penny, and if I had ſtooped upon any occaſion, I did not know how to get up again without great pain and difficulty, and with the help of my hands up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on my knees; I further found and do find my limbs to lengthen or ſet at liberty, which before was ſtiff as if they were ſhrunk, now I can leap run or any ſuch like thing with refreſhing, which before was far from me: What ſhall I ſay, I am thorow mercy a living monument of his mercies and of Gods bleſſing upon this Pill, for near this five years I have not uſed any other thing but it and my Antidote, and ſometimes of my Oyle of Amber, and if theſe ſhould fail me, as I know not how ſoon they may; I ſuppoſe I ſhould hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſend over the threſhold for what is elſwhere to be gained for mony, yet I will deal freely and truely with you, I have been put ſo to it upon extraordinary occaſions of Feavors, colds and aguiſh infections to take four Pills of good big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, betwixt eight at night and ten the next day, allowing three or four hours betwixt each Pill, and I do the rather report this, becauſe I know it will be exemplary to many, for ſuch hath been my weakneſs that if I did not take a Pill in the time aforeſaid I ſhould faint, beſides the help of high cordial waters and burnt wine, and in ſtead of cold mortal Julips, in a Feavor I make
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:30746:59"/>uſe of theſe comfortable things not fearing my Feavor, if I can but hold up my vital ſpirits, and let my Pill and Feavor try the maſtery; I know according unto Gods appointment it ſhall be but for ſo many years thorow twenty Feavors which have been apparent thus have I been helped, for if one Pill will be to weak it muſt be aſſiſted with another, and if two be too weak it muſt be aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with a third, and if three be too weak it muſt be aſſiſted with a fourth; thus far I have gone with it my ſelf, and ſeldom it is that a Feavor ſtaid with me twenty four hours, or hardly ever to keep me in a doors all the next day, but by after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon likely I am maſter of it; and let all take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice that it is far better to take a little and oft, that is to ſay, four hours aſunder, as I did and do my ſelf if there be occaſion, ſo will it work ſweetly and powerfully with eaſe and delight; and whereas I ſpake of the ſtopping of ſome of my Organical parts, they were my ears and noſe, my ears ſo opened, that when I held my breath and blew, the wind would flye thorow both my ears, I could perceive it by making my hair fly on both ſides, and indeed they are both as good as ever ſince they were mine, which before the uſe of my Pill were weak and defective; I do therefore always renew my thanksgiving unto God for ſo great a mercy beſtowed upon me now in the latter end of my days, for as I have ſaid often, ſuch hath been my continued pains and anguiſh for above twenty years that I have not known the hour in all that time wherein I have took ſo much pleaſure in my life as to deſire to live it out; I
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:30746:60"/>joyfully acknowledge unto the praiſe of my ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter which I have ſerved from my youth up with an upright and perfect heart, that in all that time the joys of a better life were always ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my face, with the lively beams thereof al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways kept alive in my heart, and thorow mercy I durſt not complain nor ſay my burden was too heavy for me, I ever abhord ſuch thoughts as too ignoble for a Chriſtian that puts his truſt in Gods free mercy in Chriſt; I perpetually cried aloud for ſtrength to bear and ſuffer his will, and it was enough for me, the maſter that I always have ſerved never ſuffered the croſs to be two heavy and burthenſom to me, I know well it croſſed no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but an unbelieving, corrupt, and carnal mind. I have oft wondred conſidering my ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent weakneſs, wherefore I did live or had life permitted me, foraſmuch as I could not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern which way I was likely to perform ſervice, either unto God or unto man, more then this that it was for my Lord and Maſters power to reſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me, and to manifeſt his glory in my great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmity, but now I am apt to think that I am pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, as with joy I do find, to be a bleſſing and a refreſhing unto many, and truely the poverty and ſickneſs, rejection of friends and relations which has paſt me, doth not (as it doth with too many) ſet me on to take hold on riches or make haſt to be rich, or fill my ſelf with the profits and pleaſures of this life, but much rather if it were poſſible for me, ſuch is the burning deſire of my heart, I ſay, I would if poſſible bear the ſickneſs and bitterneſs of all men, and frequently with joy
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:30746:60"/>and tears when I have heard the returns of thoſe poor which by my hand as a weak inſtrument; I ſay when they have told the great things <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Lord hath done for them, my ſoul within me hath revived with praiſe and thanſgiving that I am and have been ſpared unto ſo great and bleſſed a work as the Lord imploys me in; I ſee alſo and perceive why I my ſelf have been trained up in affliction, to the end I might learn of the true pattern of all obedience, Jeſus Chriſt, who came not to do his own will, but the will of him that ſent him, who ſpeaking of thoſe that are his and have intereſt in him, as of ſons and children, that he took part with them, to wit, fleſh and blood, the nature of <hi>Abraham,</hi> not Angels, and was tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pted as a man, that he might ſuccor thoſe that are tempted and learn to be a merciful Saviour; and let me ſpeak further, whether my heart deceive me God knoweth, it is my perpetual ſupplication that I might rather dye and ſeaſe, then that this my rejoycing ſhould be made void, but that I may truly and faithfully do likewiſe unto the utmoſt of my power always ready to joyn my ſhoulder un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him that is ready to fall, ſupporting, comforting and aſſiſting according unto what I have received extended always unto him that is ſick and feeble of heart; and thorow mercy there is a good witneſs for the time paſt (I doubt not) recorded in heaven; and I further hope to increaſe it thorow the bleſſed aſſiſtance of him who ſhews mercy un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the poor and needy in their diſtreſs.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:30746:61"/>
               <head>Directions how to take this Pill aright.</head>
               <p>LEt it be underſtood that each one according unto his age, ſtrength, or weakneſs is to take a portion ſeverally.</p>
               <p>The ordinary doſſe is the biggneſs of a gray peaſe ſwelled, or twelve grains, or ten, or four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen grains to twenty grains where is ſtrength, but to a child new born no more then a pin-head, and not a great one neither, but about one quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of a grain. My advice and councel is to all both old and young that they be ſure they take little enough at firſt, and in ſo doing there is great ſafty, always having regard to the ſtrength and condition of the patient, &amp; foraſmuch as the thing in its one property is a mear cordial, and a great fortifier of nature, too much you may take with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſafty, as a man may drink too much wine, but too little you cannot take as to ſafty, ſo that the leaſt grain is profitable to whole nature, and not in the leaſt prejudicial; therefore I do warn and charge that you begin with little enough, and that you do increaſe afterward as you find by good experience the patient can bear it, unto a child of ten or twenty hours old give as much as a ſmall pins-head, and ſo increaſe with care as you ſhall find it to work, it at once brings them to reſt, cauſeth them to eat and ſuck luſtily, and drives out any thing amiſs in them; and for a
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:30746:61"/>child a year old give as much as a great pin-head, ſtill increaſing as you do perceive ſtrength to bear it, but it is better to give it either to old or young a little and oft, always taking it when you are going to bed or in bed, and you muſt alow twelve or fourteen hours unto its working, and above all things take heed of colds, but if you ſhould get a cold, haſte to bed, take a good Pill, it is gone, it will do no hurt, if you find your head to be giddy and unſettled, and alſo your ſtomach to be heaving, it is beſt to give it time and repoſe by ſleep, leaſt you be very ſick and vomit, which you will not do if your ſtomach be not very foul; note that it is not in its ſtrength till four or five hours taken; there is no obſervation of diet, but for men and women to keep a wholſom open &amp; clean diet, avoyding all things that is cold and windy in ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, but always keep your ſtomach warm with that which is good &amp; wholeſom; alſo always drink a wine-glaſs of the beſt Beer, Ale or Wine after the taking of the Pill; it is to be noted that if a mans head and breaſt be well he may riſe at any time; I my ſelf do frequently riſe after the taking my laſt Pill about two hours, this is in hot weather, not but that I muſt ſleep after again; you muſt further give what time you will, if your ſtomach be foul and poiſonous you will vomit, I do in the Winter time frequently when I am abroad and find my ſelf not well, take a little Pill of four grains or a grain or two more, as I like my ſelf, and drink a cup of good Beer after it, this doth raiſe me up beyond all belief, its common opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is by ſweat and Urin which you may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:30746:62"/>as you pleaſe, you ſhall find that a double portion will have a double effect, ſo that you may do what you will with your ſelf; it is fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be noted, that after three or four days this Pill will purge your body but with haſt and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; generally it doth purge, you will alſo find a fiery ſharp humor to go away, and although it make you a little ſore for the preſent, yet will you have cauſe to give thanks to God for its diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge, although with pain; you will do well to let it take its own courſe and follow natures law; it oft appears moſt by Urin, I know many becauſe of its ſtrange working have ſlighted it, and left it, and ſpake ill of it thorow their own fears, unto their own hurt, and yet at laſt it hath been their laſt and beſt refuge, theſe are not a few in and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi>London,</hi> and now who ſhall commend it like theſe; it is no new thing to have the beſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances thrown by, if they do not in all things ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear according unto received circumſtances, I do wiſh all that are weak to do as I do my ſelf, to uſe this Pill more or leſs as they find occaſion, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways have within their reach a cup of the beſt, a ſpoonful of good cordial-water is good in cold weather; my Pill doth hate all ſmall drinks that are fomented or wrought with yeaſt, which fills with Wind and Rhums, keep ever your ſtomach warm with wholeſom meat and drink, and care not for being a little hot, let it ſuffice thee that my Pill although hot, yet doth it kill all unnatural heat whatever; I have always by me a bottle of a rich cordial-water, and a pot of ſtrong Beer, or Ale with Sugar, or of the Sirrop of black Cheries,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:30746:62"/>which after my way of making doth excel, and ſometimes I do uſe theſe apart, and ſometimes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, as I do find my ſelf, and ſometimes none of them all, but of any drink whatever it be, be not to free with it at one time, but rather a little and oft; you will find this Pill to coarſe and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low wind up and down from head to heel, as a dogg followeth a Hare thorow every hedge and buſh, and in this working you will of a ſuddain find a little faintneſs, then a ſpoonful of that which is beſt is acceptable and well applied, at that time beſure to keep your head on your Pillow, and while one would tell fourty it is gone; and thus it will do till it hath found ſome natural purger for his enemy, but if thou doſt not break wind by a ſenſible way of evacuation, yet thou ſhalt find it gone thou knoweſt not which way, thou maiſt obſerve that thy Pores are ſet open all over thy body, and by ſecret breathings at thoſe little Pores, it will oft make his way, and ſometimes by Urin it will follow natures law, and uſe thoſe purges which is moſt apt and ſpontaneous; and what pains ſoever thou haſt old or new will give way and thou at eaſe, as if thou ailedſt nothing, for the moſt part it is ſo, but if thou find it rake too high upon an old grief, know it is in order to heal and cure it; therefore I ſay, condeſcending unto thy weakneſs and unbelief, prove it firſt with a little and increaſe with judgement, as you find ſtrength and courage to bear it, thou maiſt know that it hath power, if thou haſt wiſdom to apply it.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="98" facs="tcp:30746:63"/>It falls out oft upon ſurly grieſs, as Sciatica and Gout in the feet, that it will nibble at them more ſtrongly then thou wouldſt, therefore mark what I have ſaid to thee.</p>
               <p>In my firſt Bill I did not commend it to women with child, both becauſe my Pill is not now as then, neither had I experience, but now I do commend it to them above any thing in the world for the health both of mother and child, and if young women would avoyd green and hurtful fruits and windy things, and inſtead thereof keep a good and wholeſom diet, and now and then, if cauſe, to uſe of theſe Pills, we ſhould not have ſo many miſerable weak children; but women will ſo palpably inſlave their own healths and lives and their infants unto a fooliſh luſt, to that which proves pernitious unto both, obſerving neither what is for their own or their infants health and wellfare.</p>
               <p>I will relate one ſtory of a woman with child, one that lived about Safoxus-mills in Southwark, and this woman was extreamly tormented, but did not know what it was that troubled her, ſhe had took divers things but to no purpoſe, and ſo it was that her pains<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> did exceed, that ſhe was weary of her life; this woman meets with one of my Pills, but how I did not know till after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, and without leave takes it at a venter, and contrary unto its uſual courſe, it ſet this woman a purging, and gave her above twenty ſtools, and then brought from her an abortive or falſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, whereat ſhe was well and ſo continued <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the month that ſhe had to go, and in her ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:30746:63"/>was delivered of a luſty boy very well, and ſo both mother and child continue well for any thing as ever I heard, praiſed be God, and after we heard of this woman, we likewiſe heard of others which did take it in the very hour of tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel with happy ſucceſs, and with much eaſe, more then ever they brought child into the world be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and now lately it is grown common with women that know it and uſe it in the time of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with child, to take it in their extremity, and alſo to give it their child as ſoon as born, if they diſcern cauſe.</p>
               <p>I will now give you one inſtance or two of ſome that have uſed it preſumptionſly, and have took too much of it, it may be ſuch like experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences will admoniſh the unruly to uſe a good thing to a good purpoſe and not abuſe themſelves thereby.</p>
               <p>About a month ago I chanced to light into the company of a man that lives near <hi>London</hi>-bridge in Theams-ſtreet, he ſaid he lay one night with a Gentleman which lay at his houſe, this Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man having of my Pills in a ſilver box, took one himſelf, and left his box on the table and went to bed, this man he takes as much at twice as would have made five or ſix (he compared it to to his thumb end) the leaſt of which would have been enough for him, this portion did begin to work very high upon him, and he fell into a ſtrong vomitting in a ſtrong ſweat, and after a while he needs muſt go to ſtool, he in his ſweat goes down two p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ir of ſtairs to the houſe of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, and he proteſted to me that as he ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t upon the
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:30746:64"/>ſtool the ſweat did drop off him upon his feet; thus twice he went down two pair of ſtairs to purge, and very ill by fits, it made him that he thought he ſhould have dyed no other death, but ſays he, I will never take more of your Pills: this man is old enough to have ſeen his error and my Pills benefit, yet this is his concluſion, hence let all be admoniſhed to follow direction given, for his reſolution was as raſh as taking the Pills was, and carries ſo much folly in it, as it doth ſtand more need to be pitied then anſwered, for who ſeeth not but that if he had taken a portion fit for him how profitable it would have been to him.</p>
               <p>A child in Saint <hi>Martins</hi> being preſently helped of Rickets and ill digeſtion of meat and ſuch like griefs; another of their next neighbors comes in great haſte for another child in like condition, I gave her Pills as the other had, and ſhewed her by making a one or two what quantity ſhe ſhould give the child, ſhe follows my order the firſt day, and ſhe did ſenſibly diſcern ſuch a mighty change in the boy, both as to his breath and chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs all the next day as did much delight her, and ſaid ſhe, if ſo much as this little thing do my childe ſo much good, I will give it more, and that will do it more good (and indeed ſo it proved for it cured the boy) and ſhe gave it what ſhe thought good, I ſhall never know how much it was ſhe gave him, but the next day the child was very ſick and would eat nothing but oft fainted and vomitted much, ſhe ſends to me in great haſt and ſaid ſhe feared I had
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:30746:64"/>killed her child, I asked her ſiſter whom ſhe ſent if they had followed my direction, ſhe aſſured me that they had to a tittle; in the afternoon I went to ſee what was the matter, and by that time the boy was very wel and had broke thorow it, and the woman then told me what ſhe had done, and her ſiſter who affirmed that they had ſtrictly followed my rules, ſaid, did not I tell you you would kill the boy by giving him too much, thus you may ſee how I am dealt with, and I know in this I am not alone if this child had died, I ſhould have been called the killer of it, neither ſhould I ever have heard what the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther had done to it.</p>
               <p>While I am writing, at preſent came a man to me fit to be remembred, although out of place which for two years was ſore troubled with a ſharp eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Rhum falling from his head, that he was almoſt loſt, he looked blackiſh, yallow, wan, his eys dul, he was almoſt ſtarved for want of meat, he could nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther eat nor ſleep, he could get no help, Gods good hand direct him to me in a time of need, his throat and pallate of his mouth almoſt eat away, I look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into his mouth at his requeſt, there was a hole eat out I could have turned my finger in it, it was ſad to ſee; I did ſomewhat ſuſpect what diſeaſe it ſhould be, but indeed I think both he and his wife fears God and is innocent and chaſt in their lives; I gave this man one quartern of Pills, he came a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain in five or ſix days ſo altered, as I ſcarce knew him he did look ſo chearful, freſh, his eyes quick, his throat almoſt well, ſo much more ſet him quite well, and ſo he continues and he it may be ſpends
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:30746:65"/>one quartern in one quarter of a year upon him ſelf; I confeſs I never in my life, as I can remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber knew the like, what the man ailed I cannot tell, it is ſufficient thorow Gods bleſſing even at once, as water would quench fire, ſo effectually did my Pill adminiſter healing unto him, which did quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly make him pull out the ſtuff wherewith he had ſtoped it with.</p>
               <p>To conclude I think I need not ſpeak more to my Pill or how to uſe it, for what is related in the ſeveral examples or experiences, will be as land marks to guide each one how and when to make application to themſelves and friends with comfort and faſty, ſo as they need not to trouble themſelves or me for further direction how to uſe it, and for ſuch as are not therewith ſatisfied I do heartily deſire they would let it alone, and I do aſſure them, that if they have no need of my Pills, that my Pills have no need of them, and further I add that from my heart I do intreat all who and whatever they be that have a half perſwaſion to take and try my Pills, that if that they be not ſo well perſwaded of them as to think of them to be proper means for their health, ſo as to pray for Gods bleſſing upon their uſe, that all ſuch what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they be would let them alone. I know the Atheiſtical profaneneſs of many which laugh when perſwaded to joyn faith and prayer in its uſe, their wickedneſs and folly needs no anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:30746:65"/>
               <head>Here followeth a Catalogue of names with their dwellings, of ſuch as have uſed or knoweth the uſe of my Pill, of whom you may inquire.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Henry Bonner, Fiſh-ſtreet-hill, at the Katherin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wheel.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Gibert Branden at the Swan and Bridge, at Bridge-foot.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Tho. Isgate, Bridge foot.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mrs.</hi> Hudſon Martins-lane, old Swan.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mrs.</hi> Mardin Angel-alley by Cole-harbor.</item>
                  <item>William Hawkins Butcher Eaſtcheap.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mrs.</hi> Jones Ducksfilld lane.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mrs.</hi> Fellkin, Mark-lane by Tower-ſtreet.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mrs.</hi> Bargman, Tower-ſtreet.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Nicholes, Tower-hill.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Robinſon, by the Scaffold on Tower-hill.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Nuttall, by the Poſtern Tower-hill.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mrs.</hi> Leine <hi>alias</hi> Green, Cater-lane.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mrs.</hi> Roles by the Iron-gate.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Barham Maniſter of Saint Tellins.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mrs.</hi> Laugham, Saint Tellins.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Liggon, Whit-hart-court without Biſhopſgate.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mrs.</hi> Proſſer, Half-Moon-alley little Morefields.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mrs.</hi> Lewis, Prieſt-alley Tower-ſtreet.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mrs.</hi> Thornton, Mint Tower.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> John Renals, Say maſter Tower his maid-ſervent.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Nathaniel Marſh, Monier in the Tower.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mrs.</hi> Hunt, Gravel lane Starch-maker.</item>
                  <item>
                     <pb n="104" facs="tcp:30746:66"/>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Andrews, Coopers Alms houſes Ratcliff.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Crainton, Ratcliff-croſs.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Roe, Ratcliff-croſs.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Gibſon, Ratcliff-croſs.</item>
                  <item>William Hornbe, Woollwich.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>In Lime houſe.</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Tho. Coaſts.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> John Hoſtin.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mrs.</hi> Ann Eliot.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Edmond Harman.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mrs.</hi> Ann Pope.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mrs.</hi> Elizabeth Coats.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mrs.</hi> Joan Pirkins.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Tho. Haſtin.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mrs.</hi> Sarah Skenes.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mrs.</hi> Alice Hughes.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mrs.</hi> Mary Thomſon.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mrs.</hi> Prudence Perſall.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Ravins. Woollwich.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Packwood, Woollwich.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Hance Woollwich.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Barton Woollwich.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>In Ratcliff.</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> John Smart.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mrs.</hi> Mary Smart.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mrs.</hi> Mary Andrews.</item>
                  <item>Joſeph Barker.</item>
                  <item>Elizabeth Hadwine.</item>
                  <item>Ric. Dean.</item>
                  <item>John Dean.</item>
                  <item>
                     <pb n="105" facs="tcp:30746:66"/>Adam Haire.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Coppin,</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mrs.</hi> Stanton.</item>
                  <item>Joan Reares.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Kendal of Chattham.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Booth, Woollwich.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Comfort.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mrs.</hi> Biſhop, Maſe Southwark.</item>
                  <item>Mrs. Harris, Barnesbe-ſtreet Southwark.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Stevens, Barnesbe-ſtreet end.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Caskue, Battle-bridg.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Sharp, Saint Thomas Southwark.</item>
                  <item>Will. Whitlock, Saint Thomas Southwark.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Vere, Houndſdich Currier yard.</item>
                  <item>Tho. Dennis at the Bell Southwark.</item>
                  <item>Tho. Hakelion, Bank-ſide.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Brooks, Maiden-lane Southwark.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Clemant, Bank-ſide Southwark.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Tench, near Falkeon Southwark.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Morgin, Bankeſide.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Kettel, Barber in Tho. Southwark.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Nic. Parcks, New-ſtreet near Shoo-lane.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Pittman, Meal-market Southwark.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Chapman, Gravel-lane Houndſdich.</item>
                  <item>Abednego Child, Mileend.</item>
                  <item>Tabitha Eliat, Whitechapel Churchyard.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> James Hill, Coleman-ſtreet George-alley.</item>
                  <item>Sarah Taylor, Northumberland-Alley.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Bavin, Northumberland-alley.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Smith, Northumberland-alley.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Barber, Further Tower-hill new building.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mrs.</hi> Sillito, Tower-dock.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Huſſey, Thumberland-alley.</item>
                  <item>
                     <pb n="106" facs="tcp:30746:67"/>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Deadman, Halfinoon, Cornhill.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Smith, Cock at Longlane end Alderſgate-ſtreet.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Smith, Graver Gutter-lane.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Weaver, Clock-maker at the Pumpe, Broad-ſtreet end.</item>
                  <item>Widow Smith at the A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>chor in Coleman-ſtreet.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Barton, Nags-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ead-alley, Biſhopſgate-ſtreet.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Fromantell, Clock-maker at the Millel Duck-lane by the Hoſpital.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Prime, Angel-alley at Thumberland-alley end, Allgate.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> James at <hi>Mr.</hi> Fromantells.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Lomes, Clock-makey <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> at the Mermaid.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mrs.</hi> Burrows, at the three Cocks Lothberry.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Loddinton, Barber Lothbery. <hi>Weſtminſter.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Edward Batterbes, Ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>-ſtreet.</item>
                  <item>Joh. Fells, Kings-ſtreet.</item>
                  <item>Law. Dibes, Kings-ſtreet.</item>
                  <item>Simon Clesbe, Mill-bank.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mrs.</hi> Barnes, Petty-France.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mrs.</hi> Alerige, Tuttle-ſtreet.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mrs.</hi> Kellſall, little Wood-ſtreet.</item>
                  <item>Captain Robinſon, Tuttle-ſtreet.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Joſ. Sprige, Whirehall.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Seal, Braſier Cat-eaten-ſtreet.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mrs.</hi> Heaſſell, Checker Wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lin-ſtreet.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Roberts, Lower end of Broad-ſtreet.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Barber in Fire-ball-court Hounſdich.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Hamon, lower end of Broad-ſtreet.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Jeſſeries, in fireball Court Hounſdich.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Ward, Exciſe Office.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Barnard, Exciſe Office.</item>
                  <item>
                     <pb n="107" facs="tcp:30746:67"/>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Boulſtrod, Surgis-hall.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Eſterle, Exciſe Office.</item>
                  <item>Collonel Potter of Richmond.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Prichit of Richmond.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Bacon, Controler Ely-houſe.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mrs.</hi> Rawbone, New Bridewell.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mrs.</hi> Cuttler, Charter-houſe.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Hawood, Seven ſtars Lamber-ſtreet.</item>
                  <item>Andrew Dancy, Abchurch-lane.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Laſhle Barbar, Colledge-hill.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Williams, Nelins court Black-fryers.</item>
                  <item>Ric. Andrews, Whitechappel.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Loveday, Spittlefeils.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Clement, Silkman Cheapſide by the Bull-head.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Richards, Baſing-lane.</item>
                  <item>Captain Johnſon, lower end Bow-lane.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Melliſh, Trinity-lane Baker.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mrs.</hi> Mountague, three Tim-alley London wall.</item>
                  <item>Alice Ruſe at <hi>Mr.</hi> Hudſon Martins-lane.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mrs.</hi> Brooks at the ſame <hi>Mr.</hi> Hudſons.</item>
                  <item>The Baker Martins-lane end old Swan.</item>
                  <item>Cap. Cellke Pewterer Burchin lane.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Hatten, Winsforth-ſtreet.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Penny, Exciſe Office.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Pearpoint, Douins alley Biſhopſgate-ſtreet.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Ellis, Sherbone-lane Taylor.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mrs.</hi> Freeman at <hi>Mr.</hi> Cutlers Charter-houſe.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Neal, Cheapſide.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mrs.</hi> Seeton in Saint Thomas Southwark.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mrs.</hi> Broom, Frying pan Cheapſide.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mrs.</hi> Winfeild, Hellin down by <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xbridge.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Preſton, Swan-alley Coleman-ſtreet.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mrs.</hi> Tart, Bell alley Coleman-ſtreet.</item>
                  <item>
                     <pb n="108" facs="tcp:30746:68"/>
                     <hi>Mrs.</hi> Taverner of Hillindoron.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Brade School-maſter Crutchet fryers pumpe.</item>
               </list>
               <p>
                  <hi>I have ſet down a few names with their dwell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, to the end thou mayeſt here what they will ſay, and this I will aſſure thee that they all have cauſe to ſpeak well, and ſo indeed they have done, and I think will do, otherwiſe thou maiſt believe I would never have ſet their names here; and if it were a thing neceſſary it were a ſmall matter for me in a little time to give thee ten for one; but theſe being ſcattered over the Town and at once come to mind while I am a diſpatch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this little book, I am willing without care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>funeſs to abide by their teſtimony, knowing well what I have commended whether men ſpeak well or ill in this matter, yet I muſt tell thee that ſome of theſe at</hi> Weſtminſter, <hi>and ſome at</hi> Limmehouſe <hi>I do not know, but their neighbors names them to me while I am a writing, others that I do know, and I do intreat thee to believe that it is no part of my labor to trouble my ſelf with names and peoples dwellings.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Now I will in as plain words as I can deliver unto you ſome choiſe Receits which I think have not ſeen the light, eaſily wrought, almoſt by any vulgar hand, which will be acceptable unto ſuch as are endued with love and goodwill, and do deſire the good of their neighbor.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:30746:68"/>
               <head>To draw the true Oyl of Amber, the ſam which I have uſed for many years with wonderful effect and benefit to the uſers, and the ſame of which I have ſpoken in this Book.</head>
               <p>TAke the Scruff of Amber what quantity you pleaſe (which you may buy at the Druggiſt) and beat it in a Morter groſly, then take a good new Brick, and beat it to powder likewiſe, of theſe equal weight, and mix them well toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther one a table, it is ready.</p>
               <p>Take a good Retort of glaſs and put on it a good coat of ſtrong lute made of blood, lome, hair, and ſharp ſand, and moiſten them with ſtrong Brian, lay it on all over the thickneſs of two half crowns, let it dry in the ſum, when its dry look well, and purge what is a miſs and it is ready, fill this three parts full of thy Brick and Amber, and it is ready to put into thy Furnace, make a Furnace with a grate, and lay a croſs bar of Iron eight inches above thy grate, ſet thy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tort in an earthen Diſh of aſhes or ſand upon this bar, let the noſe ſtand inclining ſo as what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denceth may run out, build up about thy Retort and keep an inch diſtance or more, and juſt at the top of thy Furnace, leave a vent ſo bigg as an egge may go in at it; note if thy vent be too ſtrait thou will be puzzled, but if too big then maiſt with tile ſhird make it leſs by laying it on the
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:30746:69"/>top, lay to it a receiver as bigg as the retort, ſee that all be dry and well fixed, then with a gentle fire of Charcole under thy grate make fire for twelve hours, thou wilt perceive thy work to ſweat, and a white wateriſhneſs to cleave unto the neck of thy Retort, and in thy Receiver, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue this degree of fire under thy grate in the aſh-pit for twelve hours or longer, till thou per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it to ſlack its working, then begin with final fire upon thy grate, govern thy work with care that it work not too fiercely, for then thou wilt endanger all thy work and break thy veſſels, and keep that heat till thou ſeeſt that it will work no more, and that as thou perceiveſt there cometh nothing, increaſe thy fire a little for three hours, and if thou perceive that it begin to ſend forth white fumes, keep that degree for ſix hours, and by this time thou maiſt be ſure that all the Fleg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is come off, then put in a Sea-cole finder or two, and ſo by degrees leave Charcole, and bring <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a thy fire with Sea-cole, it is for thy profit ſo to do, and by this time there is no great danger, the Oyl is drunk up into the Brick, and thou with a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle increaſe of fire will make him diſcharge o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſpew it out again and yet keep it from flowing, ſo that thou wilt receive now a thick, black, or deep red Oyl, thou maiſt in twelve hours more ſetch off all thy Oyl without fear, for it doth require good and ſtrong fire, and with a tile give vent at the top which thou laidſt on in the beginning of thy work, let all cool together as it ſtands, and then take off thy Oyl and have a clean retort rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and pour it thereinto, and if thou wilt
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:30746:69"/>make a retort thy receiver which is better, then let it ſtand till thou art ready for it, take out the retort with the Capud, and clap into thy Furnace an Iron Kettle, and let the bottom ſeat upon the Iron Bar, and leave a large vent ſo bigg as a ſmall fiſt way be put down it; note this Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace will ſtand in any Chimney-corner (how lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ſoever it be) and with Lime and Hair fix the ſame handſomely, let the Kettle incline a little that it may c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Oyl the better; ſet into ſand thy Retort with the Oyl, let the noſe incline that the Oyle may deſcend or drop, let it ſtand half an inch in the bottom of ſand under the retort, fill about with the ſame ſand ſo high as the Oyl in the retort is, let not the ſand be either too ſharp or too fine, but of a middle greet, break the neck of another retort to go over this, if it be two inches wide, then if need not go over above one inch, but if it be but one inch wide, it had need go over three inches, lute it faſt about with Starch and paper; do thy work neatly like a work man, make a Sea-cole fire under gently un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till all the Flegm be come over, and after increaſe thy fire, Note, that if thou haſt wr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> well in thy fir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> dr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ght, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>und of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> thou wilt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>; repeat the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n the ſecond time; then h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t thou attained unto that Oyl as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> conſtantly ſell for four ſhillings the ounce, and ſometimes unto Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlefolks, and ſometimes for nothing: thou maiſt note that I have of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>h been thus rectified ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e ten times, that I never ſold
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:30746:70"/>any of it under twenty ſhillings the ounce. Thus I have given thee without any knot, the tree and plain way of my own work, which I have done of my ſelf without any guide or teaching, but as God hath taught me, and therefore know not what way other men take, accept them at my hand, therefore whereunto I have attained, with as much love as I tender it unto thee.</p>
               <p>Many concluſions I have tried, thinking to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance the worth of this Oyl, but it proved other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe; note that with fire thou canſt not wronge it, but therewith thou muſt ſeed it, and on fire it doth ſeed as naturally as thou feeds upon thy meat; many that would be accounted wiſe we choiſe in their fire, and dare not ſtir it up leaſt all theirwork ſhould be ſpoiled, but I am ſure they are fools and ſpoil their work for want of fire, for its clearneſs muſt not come with gentle fire but with oft rectifying, for if thou wilt take from him his fetid ſent, know that he is worth nothing fit for Ladies to play wiſh, but not to do them good, and becauſe many will diſdain me in this matter, I will take in one more with me, <hi>viz. Radolphus Glover,</hi> who ſaith as much; note that it is beſt to keep this Oyl upon the Flegma as its one mother, neither will the Oyle ſower ſo ſoon: I do think in my conſcience this Oyl comes the neareſt unto a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicin univerſal, if ſtrongly rectifyed ten or twelve times, and the opperator have judgement to keep and hold his Spirituouſneſs with ſtrong Lute, of any Oyl in the world, I have found it ſo and therefore ſo ſpeak.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="113" facs="tcp:30746:70"/>But becauſe many would fain make this Oyl, who live far off and cannot get veſſels, I will ſhew them a clowniſh way or two, that they may make a ſhift as I have done; but firſt note, I do proteſt I do not know out of my own hand where this Oyl can be had for mony; I have tried again and again that which is ſold for it, but I finde little of the truth there, I do not doubt but it is in divers hands to be had for mony, but where out of my own hand I know not, but that which is trade ſtuff is fetcht more out of the Firr-tree then out of the Scruff of Amber.</p>
               <p>Let the Country gentleman that lives far off, and loves them that God loves, <hi>viz.</hi> the poor, and would fain do them good, let him attend to what I ſay, take a long neckt jugg, the longeſt you can get, and cover it well with a ſtrong lute as I appointed thee to cover the retort withall, put in thy Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> confect therein, lay thy jugg upon thy Iron bar within thy Furnace, let the noſe lie out about one inch, let not the noſe incline, but look a little upward, ſet to another jugg whoſe mouth will go over his mouth, lute them faſt together, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed in all points as formerly, and thou haft thy deſire; and if thou wouldſt rectifie thoſe veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, be ſure that they be very well burned and glazed, otherwiſe thou maiſt go ſeek thy Oyle, or thou maiſt very well make thy firſt drought in Gawbers firſt Furnace if thou have any of them, or any Potter will make thee of them.</p>
               <p>I will yet commend unto thee another way, which is no ſable but what I have wrought with my own hand and of my own invention,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:30746:71"/>which I am ſure no ingenious man will diſpiſe.</p>
               <p>Take a large Funnel of Crooked-lane-plate, or of thin braſs, as my own is of that I have uſed the ſame way and for the ſame purpoſe; and cut ſo much of its ſmall end off as thou maiſt turn thy thum in it, get a Plate of thin Iron or Braſs, and fit it unto the top of thy Funnel ſo artly that it may lie a ſtraws breadth within the rim of thy Funnel, and if thou canſt not get a Plate conveniently, take an old Frying-pan bottom; if none of theſe, then an earthen diſh, but it will require a ſtronger fire upon i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, be careful that whatever it be that it fit thy Funnel or Tunel, then take another earthen diſh about two inches deep, or a little leſs, and let it be almoſt as wide as the Funel, put it into the Funnel, and take three or four ſix penny nails, put them betwixt the diſh and the Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel ſide, that there may be a ſtraws breadth or a nails bredth betwixt the Tunnel and the diſh, for the vapor to go down by, put thy Amber groſly beaten into the diſh, but be ſure that thy plate above do reach within an inch or inch and half at fartheſt; then lay over thy plate, then take a live Charcole and lay thereon which may warm the Plate, have ready chalk beaten to fine powder, and a ſtrong lye made of Bay ſalt, and thereof make thin ſtuff as if thou wouldſt make Pancakes, and with thy knife lay this lute upon the edge of thy Funel which will bind faſt the plate &amp; the Funnel that nothing can vapor that way, take thy Funnel and ſet it into a large glaſs with a narrow mouth, and lute it well with a Iinnen cloth and ſome of thy lute,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:30746:71"/>and ſet thy glaſs where thou wilt in thy window or one thy table; it is great pleaſure to behold this working, thou maiſt govern it as thou wilt by thy increaſe or decreaſe of fire; this I have done and it is ſpeedy, eaſie, and delightful, and almoſt without charge, onely note thy Oyl comes very thick; clean all thy veſſels with warm water and ſoap, and then thou maiſt rectifie therewith; thou muſt take heed to blow away the aſhes, that the heat may take the Iron plate under it more aptly, the gentlier thou doſt fire, the better will thy work be.</p>
               <p>Of this Oyl if a vollum were writ of its pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and vertue, it would be ſhort of what is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in it; I will content my ſelf with giving thee two or three inſtances, leave thee to judge of it as it ſeems good unto thee.</p>
               <p>At the beginning of theſe unnatural wars, I think about ſeventeen or eighteen years ago (for ſo long I have uſed it) I my ſelf being extream week even as water, languiſhing by degrees, after a ſore fit of ſickneſs, which held me from Barthol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mew-tide unto Shrove-tide; and for near ſeven years, paſſing my days in as great affliction as might be and go upright, nothing that I could take doing me any good, able to digeſt no whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome food; and if I had gone the length of Tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er-ſtreet, it was pains enough for me to lie on the bed all the day after it, indeed having in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward peace I did long for death, but it fled away as God would have it; I knew not what I ailed, onely whole nature waſted and ſpent, and being deaf I imployed a man to ſerreng my ear, I found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:30746:72"/>under his hand four times, that they thought I ſhould then have dyed: the man told me I was the weakeſt man that ever came under his hand, willed me to get good Oyl of Amber, and drink three or four drops in the morning faſting, and he would warrant my recovery, I inquired what it was, and till I came unto <hi>Hans Honger</hi> in White-chappel the Hungarian, I could not learn its vertue, he commended it as one of the moſt ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute things in the world, he prepared me one ounce, for which I gave him ten ſhillings (and if I had given him ten pounds he had deſerved it) I took three dtops as I was directed, and two mornings it purged and no more, but brought me to a right order, <hi>viz.</hi> once in a day, but before I had I know not how many ſtools in a day, and alſo made water almoſt at ever poſt through weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but in three weeks or a months time I was renewed from head to heal, and was like a boy of fourteen years old no ground could hold me<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> even at once releaſed of all the ſore burdens and oppreſſions that I lay under, which did much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maze moſt that knew me and I told them with what, although few would believe it; this rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is true, praiſed be God for this Oyl as a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed inſtrument thereof, for preſently I broke wind, began to feel an appetite and digeſt that which I did eat which was happy effects to me, that for ſome years knew I not what it ment, and God ſo ordered it, that at that very time I fell in with a <hi>French</hi> Emperick which was ſervant unto the Prince of <hi>Orringe,</hi> and from the time I have labored in this art of Alchimy.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="117" facs="tcp:30746:72"/>A child being near death with Convulſion-fits, its father, mother, grandmother coming into th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Country where the child was at nurſe intending to bury it before they went home to <hi>London,</hi> the child having had thirty fits, ſome black and ſome white, nothing could interpoſe; I deſired them to annoint the breaſt with ſome of this Oyl, and indeed it was the firſt draught onely, it ſtopt the fit coming, and the child had no more fits while ſhe had it to nurſe, unto their great aſtoniſhment, the Nurſe ſaid to me, that if I would have aſked at that time five pound a drop, I might have had it, but eighteen pence did ſerve the turn.</p>
               <p>Another time I did uſe to go oft unto a friends houſe where one lay ſick of the Peſtilence, I fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cied with my ſelf not to be afraid, neither can I ſay I was afraid, but ſo it was that I felt ſomething riſe and ſwell under my right arm, I let it alone two or three days, till at laſt it was ſo bigg that I could not get my arm unto my ſide as I was wont, and to my thinking it was as bigg as an egg, and begun to be ſore; I then had two ſorts of Oyl of Amber, one that was fine to drink, and another ſort that was courſe to annoint; I drank my por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the beſt, and then I called for my courſer ſort as I was in bed, and with my left hand an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed under my arm, and while my hand was upon it, it did avoid the place and fell under my ſhort ribs, I followed it with Oyl upon my ribs, and while my hand was on it, it leaped up un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der my arm again, I to it again under my arm with more Oyl, and while my arm was on it, it went I know not whether, the next morning I
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:30746:73"/>felt a little pain upon the contrary ſhoulder, and thus it went away and I heard no more of it, bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be God for his goodneſs and mercy unto me.</p>
               <p>I was once almoſt forced to viſite a Gentleman who was lame of the Gout, I left him Pills, and gave him of this Oyle to annoint his feet; this man neglected his Pills, onely annointed with this Oyl, he told me the next day he was in eaſe, and his foot and legg all alike ſore; this man with one or two Pills and this Oyl was ſo well as I obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved him he ran after me to open his door to let me out, and ſo at once was well of his lameneſs; this is true, I have related.</p>
               <p>Many by drinking this Oyl onely have voided many ſtones and much gravel when drunk is White-wine; I do uſe in Feavors to rubb my ſelf all over with this Oyl and drink it inwardly, and do find the ready way to cure with my Pills, and although it be fire, for ſo is my Pills, yet do they quickly extinguiſh an unnatural fire, as all find that uſe them, thanks be to God for it.</p>
               <p>I never knew Convulſion ſtand with it, but it is ready help, as far as I have proved, and as profitable for any ach of limbs whereever, nay I have known when able Doctors have concluded of nothing but death, where extream vomiting and tearing of limbs have been, being left, I have then cauſed the patient to be rubbed all over with this Oyl with a warm hand, which inſtantly hath cauſed ceaſe of pain, and ſuch breaking wind as is not to be credited, and forthwith health hat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> followed, this I have ſeen with my eyes, bleſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="119" facs="tcp:30746:73"/>be God for it. I leave it to Gods bleſſing in thy hand; I think to ſpeak no more of it, this book having already exceeded my intention, you may ſafely annoint a little child of a month old or younger if you have the true Oyl; yea as ſoon as it is born without danger, and I have known it given inwardly at ſixteen weeks old without danger, it is altogether diſcorſive and not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractive, and therefore ſafe and profitable for women that have Cankers in their Breſts, as I have known ſome cured with my Pills and this Oyl, praiſed be God for it; but I am weary of writing being very burthen ſome unto me. I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but further add that till I knew my Pills I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver knew the like for all grieſs whatever that took their root from wind and Rhums, it break wind apparently ſenſible twenty four hours from off the ſtomach.</p>
               <p>I will alſo here commend to the another which I am perſwaded may truely be accounted brother unto the Oyl of Amber, for I have much uſed it, and found it for all inward applications no whit inferior unto it; this thou maiſt, know, for it is not any part of my deſign to deceive thee, that I have found that if I did drink Amber above four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen days or three weeks, then its vertue would be gone, then have I left it off and drank this Oyl I ſhall now ſpeak of as long, and then the Oyl of Amber would come freſh as at firſt in ſtrength and vertue, thou maiſt note alſo that the Oyl of Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber if you take too much of it in hot weather will produce faintings, which this will not, further note, I never durſt uſe this Oyl outwardly,
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:30746:74"/>but the Oyl of Amber with great faſty.</p>
               <p>Of this Oyl I never read in all my life, nor ever heard of any that ever did make any uſe of it but my ſelf, and my one reaſon led me to it contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plating one the ſubject, could not but believe, there was real worth in it, as I by experience have truely found, and this Oyl I call the Oyl or Spirit of Pine, for ſo indeed it is, for Tar is made of the Pine-tree, as <hi>Johnſon</hi> reports; I know nice noſes will ſnuffel at this Oyl as a thing moſt deteſtable; I do is this as in other things admire the depth of the wiſdom and goodneſs of God, who puts honor upon thoſe things men moſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſe, but I being all my life put hard to it for the preſervation of my health have laid phantaſtical humors aſide, and ſeriouſly ſearched into the bleſſing of God hid and covered even in diſpiſed things; and truely I cannot ſay I have labored in vain, and indeed the benefit of this one as to health makes amends for an hundred abortives or errors.</p>
               <p>Take therefore in the name of God what quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of Tar thou pleaſeſt, and put it into a retort w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll lut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d take like quantity of Bay-ſalt, put it into a new earthen veſſel, make a good fire of Charcole about it, which is called a Wheel-fire of S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>tat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> and let thy Salt ſtand meanly red till it will crack no more, and that is called Decrepitating, beat this Salt to powder while it is warm in a ſtone Morter, and then with a wide Funel power it upon thy Tar which thou put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Retort, let all together fill thy retort two thirds, ſet the retort in the palm of thy hand, and
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:30746:74"/>mix them well by ſhaking of them together, place this retort upon the Iron bar eight inches above thy grate in a diſh of ſifted aſhes, as is taught in the drawing of the Oyl of Amber, proceed with it in all points as with the Oyl of Amber, onely at the laſt give violent fire for twelve hours, thou ſhalt receive three ſubſtances, <hi>viz.</hi> in the bottom of thy glaſs thou ſhalt receive a white Balſom, which is of unknown worth and vertue, as to my ſelf I ſpeak, the leaſt heat diſolves it, but I never made no experiment with it, but gave it to a friend which uſed to handle hard tools, and he had a corn for divers yeers in one of the joynts of his finger which was a daily grief and pain unto him; he annointed it with this balſom, and it did ſwell and riſe, he took a ſharp knif and did cut off what did riſe up, and then did annoint a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, it made it to riſe again, he cut it again, and then did annoint again, and it did ſwell and riſe again, this labor he continued till the corn came perfectly out, and ſo remains unto this day, which is now at leaſt this ſeven years; I know no wiſe man that conſiders what I have ſaid but will grant that which hath power thus to work, can alſo go further when a wiſe man hath it in hand; above this Balſom thou wilt receive a ſour Flegm, I do not know <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ny thing it is good for, and above that thou wilt receive a deep red Oyl which ſeparate from this Balſom and Flegm, and that rectified once in aſhes, and a ſecond time in Balneo Maria; thus far I went with it and no further for my own uſe, and I found it precious above gold. There came a fat man to
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:30746:75"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="117" facs="tcp:30746:75"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="118" facs="tcp:30746:76"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="119" facs="tcp:30746:76"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="120" facs="tcp:30746:77"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="121" facs="tcp:30746:77"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="122" facs="tcp:30746:78"/>me once that was troubled with ſtrange fits and would beat himſelf and foam at mouth, and when any thing did over charge his ſpirits, he would fall into thoſe fits; I gave him ſome of this ſpirit of Pine, and willed him to drink four, five or eight drops and more as he found it work, and that he could bear it, in a weeks time or a little more he ſent me word he was cured, I willed him to proceed for ſometime however, and one morning after he had drunk this Oyl, going a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong his neighbors, they ſmelt a ſtrong ſmell, at laſt they ſaid it was like Tar, he fancied I had given him ſomewhat made of Tar, was angry with me, chooſing rather to have his fits ſtill, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then take any thing of Tar; I think it is very fit this man ſhould keep his fits ſtill, onely I am afraid he hath ſome fits more then doth him good; the abundant mercy from heaven is manifeſt in the freedom of nature to all men, which offers her treaſures free without price, and God gives wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom to men to ſearch it out, and happy is that man whoſe heart is ſet open and free to do good imitating God and nature in their bountuous gifts; and as palpable is that mans folly who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prives himſelf of thoſe bleſſings freely offered un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him; and thrice more wretched is that man who withholds thoſe mercies from mankind, unto whom the higheſt hath freely granted them, for what have I or another that we have not receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and wherefore have we received, but to fullfill the ends of the giver, miſerable is that man that wants that witneſs in heaven and in his own conſcience; the bleſſing that I have receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:30746:78"/>in the taking of my Pill and in the giving it to others hath hindred me from making thorow proof of this Oyl and Balſom, I have given thee a plain receipt, and leave thee to Almighty God in the uſe of it, I know no more but to drink it in the morning two hours before meat, it break wind upward all day and cauſeth appetite, digeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth meat, and where theſe are there will not want ſtrength, ſo I write, becauſe ſo I have found by good experience; note, drop it upon a ſpoonful of Ale or Beer &amp; handſomely throw it down that thou touch it not, nor let the ſpoon touch it, ſo will you ſmell of it either not at all or very little, and the like for oyl of Amber, but when you belch you will taſte it, hardly elſe; I know the ſcornful will not touch it, but the pained will be glad to uſe thoſe things that doth them eaſe.</p>
               <p>Now I will plainly give thee a plain receit which hath been kept up as a great treaſure, and ſo indeed it is, as I thing no man of any judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment but will ſo judg it, I cannot ſpeak of my own knowledge much of it, but my good friend from whom I have it hath been for many years reliev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by it, when other means failed him, and he being ſatisfied with my preſſing deſires to do good, freely gave it me to that end, and I free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly give it you, it will ſpeak for it ſelf, it is of very inconſiderable preparation and yet of great effect, and thou maiſt prepare as much in few hours as will contain one thouſand doſſes, I know there are many good Gentlemen and Gentlewo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men which deſire to do good unto their poor neighbor; I intreat them attend, to this, I have
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:30746:79"/>done it, it is ſo eaſily done, as it deſerves not the name of a Chymical preparation: I alſo have known it ſafe and profitable, and worketh ſo ſweetly as indeed it is a Medicin to be deſired.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To prepare Antimony.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take one part of Antimony, and ſix parts of the beſt India Salt-peeter, pound them together and ſerce them thorow a hair ſive, take a ſtrong cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible three ſquare, and let it ſtand clean in a ſtrong ſire of Charcole (have a ſpoon tied unto a ſtick) put in a ſpoonful and it will burn, but in more and more as it burneth till the cruſible is full, take a clean Tobaco pipe with the little end ſtir it well, let it boil and ſtir that till you are ſure it will ſparkle no more, have a Braſſe or Iron Morter clean ſtand by you, and with your Tonges, take up your cruſible &amp; empty it into the Morter, ſet it again in the fire, and go on as at firſt, untill you have done all that you intend to do for that time, have a care to keep ſtrong fire, it ſhould be upon a grate that it may be ſtrong bring this unto ſine powder, and ſear it thorow a Lawn five, and it is prepared for your uſe. Note, that if it do not fire as you do ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect, touch it with a live coal and ſet it on fire.</p>
               <p>Antimony thus prepared, is depurated of all its fecis and poiſonous qualities, looſing utterly its maligne heat; it purgeth copiouſly without trouble and moleſtation, all groſſe, cold and Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarous humors, and openeth all ſtopped paſſages.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="125" facs="tcp:30746:79"/>
                  <hi>To prepare Scamony.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take of the beſt Scamony what quantity you pleaſe and beat it to powder, and ſerce it, have ready a Tobacco drier, and put upon it a ſpungy thin brown paper, take your Embers and ſtrow in Brimſtome into the fire, hold over the Scamo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, ſo that the fumes of the Brimſtone may take thorow the paper, and when you perceive that it ſticks unto the Paper but as thick as a half crown or ſhilling, caſt off the reſt upon a clean Paper, &amp; with a ſpoon ſcrape off what ſticks upon the paper for it is prepared, then put on again the powder of Scamony, and caſt into your fire more powder of Brimſtone till you perceive that ſome doth ſtick unto your paper, then caſt off the looſe powder and ſcrape off with a ſpoon as formerly, and this work you muſt repeat untill all your Sca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony have been ſcrapt off in like manner, then is it all prepared, but you muſt be ſure to take it off as ſoon as your can, leaſt your Scamony quite looſe all its vertue, as it will if you ſume it too much with the Brimſtone.</p>
               <p>Scamony thus prepared, is good againſt chollar and all thin hot humors, having in it neither ſavor nor ſmell, &amp; purgeth very eaſily &amp; without pain, which is corrary unto all other preparations.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The preparation of the cream of Tartar is ordinary, or the Cryſtals of Tartar to be had at any Drugiſt uſed in this Portion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Note that all theſe three is to be kept cloſe in fine powder ſeverally in glaſs-bottles.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="126" facs="tcp:30746:80"/>The greateſt doſſe for men; Antimony ten grains, Scamony fourteen grains, Tartar eight grains.</p>
               <p>The ordinary doſſe for men; Antimony nine or ten grains, Scamony eleven or twelve grains, Tartar ſix grains.</p>
               <p>The leſſer doſſe for men; Antimony fix grains, Scamony nine grains, Tartar five grains.</p>
               <p>For children betwixt ſeven and fourteen; An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timony ſeven or eight grains, Scamony five or ſix grains, Tartar three grains.</p>
               <p>For ſucking children and under ſeven; Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony two or three grains, Scamony four or five grains, Tartar three grains.</p>
               <p>To children give it with Sugar or ſome ſweet liquor, but to others as you pleaſe, if the Ague or diſeaſe ceaſe not at the firſt time, give it again four or five times, ever diminiſhing the quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity, becauſe the humors being once ſtirred they are the eaſier carried out; or if this portion do little the firſt day, then add more with diſcretion.</p>
               <p>This Powder you may uſe in all diſeaſes where humors do offend, either ſimple or compound, hot or cold, thin or groſs, clammy or windy, worms or extention above nature, it helpeth the ſtopping of the Flowers, the extention of the belly, the Dropſie in the beginning, Tertians, Quartans, and all ſharp Feavors, Choller, ill ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite, watching, thirſt, unquietneſs of mind; i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> helpeth the ſmall Pox and Pluriſie, it is not to be given where is great evacuation, but explition and fullneſs, it is much better then letting of blood.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="127" facs="tcp:30746:80"/>As for this portion of Phyſick rightly prepared and applied, I do believe conſidering the incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderableneſs of the preparation, the world never had any better, and I truſt in God I have done good ſervice unto my Country in bringing it to light, but if any be envious and is diſpoſed to cavil at it, all that I deſire of him is, that he would let it alone.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The true preparation of Crocus Martis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take the filings of Steel, what quantity you pleaſe, which you may buy at the Druggiſt, and put it in a broad earthen well glazed diſh, and ſprinkle it twice a day with ſtrong Vinegar, ſet it in the hot Sun, or cover it with another diſh, and let if ſtand upom Embers the night time, do this for one month, now and then ſtir it up and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain give it Vinegar till thou perceive it is all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ruſty, dry it well and beat it to ſine pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, then take a large glaſs body, and put it into it, and pour upon it diſtilled Vinegar (which muſt needs be ſo, otherwiſe thou wilt be as much troubled with the fecis of the Vinegar, as the thou wilt be with the damd Terra of the Crocus) let it be covered with a blind head (but firſt ſtir it well) ſet it in a Furnace of aſhes, or in Balneo Maria for four or five days, look that the Vinegar be deeply colloured red, if not ſhake it well to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether and let it ſtand in the fire till it is, then caſt off the clear into a clean veſſel, &amp; put on more Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negar, and this repeat till thou ſeeſt that it wil ting no more, take all thy Vinegar, and filter it thorow
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:30746:81"/>a double Cap paper (it will thorow by reaſon of the ſharp penetration of the Vinegar) then in a clean glaſs veſſel vapor all the Vinegar away, or with a head and receiver draw off thy Vinegar, and in the bottom thou wilt receive a fair red Crocus, but if thou wilt take the pains to repeat this labor again, that is, to diſſolve it in freſh Vinegar after thou haſt taken it out, and put in a clean new earth veſſel, and let it be gently cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cined for four or five days; and again deſolved, filtred, coagulated, thou wilt have a Medicin of more worth then gold; God be merciful to men and women, which in ſtead of this have only the ruſt of Iron put into their bellies; this Medicin is vaſt in its effects, but moſt omninous in all kind of Fluxes, let it content thee for this time I have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven thee a true receit.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To prepare the Sugar of Saturn.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take what quantity of lead thou wilt, and in a Iron Kettle melt it, and with a ladle of Iron ſtir it, this continue till all the lead be turned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an Aſh colloured powder; if thou, wilt (as I have done) add Bay ſalt, and continue it over a ſtrong fire till thou perceive it begins to attain a red collour, let it cool, put it into a clean veſſel not greaſie, and waſh out all the Salt well, and be ſure thou take all the Salt taſte away as by thy taſting, the laſt water thou maiſt perceive, then dry it well in a clean veſſel, then grind it well up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a Purſry with diſtilled Vinegar fit for to be uſed with a penſill, put it into a clean glaſs, cover it
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:30746:81"/>ſix fingers with diſtilled Vinegar, put on a blind head, and let it ſtand in aſhes or Balneo Maria three or four days, let all cool, thy Vinegar will be as ſweet as Sugar to thy taſte, cant of the clear, put on more diſtilled Vinegar, proceed as afore, till it will yield to thee no more ſwee tneſs; fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all as before of thy Crocus, vapor away till thou ſee a ſcum ariſe upon the top, let all cool, ſet it in a cool place or ſeller and it will ſhoot into moſt tranſparent Chryſtals which is called the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar of Saturn; note if it do not ſhoot into Cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtals thou haſt not vapored it enough away, when thou haſt took out thoſe Chryſtals, vapor the reſt and it will ſhoot Chryſtals afreſh, but if thou wilt take theſe Chryſtals and calcin them again, and then diſolve filter, congeal as is ſaid above it will yet excel, I have done it five or ſix times o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver; I cannot tell thee what this is good for; I know it is a great aſtringer, it is no part of my indeavor to make my ſelf wiſer then I am, let it ſuffice thee for this time that I have given thee a true receipt, for I dare not write beyond the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor of my hand, if thou canſt believe me, there is no deceit in what I commit unto thee; thou maiſt as I have done alſo work this out of Red-lead, hut it did like me better to work it out of lead it ſelf.</p>
               <p>I will now give thee a true and plain Receipt of one of the moſt potent ſtatelieſt Medicins that I think is attainable in the world.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The true preparation of the eſſence of</hi> Venus, <hi>commonly called</hi> Ens Veneris.</p>
               <p>Take from the Dunghill at the Refiners his dead
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:30746:82"/>head, commonly called <hi>Caput mortuum,</hi> that which is left of his Aqua Fortis, the blacker it is the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it is, for that is moſt burnt, put it into clean water and it will diſolve, ſtir it, let it fine cant off that water; but on freſh water, this repeat till you by taſte find no more ſharpneſs in it, keep that water together, dry well the red earth, take of this red earth what quantity thou wilt of Salt Armoniake equal parts, grind them well together, put them into a ſublimatory of good glaſs (note it may be done in earth) ſet it in ſharp ſand, begin with gentle fire, leave the hole open at the top onely, ſtop it with Cotton-wooll, that the wily Spirits of the Armoniak may go, elſe thou wouldſt break the veſſel; after twelve hours moderate fire, ſtop cloſe the hole above, increaſe fire, thou maiſt with thy hand on the veſſel know well whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thou give fire orderly; note that after twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty four hours, or thirty hours, thou canſt not hurt it with fire, let all cool, and with an Hares foot cleanſe off thy ſublimation, which will almoſt be on the collour of gold, take that which is ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limed, and weigh its weight of freſh Ens well ground together and ſublime it again, and this work thou muſt repeat four time always upon freſh Ens, before thy work be perfect; if thou dealeſt honeſtly with this preparation, which thou maiſt do in a matter of 10 or 12 days; there needeth little other Phyſick, three or four grains drank in white wine or in any proper Vehicle, always ballancing a proportion by the ſtrength and weakneſs of the patient; this is a true receit as I have done it, let if ſpeak for it ſelf; but I did not paſs all the ſublimations at once, having no
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:30746:82"/>preſent occaſion for it, I have ſeen this ſo glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous as to my thinking it hath exceeded gold; God Almighty proſper that man that ſtrives to excel in well-doing. Now take all thy water and filter it very clean and vapor it away, and thou wilt receive a conſiderable quantity of fixed ſalt white and good, put it into a ſtrong cruſible, and calcine it in a reverberatory for ſix hours, have care that thy heat do not make it flow, but let it be meanly red hot, then diſſolve it in diſtilled rain water, filter it, vapor away the water, it is abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly fairer then it was at firſt; note thy water muſt be twice diſtilled which is beſt done in quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity in a Copper Still with a Serpentine Refrige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory; in this work let dirt ſooner fall into thy eye then into thy work, then calcine again a third time and proceed as above, thou haſt a Medicine of great force, but if thou wilt repeat this work till thy Salt will yield unto thee no more Fecis, I dare not tell thee what I think it will do, I know thou art haſty with me, and demands what this fixed ſalt is good for, and my anſwer is as ready (go look) I cannot tell, but if thou wilt know what a fixed Medicin is good for look amongſt the Cronical of fixed diſeaſes which the Galliniſt counts uncurable, thou canſt not knock down an Ox with a ſmall Mallet, the remedy muſt over ballance the diſeaſe. Note, aſter this order you may almoſt gain the Salt of any thing, I therefore have write this.</p>
               <p>Undoubtedly no greater pleaſure can be had on earth in earthly things, then to be buſily im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in the curious purſuing of theſe things<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:30746:83"/>do therefore account my ſelf moſt happy, whoſe good hap it is next to the true fear, love, and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of God, to be ſwallowed up in the daily pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuance hereof; above all things ſee that thou a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict thy ſelf to be neat and cleanly in thy work; if thou knoweſt any thing in Alchimy, thou muſt know that with patience thou muſt work to take a few grains of the excremental parts, out of an ounce of the ſubſtantial parts, and it may be work long, and throw all away and begin a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, and this without change or reluctance of mind, being fully reſolved to work ever if thou ever meaneſt to ſpeed, its profitably miſcarried, if thou thereby art humbled, elſe thou wilt not be taught, God reſiſts the proud, but gives grace and teacheth the humble; therefore give time with patience, for that is of God, but haſt and unpati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is of the devil, the greateſt maſtery is the well governance of the regiment of fire, beſure that thou haſt Vulcan well yoaked in his own fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and ſee well that his bellows be not too big, onely ſtudy to make Volatil that which is fixt, and to fix that which is Volatil, and all this after due cleanſing, if thou canſt ſo deal with this ſalt thou wilt find bread; thou wilt never want matter if thou haſt this power, he onely is happy whom God teacheth, his true fear is the beginning of wiſdom, them he teacheth the way they ſhall go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> be not curious beyond nature. I my ſelf for ſome years paſt have much exceeded, following the Chimaerais of my own head, ſoar not to things too high and beyond thee, remember the ſaying of one of the chief Pillars in Phyſick; Art is
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:30746:83"/>long, life is ſhort, know God is in heaven, and thou on earth, thou canſt not fathom his depths in the leaſt natural thing; how canſt thou then comprehend him who fills all things? Be not of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended becauſe I am bold with thee, tis becauſe I love thee; I cannot but improve the tallent be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed, and ſo I ſhall leave it with thee, if thou counts me a fool, I care not for if, I know it well, I am contented, if I add a tittle to thee it is that which I deſire, no mans goodneſs can add any thing to God, he already is perfect therein, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect harmony, perfect ſilence and reſt for ever in himſelf, to whom nothing can be added, but our goodneſs may be extended unto the men on the earth, to them that excel in vertue, I ſtrive there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after as I receive help, ſome of theſe receits can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be wrought by unpracticed hands; I can but give as I have received, good will excits and moves this offer, let it work likewiſe in thee to accept in what I have done weakly, be thou more ready to mend then find fault, if I have deſerved rebuke, I will accept it from thee in any language with thanks.</p>
               <p>I will now deliver thee in as plain words as I can, a moſt ſtately Receit, which I have wrought and given many ſcores of times with great ſucceſs</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The preparation of the Salt of Mars, ſalt of Steel, ſo called.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Take what quanity of Oyl of Vitriol thou pleaſeſt, and put it in an open Glaſs, or in a well glazed veſſel, ſet it upon a ſtool in a Chimney,
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:30746:84"/>put into it for each pound of Oyl one ounce of Salt Jem or Stone Salt beaten to fine powder, take the filings of Steel, and with a ſpoon ſprinkle upon the Oyl, and it will foam, boil and fret, have care thou be not too haſty, for then will it boyl over, continue this ſhaking in of the powder of Steel ſo long that thou perceive it to be all dry and hard, and will foam and fret no more, then ſet it in a ſand Furnace and dry it very well, that it be hard, and like a ſtone almoſt for hardneſs; bring this to fine powder, have a good quantity of water warm, and ſprinkle this powder there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and keep it ſtirring with a ſtick, otherwiſe it will knit to a ſtone in the bottom; filter this wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, put on more, repeat this putting on of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter till it be no more ſharp, let all be clean filtred, and vapor away the half or above, and it will ſhoot into tranſparant green Chryſtals very fair Vitriol, vapor yet again and it will ſhoot again, if thou haſt vapored enough of it away, take all the Chryſtals or Vitriol, and lay it abroad on a well glazed diſh, and ſet it in a ſtove or in the Sun in his ſtrength, and it will break into white pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; then put it into a clean diſtilled water, and it will diſſolve, filter it again, coagulate it into Chryſtals, it will ſhoot into far more fairer Vitriol then the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>irſt; this ought to be repeated ſo oft till it will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>et no more fecis, but at this twice it will be in a very honorable condition, and ſo far I have gon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, dry it well, it will be a white yellow powder, and keep it cloſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>opt in a glaſs for thy uſe; of this powder ten or twelve grains in the morning, and ſo for a week toge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is profit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:30746:84"/>to bring the Flowers, if drunk in good white wine, and ſtirring upon it, it ſometimes cauſeth vomiting, ſometimes purging, and ſometimes nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; it eaſeth the breaſt of ſtopping, helps Rickits and killeth worms, give to children three or four grains according to their ſtrength, it is a choice Medicin as I have proved.</p>
               <p>If thou would draw the Oyl of Vitriol thy ſelf take good Copperas, and in a new earthen pan boyl it dry; beat it to powder, put it in long necks, lute faſt &amp; draw it with judgement, as much as the Oyle of Amber is, ſome calcine it red firſt as I have done my ſelf, but for this work it need not ſo be done.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A true Receit of the powder of Sympathy, or the Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pathetical powder, made of Roman Vitriol, lately commended by Sir <hi>Kenelme Digby,</hi> but no plain Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit given which I here perform and freely give thee, knowing that there is none better.</head>
               <p>Take what quantity of Roman Vitriol thou wilt, diſſolve it in rain water, but put no more wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then will diſſolve it, always leaving ſome un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſſolved in the bottom, filter it as clean as poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible (let thy water be milk warm in thy diſſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) put it in a clean glaſs-body ſet in ſifted aſhes, and give it gentle heat, ſo that it never exceed the heat of thy belly, and in that heat let it vapor away till thou ſee it covered with a Catecula or thin ſcum or cream, then withdraw thy fire, let it ſland unmoleſted for three days, covering it well that nothing fall into it, then with a glaſs ſpoon
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:30746:85"/>or wooden ſpoon, take out the coagulated Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triol which is ſhot into fair green Chryſtals, then kindle thy fire again, and with like degree con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue till it be covered with a ſcum, withdraw thy fire again, let it ſtand other three days, take up again with a wooden ſpoon the coagulation; this you muſt repeat untill thou haſt the ſubſtance of thy Vitriol again, but freed from much of its filth; take all thy Vitriol which thou haſt gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſpread it on a glaſs or well glazed diſh in the heat of the Sun, or in defect thereof a clean ſtone of equal heat with the ſcum, and take heed thou doſt not exceed, for then wilt thou leeſe its vital parts which are quickly volatil and ſubtil, neither wilt thou attain any more greenneſs on thy Vitriol which when thou perceiveſt, begin a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, all is loſt, underſtand thy degrees of fire bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but if you give it its dew heat then will it break into a white powder, and the greenneſs which is its life will obſcure and hide it ſelf, then take it again, and in rain water diſtilled twice, diſſolve it as at firſt. Now mark, I bring thee again to thy beginning, and there I leave thee; for this work thou ſhouldſt repeat ſo oft and ſo long till it ſet no more fecis to thee, but conclude when thou wilt, thou ſeeſt what Sir <hi>Kenelum Digby</hi> doth write, <hi>viz. The Antients did uſe this Vitriol in its groſſe body beat to powder.</hi> I have here given thee ſo true away as I know none better, for in this thou bringſt it beyond what is fit to be written, and doth hold, preſerve and keep all its power, both ſpiritual, ſympathetical, fixt and Volatil.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="137" facs="tcp:30746:85"/>If thou haſt ears I have ſaid much, what is wanting unto thee, conſult with <hi>Van Helmount, Aſwall Groby,</hi> Mr. <hi>Boulton,</hi> and Sir <hi>Kenelme Digby.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Being moved fully with good will, I will here give thee one receit more, the like I confidently affirm never ſaw the light for the good of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, and whoſoever will be perſwaded upon my faith and credit always to have it truely and faithfully prepared, may with much confidence ceaſe from all other things in the world, &amp; quietly commit themſelves and relations into the hands of Almighty God in the uſe of this with quietneſs and reſt, and I ſpeak boldly if this prove ſhort, to correct thy Feavor and heal thy diſeaſe, and hath not power to purge thy blood, and throw all out that is noxtious unto thy vital Spirit, let thy ailes be what they will, look not for it to be done in this world; I pitty thy fugitive mind and pray for thee when I ſee thee hunt from one man to another, and from one Medicine unto another, which is indeed the harbinger of death; but if thou art admoniſhed from thy vain worſhipping of men to fall off, and with a quiet mind pray and uſe this and therein reſt waiting upon God: I am ſully poſſeſt and perſwaded in my conſcience it is ſufficient for thee, and if thou as blind as Bayard cry out of the ſtrong poiſon of the ſubjects, <hi>viz.</hi> Poppey and black Hellebor, thou ſnarling fool ceaſe and firſt learn the power of Salt of Tartar, and do not bewray thy folly and ignorance till thou haſt proved its power, leaſt thou give juſt occaſion of perpetual laughter unto thoſe whom experience hath taught &amp; informed, I do confeſs
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:30746:86"/>I can exempt no Medicin in the world but my Pill and Antidote, whoſe receits I may not at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent here give thee; and this I proteſt unto thee, that if thou haſt made a right uſe of this that I have here in full and plain words taught, I ſhould have ſmall hope with any thing I am made Maſter of, to help and cure where this cannot; and therefore as thou haſt reſpect unto thy life conſider what I now teach thee, I ſay I teach thee under God, for I have not had the leaſt light or guide from any breathing, or from any book, but God Almighty my Lord and good Maſter hath been my guide, and therefore I with joy do aſcribe unto him all praiſe and thanſgiving for ever.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rec.</hi> Take one pound of the beſt White Rhen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Tartar, and one pound of India Salt-peeter, bring them to powder in a ſtone Morter &amp; ſerce them thorow a Hair Sive, take a Pipkin that was never uſed, &amp; ſet it upon Charcole, let the bottom heat as the coals do kindle, put in a ſpoonful of this powder, if the bottom be read hot it will burn, put in one ſpoonful after another till all be burned, it is then for this work prepared, &amp; if thou haſt wrought well thou wilt have of a white Salt but yellowiſh, ſeventeen ounces again of thy two pounds. Take half a buſhel of White-lime, put it in a clean tubb, and put on it fair water, that the water may cover it four inches, let if ſtand all night, take two gallons of this water and put in it thy ſalt, and it is prepared for thy work, then take one pound weight of Poppe-leaves good and red, newly gathered as near as thou canſt, ſtamp them and put them into thy prepared wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:30746:86"/>take alſo one pound of Juniper berries, and do likewiſe alſo take one pound of black Hellebor which thou maiſt buy at the Druggiſt for a ſmall matter, beat it groſly and put it into the reſt, ſtir all very well, let them ſimper upon a fire twenty four hours in a glaſs-body, or in a Tin veſſel or Pewter, but let it be cloſe covered, then drive all through a Hipocris bagg and its prepared for thy uſe, drink of this three or four ſpoonful in White-wine and Sugar, but give more or leſs as the patient is ſtrong or weak, to weak children half a ſpoonful or a ſpoonful with Wine or Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar; note thou maiſt do what thou wilt with this if thou knoweſt how to apply it for thy health; I deſire thee whatever thou art to praiſe God for this, the like I believe is not made manifeſt for the preſerving of thy health againſt all diſeaſes, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, Feavors, Surfeits, this will not fail thee of relief let thy pains be what they will, nor of cure if God permit; if thou haſt patience and will give it time, I have from my conſcience ſpoke my belief grounded upon reaſon and experience, and freely give it thee, beſeeching God to bleſs it to thee and inlarge thy heart as mine is inlarged, that is, that thou maiſt do for thy neighbor as I now do for thee, preſenting nothing in this or any thing about it but the labor of my hand, and what I daily put into my own belly; and let me further tell thee I had much wreſtling with my ſelf as in the preſence of God, before I could prevail upon the gain-ſaying that was in me, to draw ſo nigh thee for thy unvaluable benefit, for if thou con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidereſt the things are eaſie attained, every ditch
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:30746:87"/>offering the ſome of them, and the preparation ſo trinial, that there is as much art to make a meſs of pottage; in this above all other I have deſerved well at thy hand, if thou haſt a heart to improve it, neither do I doubt, although many will be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry and ſnatter at it, but this entrance which I have given in this receipt will ſtand while the world indures and get ſtrength, and my memory held in honor, for ſo good ſervice in it. This book hath ſwelled beyond my intention, yet I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to give thee one receipt or two more in few words, and ſo I for this time ſhall reſt, praiſing God who helped me before I go out of this world to perform ſome real ſervice for the good of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind in general.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To make the drink that is now much uſed, called Coffee,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Coffee Berries is to be bought at any Dru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſt, about three ſhillings the pound, take what quantity you pleaſe, and over a Charcole-fire in a old pudding-pan or frying-pan, keep them al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways ſtirring untill they be quite black, and when you crack one with your teeth, that it is as black within as it is without, yet if you exceed, then do you waſt the oyl which onely makes the drink and if leſs then will it not deliver his Oyl which muſt make the drink, and if you ſhould continue fire till it be white, it will then make no Coffee, but onely give you its ſalt; the Berry prepared as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove beaten and ſerced thorow a Lawn Sive is then fit for uſe.</p>
               <p>Take clean water and boil one third of it away
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:30746:87"/>what quantity ſoever it be, and it is fit for uſe.</p>
               <p>Take one quart of this prepared water, put in it one ounce of your prepared Coffee, and boil it gently one quarter of an hour and it is fit for your uſe, drink one quarter of a pint as hot as you can ſip it; note that inſtead of Coffee, take Engliſh Wheat and thou wilt find it in all points as good and as profitable for thee as I have wrought and proved it, and ſpeak it from knowledge, and I do from my heart bear witneſs to this drink as the beſt and ſafeſt for the health of mans body; and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I do know that it doth abate the fury or ſharpneſs of the Accrimony which is the gender of thoſe diſeaſes called Cronical, and although it doth want fermentation, yet hath it the true ſtrength of the grain if be well prepared, and doth in no wife ſume to intoxication for that it is unfermented, and undoubtedly thoſe which loves health will love this drink, and is an abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute enemy unto natures enemies, I had thought to have ſpoken much and from good grounds of the worth and benefit of this drink, but being al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready inlarged beyond intention, I am conſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to leave it for this time.</p>
               <p>I have wrote many things which will have an ungrateful taſte, yet of mighty force for thy health I cannot conclude this book but I muſt give thee one receipt more, which will be acceptable unto thy fooliſh fancy, that in truth thy appetite never taſted a more ſtately thing or higher cordial for health, and yet cheap and of very eaſie and vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar preparation, as followeth.</p>
               <p>Take twelve pound of Black-Cherries that is
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:30746:88"/>full grown and ſweet, break all their ſtones in a morter, put them in a Limbeck or in a ſmall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Stillers Still, put to them one gallon of fair Spring water, diſtill off again one Gallon or on gallon within a point; this water doth far exceed that which is commonly ſold for black-Cherry water, take all out and run it throw a Pulpring ſive, and waſh with clean water the ſtill or the Limbeck, and what runs thorow the Sive of it ſelf, keep to make thy Surrup of, the reſt drive thorow the Sive by force, that nothing be leſt but ſkin and ſtones, and that keep by it ſelf, for thy Surrop take the firſt that is thin and run thorow the Sive of it ſelf, put unto it for each pint two pound of ſweet ſented Lisborn Sugar, and put into one quart of Roſe water, and one quart of Sparmint water; boyl all at leaſt eight hours; Note that if from firſt to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſt the matter be not boiled twelve or fourteen hours it will not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer thy intention, but if thou wilt feed it with fire twenty four hours, thou therewith may do wonders; I have ſo wrought it and baked it o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver and over ſeveral times, and thou maiſt know that a Black Cherry is a ſubſtance unknown, and cannot by fire be made dry, but as ſoon as it is cold, it will draw to it ſelf a moiſt air, and will relent do what thou canſt, yet I have ſo fired him, or fed him with fire, that I could not touch it with my teeth, ſuch hath been its mighty force, and for obſtructions all have flown before it, and when I would, taking but a little more then ordinary it would looſe my belly, and give a ſtool or two, but if thou wilt make a Surrup of it without this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:30746:88"/>firing it will not then be worth an half pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, but will be only toothſome as other ordinary Sirrops is. I leave thee to judge of it as thou wilt, I know for my ſelf many years ago it was precious in its effects unto me, and from that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience I had of it, I now moved with good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will, commit it unto thee.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
